<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
   <bookinfo>
      <title>VR Juggler Portable Runtime</title>

      <subtitle>Programmer's Guide</subtitle>

      <copyright>
         <year>2003–2007</year>

         <holder>Iowa State University</holder>
      </copyright>

      <legalnotice>
         <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
         document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License,
         Version 1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software
         Foundation; with the Invariant Sections being <xref
         linkend="appendix.gfdl" />, with no Front-Cover Texts, and with no
         Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included in <xref
         linkend="appendix.gfdl" />.</para>
      </legalnotice>

      <releaseinfo>Verrsion 2.1</releaseinfo>

      <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
   </bookinfo>

   <preface>
      <title>Vaporous Programming</title>

      <para>For those developers new to the <ulink
      url="http://www.vrjuggler.org/vapor/">VR Juggler Portable
      Runtime</ulink> (VPR), VPR provides an cross-platform, object-oriented
      abstraction layer to common operating system features. VPR is the key to
      the portability of Gadgeteer, Tweek, VR Juggler, and other middleware
      written at the Virtual Reality Applications Center. It has been in
      development since January 1997, and it has grown to be a highly
      portable, robust tool. Software written on top of VPR can be compiled on
      IRIX, Linux, Windows, FreeBSD, and Solaris, usually without
      modification.</para>

      <para>Internally, VPR wraps platform-specific APIs such as BSD sockets,
      POSIX threads, Win32 threads, and Win32 overlapped I/O. Depending upon
      how it is compiled, it may also wrap the <ulink
      url="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/nspr/index.html">Netscape Portable
      Runtime</ulink> (<glossterm linkend="gloss.nspr">NSPR</glossterm>),
      another cross-platform OS abstraction layer written in C. By wrapping
      NSPR, VPR provides developers with an object-oriented interface and
      gains even better portability. These details are all hidden behind the
      classes that make up VPR, and users of VPR do not need to worry about
      platform-specific details as a result.</para>

      <para>VPR is basically a collection of utility classes. As such, the
      biggest part of using VPR is knowing the interface for a given class. In
      this book, we provide high-level information about various pieces of VPR
      in hopes of making VPR easier to use. The book itself is designed so
      that readers can focus on what they need to know about VPR classes. For
      example, someone who wants to learn about using the VPR thread
      abstraction can go straight to that part of the book (i.e., <xref
      linkend="part.multi-threading" />). Within each part, however, the
      chapters build up the concepts incrementally, so it is advisable, for
      example, to understand the basics of VPR I/O before trying to learn
      about the serial port abstraction.</para>
   </preface>

   <part id="part.io">
      <title>Input/Output</title>

      <partintro>
         <para>To begin, we will cover the components of VPR that will be used
         for I/O programming. This includes how to use VPR sockets and serial
         ports. We assume that the reader has at least some familiarity with
         operating system programming, in particular with serial device I/O
         and socket I/O.</para>
      </partintro>

      <chapter id="chapter.buffered.io">
         <title>Buffered I/O</title>

         <indexterm zone="chapter.buffered.io">
            <primary>input/output abstraction</primary>
         </indexterm>

         <para>One of the largest components of VPR is its I/O abstraction.
         All I/O classes (file handles, serial ports, and sockets) share the
         base class <classname>vpr::BlockIO</classname><indexterm>
               <primary>classes</primary>

               <secondary>vpr::BlockIO</secondary>
            </indexterm>. Reads and writes are performed using contiguous
         blocks of memory (buffers). This design provides an API that closely
         resembles that of the underlying operating system (with methods
         called <methodname>read()</methodname> and
         <methodname>write()</methodname>), but it is in contrast to
         stream-oriented I/O that is usually seen in C++. Streams could be
         written on top of the buffered I/O classes, but thus far, the need
         has not arisen. With this in mind, the design provides an API that is
         immediately familiar to programmers used to POSIX-based interfaces,
         but the API may seem clumsy to C++ programmers who are accustomed to
         using <type>std::ostream</type> and friends.</para>

         <para>Readers interested in the implementation of the I/O component
         of VPR are referred to <xref linkend="appendix.io.impl" />. We
         discuss the use of the VPR socket abstraction, and we provide some
         insight into how the abstraction is implemented. By providing some
         implementation details, it is our hope that the online API reference
         will be easier to understand and navigate.</para>

         <section>
            <title>Opening and Closing</title>

            <para>Opening and closing I/O devices is quite simple. There are
            two methods for performing these actions:
            <methodname>vpr::BlockIO::open()</methodname> and
            <methodname>vpr::BlockIO::close()</methodname>. However, at the
            <classname>vpr::BlockIO</classname> level, these methods are pure
            virtual (i.e., abstract), and thus, the implementation varies
            depending on the actual I/O device, be it a socket, serial port,
            or file descriptor. Regardless of the implementation, the
            preconditions for <methodname>vpr::BlockIO::open()</methodname>
            state that the device must not already be open. For
            <methodname>vpr::BlockIO::close()</methodname>, the device must be
            open before an attempt is made to close it.</para>

            <section>
               <title>Setting Attributes for Opening</title>

               <para>Prior to opening an I/O device, some attributes can be
               set. These in turn affect how the device is opened. In the
               general case of <classname>vpr::BlockIO</classname><indexterm>
                     <primary>classes</primary>

                     <secondary>vpr::BlockIO</secondary>
                  </indexterm>, the only attribute that is available
               determines whether the device will be opened in blocking mode
               or non-blocking mode. By default, all devices open in blocking
               mode, and in most cases, this is the desired mode.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Blocking Versus Non-Blocking</title>

               <para>The decision to use blocking or non-blocking I/O depends
               on the needs of the application or library being developed on
               top of VPR. While the decision can be made before opening the
               device, it can also be made after the device is open using the
               methods <methodname>vpr::BlockIO::enableBlocking()</methodname>
               and <methodname>vpr::BlockIO::enableNonBlocking()</methodname>.
               Typically, the blocking/non-blocking state should be set
               exactly once (either before or after opening the device). In
               some cases, it is not possible to change the state after a
               critical <quote>point of no return.</quote> Refer to <xref
               linkend="section.fixed.socket.blocking" /> for more information
               on this.</para>
            </section>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Reading and Writing</title>

            <para>Reads and writes occur using the
            <methodname>read()</methodname> and
            <methodname>write()</methodname> methods respectively. These
            methods are overloaded for common data structures that may be used
            to store the information being read or written. For example,
            strings are used frequently in I/O handling, so the type
            std::string can be used for easy management of string data. When
            reading <varname>n</varname> bytes, the
            <classname>std::string</classname> object will be resized
            internally by <methodname>read()</methodname> to ensure that it
            has enough room to store the full buffer. The same is true for the
            <methodname>read()</methodname> variant that takes a
            <classname>std::vector&lt;vpr::Unit8&gt;</classname> object
            reference. This overloaded version of
            <methodname>read()</methodname> is helpful when dealing in arrays
            of bytes. Of course, the lowest level variant of
            <methodname>read()</methodname> is the version that takes a
            <type>void*</type> buffer. In this case, the buffer pointed to
            must have at least <varname>n</varname> bytes of contiguous
            storage prior to calling <methodname>read()</methodname>.</para>

            <para>There is also a special method called
            <methodname>readn()</methodname> that guarantees that
            <varname>n</varname> bytes will be read. (The
            <methodname>read()</methodname> method only guarantees that it
            read <emphasis>at most</emphasis> <varname>n</varname> bytes.) As
            such, <methodname>readn()</methodname> is a blocking call, even
            when a non-blocking data source is being used behind the scenes.
            It will not return until all <varname>n</varname> bytes have been
            read or an error occurs while reading.</para>

            <para>Writing to an I/O object works as one might expect. The same
            overloads are available for <methodname>write()</methodname> as
            are available for <methodname>read()</methodname> and
            <methodname>readn()</methodname>. The buffer passed in to
            <methodname>write()</methodname> must be at least as big as the
            amount of data to be written (in bytes), or a memory access error
            can occur.</para>

            <tip>
               <para>Always make sure that the buffer size matches the amount
               of data to be read or written. Buffer overflows have long been
               a source of security problems in software, and they can be
               avoided by managing memory carefully.</para>
            </tip>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Statistics Collection</title>

            <indexterm>
               <primary>input/output abstraction</primary>

               <secondary>built-in statistics collection</secondary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>All the I/O classes in VPR have built-in statistics
            collection capabilities. By default, the code is not activated so
            as to prevent unwanted overhead. However, it can be enabled quite
            simply using the method
            <methodname>vpr::BlockIO::setIOStatStrategy()</methodname>. This
            method takes a single parameter, a statistics collection object,
            and invokes the correct methods whenever I/O occurs. Within the
            specific implementation, any form of statistics related to reading
            and writing of data may be collected.</para>

            <para>From the name of the method in
            <classname>vpr::BlockIO</classname>, we see the first indication
            that a Strategy pattern <xref linkend="ref.design.patterns" /> is
            used to implement the pluggable statistics collection code. All
            statistics strategy classes must derive from
            <classname>vpr::BaseIOStatsStrategy</classname><indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::BaseIOStatsStrategy</secondary>
               </indexterm>, and strategies can be mixed using the templated
            class <classname>vpr::IOStatsStratgeyAdapter&lt;S,
            T&gt;</classname><indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::IOStatsStrategyAdapter&lt;S,
                  T&gt;</secondary>
               </indexterm>. Currently, the only strategy class is
            <classname>vpr::BandwidthIOStatsStrategy</classname>, used for
            collecting information about bandwidth usage of a given I/O
            object.</para>
         </section>
      </chapter>

      <chapter id="chapter.vpr.sockets">
         <title>Sockets</title>

         <indexterm zone="chapter.vpr.sockets">
            <primary>socket abstraction</primary>
         </indexterm>

         <para>Socket programming can be a very difficult task, and the API
         used to write network code is difficult to understand in and of
         itself. The purpose of the VPR socket abstraction is thus two-fold:
         it abstracts the platform-specific API, and it aims to simplify the
         interface so that developers can focus on protocol
         implementations.</para>

         <note>
            <para>Readers not familiar with socket programming should consult
            a reference manual (<xref
            linkend="ref.unix.network.programming" /> is recommended). We do
            not attempt to explain the ins and outs of socket programming.
            Instead, we assume that readers are familiar with socket-level I/O
            and the ideas involved with various types of network
            communication.</para>
         </note>

         <para>The socket abstraction follows the concepts set forth by the
         <glossterm linkend="gloss.bsd.sockets">BSD sockets</glossterm> API,
         which was also the model for the Winsock API used on Windows. In VPR,
         two types of sockets may be instantiated: stream-oriented (TCP,
         <classname>vpr::SocketStream</classname><indexterm>
               <primary>classes</primary>

               <secondary>vpr::SocketStream</secondary>
            </indexterm>) and datagram (UDP,
         <classname>vpr::SocketDatagram</classname><indexterm>
               <primary>classes</primary>

               <secondary>vpr::SocketDatagram</secondary>
            </indexterm>). The helper class
         <classname>vpr::InetAddr</classname> makes use of Internet Protocol
         (v4) addresses easier. Built on top of
         <classname>vpr::SocketStream</classname> are two classes that make
         writing client/server code easier:
         <classname>vpr::SocketConnector</classname><indexterm>
               <primary>classes</primary>

               <secondary>vpr::SocketConnector</secondary>
            </indexterm> and
         <classname>vpr::SocketAcceptor</classname><indexterm>
               <primary>classes</primary>

               <secondary>vpr::SocketAcceptor</secondary>
            </indexterm>. Finally, VPR provides cross-platform data conversion
         functions (see <xref linkend="chapter.data.marshaling" />) to deal
         with endian issues.</para>

         <para>We begin our discussion by diving right into the common
         features of sockets, as collected in the class
         <classname>vpr::Socket</classname><indexterm>
               <primary>classes</primary>

               <secondary>vpr::Socket</secondary>
            </indexterm>. We assume that readers already have an understanding
         of the buffered I/O concepts (see <xref
         linkend="chapter.buffered.io" />) used in VPR I/O programming. The
         following sections cover datagram-oriented sockets and
         stream-oriented sockets respectively. We will conclude this chapter
         with a review of the high-level patterns implemented for simplifying
         the authoring of client/server architectures.</para>

         <section id="section.inet.address">
            <title>Internet Addresses</title>

            <indexterm>
               <primary>sockets</primary>

               <secondary>Internet addresses</secondary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>All socket code written using the VPR socket abstraction
            must use Internet Protocol (IP) addresses. The class
            vpr::InetAddr<indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::InetAddr</secondary>
               </indexterm> neatly abstracts the low-level details of using
            Internet addresses<footnote>
                  <para>The current implementation of
                  <classname>vpr::InetAddr</classname> only supports IPv4,
                  though support for IPv6 will be added when the need
                  arises.</para>
               </footnote>. This class encapsulates both the IP address and
            the port number. It manages all the endian issues and the lookup
            of host names as necessary.</para>

            <para>When constructed, a new <classname>vpr::InetAddr</classname>
            is initialized to the constant value
            <constant>vpr::InetAddr::AnyAddr</constant><indexterm>
                  <primary>constants</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::InetAddr::AnyAddr</secondary>
               </indexterm>. This value corresponds with the OS-level constant
            <constant>INADDR_ANY</constant>. Typically, either a host name, a
            port number, or both must be set after the object is constructed.
            Such details will vary depending on the application needs. The IP
            address can be set using a symbolic host name (which will be
            resolved through DNS queries) or using the human-readable
            <quote>dotted-decimal</quote> notation. The port number is set
            using the native byte ordering; it is converted internally to
            network byte order. It is also possible to set the host name and
            port number together in a single string that uses the format
            <quote>host:port</quote>. This format is convenient when the
            values for the host name and port come in as string values.</para>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Socket Commonalities</title>

            <indexterm>
               <primary>sockets</primary>

               <secondary>common features of</secondary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>At the lowest level, all sockets have several things in
            common. For example, all sockets must be opened before they are
            used, and they must be closed when communication is complete.
            During communication, data is read from and written to a socket,
            and reads and writes may be blocking (synchronous) or non-blocking
            (asynchronous). All sockets are bound to a local address, and
            <emphasis>connected</emphasis> sockets have a remote
            address<footnote>
                  <para>Unconnected sockets may send data to a different
                  destination at every write. They may also receive data from
                  any remote address.</para>
               </footnote>.</para>

            <note>
               <para>It is important to note that a socket does not have to be
               stream-oriented to be in a connected state. A datagram-oriented
               socket may be <quote>connected</quote> to a remote address so
               that it has a default destination. This alleviates the need to
               specify the destination address at every send.</para>
            </note>

            <para>These commonalities are collected into the class
            <classname>vpr::Socket</classname><indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::Socket</secondary>
               </indexterm>, which serves as the base interface for datagram-
            and stream-oriented sockets. The API for this class includes
            methods such as <methodname>open()</methodname>,
            <methodname>close()</methodname>, <methodname>send()</methodname>,
            <methodname>recv()</methodname>, and
            <methodname>connect()</methodname>. Note that
            <methodname>recv()</methodname> and
            <methodname>send()</methodname> are provided as analogues to
            <methodname>read()</methodname> and
            <methodname>write()</methodname> respectively. These are included
            because the BSD sockets API defines the system calls
            <function>recv</function>(2) and <function>send</function>(2), in
            addition to <function>read</function>(2) and
            <function>write</function>(2), for use with socket file
            descriptors. The extra methods are thus provided to give
            programmers already familiar with the BSD sockets API an easily
            recognizable interface.</para>

            <section>
               <title>Uses of <classname>vpr::Socket</classname></title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Socket</primary>

                  <secondary>polymorphism and</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>Instances of <classname>vpr::Socket</classname> cannot be
               created because the constructors are not public. Instances of
               the concrete types
               <classname>vpr::SocketDatagram</classname><indexterm>
                     <primary>classes</primary>

                     <secondary>vpr::SocketDatagram</secondary>
                  </indexterm> and
               <classname>vpr::SocketStream</classname><indexterm>
                     <primary>classes</primary>

                     <secondary>vpr::SocketStream</secondary>
                  </indexterm> can be used polymorphically as instances of
               <classname>vpr::Socket</classname> (and
               <classname>vpr::BlockIO</classname>, of course). Because the
               basic operations such as <methodname>read()</methodname> and
               <methodname>write()</methodname> are defined by the base class,
               using the concrete socket types polymorphically could be a
               convenient mechanism for mixing socket communication protocols
               in an application.</para>
            </section>

            <section id="section.fixed.socket.blocking">
               <title>Fixed Blocking State</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>sockets</primary>

                  <secondary>blocking semantics</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>Due to the semantics of sockets on Windows NT, the VPR
               socket abstraction contains a slight variation of the behavior
               that is available on UNIX-based systems. In Windows, once a
               call to <methodname>read()</methodname>,
               <methodname>write()</methodname>,
               <methodname>accept()</methodname>, etc., is made, the blocking
               state of the socket is fixed<footnote>
                     <para>UNIX-based systems allow the blocking state to be
                     changed from blocking to non-blocking or vice versa at
                     any time.</para>
                  </footnote>. That is, if the socket is a blocking socket, it
               will forever remain in a blocking socket after one of these
               calls. The same is true for non-blocking sockets. Furthermore,
               for a stream-oriented socket that is accepting connections, the
               sockets created as clients connect inherit the blocking state
               of the accepting socket. The full list of methods that fix the
               blocking state is as follows:</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para><methodname>vpr::Socket::read()</methodname>,
                     <methodname>vpr::Socket::readn()</methodname>,
                     <methodname>vpr::Socket::recv()</methodname>,
                     <methodname>vpr::Socket::recvn()</methodname>,
                     <methodname>vpr::SocketDatagram::recvfrom()</methodname></para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para><methodname>vpr::Socket::write()</methodname>,
                     <methodname>vpr::Socket::send()</methodname>,
                     <methodname>vpr::SocketDatagram::sendto()</methodname></para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para><methodname>vpr::SocketStream::accept()</methodname></para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para><methodname>vpr::SocketStream::connect()</methodname></para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>

               <para>The <ulink
               url="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/nspr/">NSPR
               documentation</ulink> has a more complete description of this
               issue. We must implement our socket abstraction in this way in
               order to provide consistent semantics (not just consistent
               syntax) across platforms.</para>
            </section>
         </section>

         <section id="section.datagram.sockets">
            <title>Datagram-Oriented Sockets</title>

            <indexterm zone="section.datagram.sockets">
               <primary>sockets</primary>

               <secondary>datagram</secondary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>The class
            <classname>vpr::SocketDatagram</classname><indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::SocketDatagram</secondary>
               </indexterm> provides VPR's abstraction to datagram-oriented
            sockets, typically known as UDP (user datagram protocol) sockets.
            Indeed, this class wraps the underlying operating system's
            implementation of UDP sockets. The interface for
            <classname>vpr::SocketDatagram</classname> extends
            <classname>vpr::Socket</classname><indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::Socket</secondary>
               </indexterm> to include the methods
            <methodname>sendto()</methodname> and
            <methodname>recvfrom()</methodname>, overloaded in the same way as
            <methodname>read()</methodname> and
            <methodname>write()</methodname>. As with the operating system
            API, these methods are used to send a message to a specific
            destination address or to receive a message from a specific remote
            address, respectively.</para>
         </section>

         <section id="section.stream.sockets">
            <title>Stream-Oriented Sockets</title>

            <indexterm zone="section.datagram.sockets">
               <primary>sockets</primary>

               <secondary>stream</secondary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>The class <classname>vpr::SocketStream</classname><indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::SocketStream</secondary>
               </indexterm> wraps the use of TCP (transmission control
            protocol) sockets. TCP sockets are also known more abstractly as
            stream-oriented sockets. All such sockets must be connected to a
            specific peer, and thus there is no interface comparable to
            <methodname>vpr::SocketDatagram::sendto()</methodname> or
            <methodname>vpr::SocketDatagram::recvfrom()</methodname>.</para>

            <para>In order for connections to be made, a socket must be
            listening for incoming connection requests. For that purpose,
            vpr::SocketStream introduces the methods
            <methodname>listen()</methodname> (to put a socket into a
            listening state) and <methodname>accept()</methodname> (for
            accepting new connections). These work the same way as the system
            calls after which they are named. However,
            <methodname>accept()</methodname> is somewhat unique in that it
            takes an unopened <classname>vpr::SocketStream</classname> object
            as a parameter. The object reference is <quote>set up</quote> when
            a successful connection occurs. Thus, when
            <methodname>vpr::SocketStream::accept()</methodname> returns
            successfully, the caller can be certain that the
            <classname>vpr::SocketStream</classname> reference passed in is
            now a valid, connected socket.</para>

            <para>Finally, since stream-oriented sockets always have an
            accepting socket that handles incoming connection requests,
            <classname>vpr::SocketStream</classname> provides a convenience
            method called <methodname>openServer()</methodname>. This can be
            used in place of the usual open-bind-listen sequence of calls for
            setting up an accepting (server) socket. Use of this method is not
            required for putting a socket into a listening state; rather, it
            exists to shorten user code slightly. The drawback of using it is
            that, in the case of failure, the returned status will not tell
            the caller what stage of setting up the listening socket
            failed.</para>
         </section>

         <section id="section.acceptor.connector">
            <title>The Acceptor/Connector Pattern</title>

            <indexterm zone="section.acceptor.connector">
               <primary>sockets</primary>

               <secondary>acceptor/connector pattern</secondary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>Building on the foundation of stream-oriented, connected
            sockets, VPR implements the Acceptor/Connector Pattern <xref
            linkend="ref.network.patterns" />. The classes used in the
            implementation are
            <classname>vpr::SocketAcceptor</classname><indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::SocketAcceptor</secondary>
               </indexterm> and
            <classname>vpr::SocketConnector</classname><indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::SocketConnector</secondary>
               </indexterm>. This pattern captures the concepts used in
            writing stream-oriented network software. The software may use a
            client/server protocol or a peer-to-peer protocol, but in either
            case, an initial connection must be made to an accepting
            socket.</para>

            <section>
               <title>The Acceptor</title>

               <para>The acceptor is created using a
               <classname>vpr::InetAddr</classname> object that specifies the
               address on which the acceptor listens for incoming connection
               requests. Once opened, the acceptor is ready to accept new
               connections. The call to
               <methodname>vpr::SocketAcceptor::accept()</methodname> uses the
               same arguments and behavior as
               <methodname>vpr::SocketStream::accept()</methodname>, so
               programmers already familiar with setting up an accepting
               socket with <classname>vpr::SocketStream</classname> will find
               <classname>vpr::SocketAcceptor</classname> very easy to
               use.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>The Connector</title>

               <para>The connector is designed to make non-blocking
               connections easy to manage. Depending on the arguments passed
               to <methodname>vpr::SocketConnector::connect()</methodname>, a
               socket may be put into non-blocking mode if it is not already
               set as such. Thus, a connection can be made <quote>in the
               background</quote> if necessary. However, due to the semantics
               described in <xref linkend="section.fixed.socket.blocking" />,
               after a background connection is made, the socket must remain
               in non-blocking mode for the duration of its lifetime.</para>
            </section>
         </section>
      </chapter>

      <chapter id="chapter.vpr.serial-ports">
         <title>Serial Ports</title>

         <indexterm zone="chapter.vpr.serial-ports">
            <primary>serial port abstraction</primary>
         </indexterm>

         <para>Most input devices used for virtual reality systems today make
         use of a computer's serial port for data communication. In our
         experience, serial port programming is not much different than other
         I/O programming. Implementing the communication protocol used by a
         given device tends to be the hard part, and that will likely be the
         case regardless of the underlying hardware.</para>

         <para>The VPR serial port abstraction is based on the concepts
         implemented by the standard termios serial interface used by most
         modern UNIX-based operating systems <xref
         linkend="ref.advanced.prog.unix" />. As such, the API allows enabling
         and disabling of a subset of the serial device features that can be
         manipulated using termios directly. To provide cross-platform
         semantics, however, some termios features are not included because
         there is no corresponding capability with Win32 overlapped I/O.
         Furthermore, any termios settings that relate only to modems are not
         included in the VPR serial port abstraction.</para>

         <section>
            <title>Interface Overview</title>

            <para>In termios, serial ports are configured by setting or
            clearing a wide variety of bits in various data structures. Based
            on this, the VPR serial port API includes methods for enabling a
            feature, disabling a feature, and testing the current status of a
            feature. For example, the following methods deal with the hardware
            flow control bit:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para><methodname>enableHardwareFlowControl()</methodname>:
                  Enables hardware flow control (if it was not already
                  enabled)</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para><methodname>disableHardwareFlowControl()</methodname>:
                  Disables hardware flow control (if it was not already
                  disabled)</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para><methodname>getHardwareFlowControlState()</methodname>:
                  Returns the current state of hardware flow control (true for
                  on, false for off)</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>When changing the enabled state of a serial port feature,
            the change may not take effect immediately. This is determined by
            the update action setting, which is manipulated by
            <methodname>vpr::SerialPort::setUpdateAction()</methodname>. There
            are three possible states (corresponding to the enumerated type
            <type>vpr::SerialTypes::UpdateActionOption</type>):</para>

            <orderedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Now: Perform the change immediately</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para>Drain: Perform the change after all output is
                  transmitted</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para>Flush: Perform the change after all output is
                  transmitted and discard all unread input</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>

            <para>The right setting to use may depend on the specific hardware
            or on the desired behavior.</para>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Abstraction Details</title>

            <para>The serial port abstraction is handled differently than the
            other I/O abstraction components. We wrap two serial port
            interfaces: termios and Win32 overlapped I/O. Because NSPR does
            not provide a serial port layer, we have to allow the termios to
            be used with NSPR on UNIX-based platforms. While this makes the
            implementation a little clumsy and the build system a little more
            complicated, it has little if any impact on users. The point of
            the abstraction is to hide the low-level details to provide a
            consistent interface across platforms.</para>
         </section>
      </chapter>

      <chapter id="chapter.data.marshaling">
         <title>Data Marshaling</title>

         <indexterm zone="chapter.vpr.serial-ports">
            <primary>object serialization</primary>
         </indexterm>

         <para>Network communication involves the transfer of data between
         computers, and for it to work, the two computers must be able to talk
         to each other using the same language. This must occur even if the
         two have different internal representations of the data they hold.
         Thus, the data must be marshaled into a common format when it is sent
         out and demarshaled into the local native format when it is received.
         VPR provides some helper functions and utility classes to simplify
         the efforts of network programmers.</para>

         <section>
            <title>Endian Conversion</title>

            <indexterm>
               <primary>byte order</primary>

               <secondary>host/network conversion</secondary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>A very common data marshaling activity is the conversion of
            a multi-byte data unit from host byte order to network byte order.
            Such conversions are necessary for elements of data that occupy 16
            or more bits. In VPR terms, that means the types
            <type>vpr::Int16</type>, <type>vpr::int32</type>,
            <type>vpr::Int64</type>, and the unsigned variants thereof. The
            interface <classname>vpr::System</classname><indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::System</secondary>
               </indexterm> provides conversion functions from host to network
            byte order and vice versa for all of these types. All the
            functions operate in terms of the unsigned version of the
            aforementioned integer types, but they work with the signed
            versions as well since they simply manipulate the actual bits. The
            full list of functions is as follows:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para><methodname>vpr::System::Htons()</methodname>:
                  Converts a 16-bit integer from host to network byte
                  order.</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para><methodname>vpr::System::Ntohs()</methodname>:
                  Converts a 16-bit integer from network to host byte
                  order.</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para><methodname>vpr::System::Htonl()</methodname>:
                  Converts a 32-bit integer from host to network byte
                  order.</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para><methodname>vpr::System::Ntohl()</methodname>:
                  Converts a 32-bit integer from network to host byte
                  order.</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para><methodname>vpr::System::Htonll()</methodname>:
                  Converts a 64-bit integer from host to network byte
                  order.</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para><methodname>vpr::System::Ntohll()</methodname>:
                  Converts a 64-bit integer from network to host byte
                  order.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>Single-precision floating-point values (which occupy 32 bits
            of memory) can be converted using
            <methodname>vpr::System::Htonl()</methodname> and
            <methodname>vpr::System::Ntohl()</methodname>. Similarly,
            double-precision floating-point values (which occupy 64 bits of
            memory) can be converted using
            <methodname>vpr::System::Htonll()</methodname> and
            <methodname>vpr::System::Nothll()</methodname>.</para>

            <note>
               <para>Programmers already familiar with the operating
               system-level calls such as <function>ntohs(3)</function> and
               <function>htonl(3)</function> may wonder why the above
               functions are named with a capital letter (i.e.,
               <methodname>vpr::System::Htonl()</methodname> versus
               <methodname>vpr::System::htonl()</methodname>). We have used
               this naming convention because the byte order conversion
               functions are preprocessor macros on some platforms, and the C
               preprocessor cannot tell the difference between a method
               declaration and the use of a macro. In other words, the code
               would not compile on platforms where the functions are really
               macros.</para>
            </note>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Object Serialization</title>

            <indexterm>
               <primary>object serialization</primary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>Serializing objects is more complicated than dealing with
            individual integer variables, but ultimately, a class is composed
            of other data types. If the internal data types can be serialized,
            then the object that holds them can be serialized as well. To
            enable this functionality, VPR defines the interface
            <classname>vpr::SerializableObject</classname><indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::SerializableObject</secondary>
               </indexterm>. It operates in terms of two other interfaces:
            <classname>vpr::ObjectReader</classname><indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::ObjectReader</secondary>
               </indexterm> and
            <classname>vpr::ObjectWriter</classname><indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::ObjectWriter</secondary>
               </indexterm>. Together, these allow an object and all the data
            it aggregates to be serialized into an array of bytes that can be
            sent over the network. Once received, the array can be
            de-serialized into a duplicate of the original object.</para>

            <para>The basic idea behind the object serialization interface in
            VPR is the same as in Java (see the API documentation on
            <classname>java.io.Serializable</classname>). An class identifies
            itself as being serializable by adding
            <classname>vpr::SerializableObject</classname> to its list of
            parent classes. Two pure virtual methods must then be implemented:
            <methodname>readObject()</methodname> and
            <methodname>writeObject()</methodname>. When a class instance must
            be serialized, <methodname>writeObject()</methodname> is invoked
            with an argument that provides the class with a
            <classname>vpr::ObjectWriter</classname> instance. The
            implementation of <methodname>writeObject()</methodname> would
            then add the instance data to the object writer and return.
            De-serializing an object occurs in
            <methodname>readObject()</methodname> using an instance of
            <classname>vpr::ObjectReader</classname>. A full class hierarchy
            can be serialized and de-serialized through polymorphism. The
            derived classes must simply call the parent class'
            <methodname>writeObject()</methodname> and
            <methodname>readObject()</methodname> methods, thus following the
            class hierarchy up to the first class that identified itself as
            serializable.</para>

            <para>Because vpr::ObjectReader and vpr::ObjectWriter are abstract
            types, the actual implementation of these may vary. This is
            similar to the way that Java can serialize an object to a variety
            of data streams. Currently, VPR can serialize a class to an array
            of bytes (<classname>vpr::BufferObjectReader</classname><indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::BufferObjectReader</secondary>
               </indexterm> and
            <classname>vpr::BufferObjectWriter</classname><indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::BufferObjectWriter</secondary>
               </indexterm>) or to XML
            (<classname>vpr::XMLObjectReader</classname><indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::XMLObjectReader</secondary>
               </indexterm> and
            <classname>vpr::XMLObjectWriter</classname><indexterm>
                  <primary>classes</primary>

                  <secondary>vpr::XMLObjectWriter</secondary>
               </indexterm>). The array of bytes is suitable for network
            transmission and makes sharing of classes between hosts
            easy.</para>
         </section>
      </chapter>
   </part>

   <part id="part.multi-threading">
      <title>Multi-Threading</title>

      <partintro>
         <para>In this part, we present the capabilities VPR provides for
         writing cross-platform multi-threaded software. It is assumed that
         readers already know the basics of multi-threaded programming
         including the definition of <firstterm>thread of
         control</firstterm><indexterm>
               <primary>thread of control</primary>
            </indexterm>. What is described here is how to use the VPR thread
         interface, <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>, not how to write
         multi-threaded software. For that reason, it is recommended that
         readers be familiar with the following publications before
         continuing:</para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para><ulink
               url="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/pthread/"><emphasis>Pthreads
               Programming</emphasis></ulink> by Bradford Nichols, Dick
               Buttlar, and Jacqueline Proulx Farrell.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <para>The <function>pthread(3)</function> manual page for your
               operating system. The pthread functions are part of a POSIX
               standard and will be the same across platforms.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
      </partintro>

      <chapter id="chapter.threads">
         <title>Creating Threads</title>

         <para>When considering multi-threaded programming, it is important to
         know that with great power comes great responsibility. The power is
         being able to provide multiple threads of control in a single
         application. The responsibility is making sure those threads get
         along with each other and do not step on each other's data. VR
         Juggler is a multi-threaded library which makes it very powerful and
         very complex.</para>

         <para>As a cross-platform framework, VR Juggler uses an internal
         threading abstraction that provides a uniform interface to
         platform-specific threading implementations. That cross-platform
         interface is available to programmers to make applications
         multi-threaded without tying them to a specific operating system's
         threading implementation.</para>

         <section id="section.vprThread">
            <title>Threads: Using <classname>vpr::Thread</classname></title>

            <indexterm zone="section.vprThread">
               <primary>multi-threading</primary>

               <secondary>vpr::Thread</secondary>
            </indexterm>

            <indexterm zone="section.vprThread">
               <primary>vpr::Thread</primary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>The threading interface in VPR is modeled after the POSIX
            thread specification of POSIX.1b (formerly POSIX.4). The main
            difference is that VPR's interface is object-oriented while POSIX
            threads (pthreads) are procedural. The basic principles are
            exactly the same, however. A function (or class method) is
            provided to the <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> class, and that
            function is executed in a thread of control that is independent of
            the creating thread.</para>

            <para>Threads are spawned (initialized and begin execution) when
            the <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> constructor is called. That
            is, when instantiating a <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>
            object, a new thread of execution is created. The semantics of
            threads says that a thread can begin execution at any time after
            being created, and this is true with
            <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>s. Do not make any assumptions
            about when the thread will begin running. It may happen before or
            after the constructor returns the
            <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> object.</para>

            <para>To pass arguments to threads, the common mechanism of
            encapsulating them in a C++ <type>struct</type> must be used. The
            function executed by the thread takes only a single argument of
            type <type>void*</type>. An argument is not required, of course,
            but to pass more than one argument to a thread, the best way to do
            this is to create a structure and pass a pointer to it to the
            <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> constructor.</para>

            <para>Once a <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> object is created,
            it acts as an interface into controlling the thread it
            encapsulates. Thread signals can be sent, priority changes can be
            made, execution can be suspended, etc. This interface is the focus
            of this section.</para>

            <para>We begin our discussion of creating threads with VPR by
            explaining the use of the class
            <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>. Use of
            <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> is intended to be easy.
            Multi-threaded programming has enough complications without having
            a difficult API as well. In almost all cases, thread creation can
            be done in a single step, executed one of two ways:</para>

            <orderedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Pass a function pointer to the
                  <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> constructor along with
                  any argument that should be passed to the function when the
                  thread is created</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para>Pass a <glossterm>functor</glossterm><indexterm>
                        <primary>functor</primary>
                     </indexterm> (a callable object) to the
                  <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> constructor</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>

            <para>The second appears easier, but to create the functor,
            parameters to the function executed by the thread may still have
            to be passed. The presence of parameters depends on the specific
            function being run by the thread. In addition to the function
            pointer or functor, parameters such as the priority and the stack
            size may be passed to the <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>
            constructor, but the defaults for the constructor are quite
            reasonable.</para>

            <para>A minor issue with creating a
            <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> is the concept of functors. The
            topic of functors will be put off until the next section. For now,
            just think of them as callable objects.</para>

            <para>Before writing code that uses
            <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>s, make sure that the header
            file <filename>vpr/Thread/Thread.h</filename> is included. Never
            include the platform-specific headers such as
            <filename>vpr/md/POSIX/Thread/ThreadPosix.h</filename>. The single
            file <filename>vpr/Thread/Thread.h</filename> is all that is
            required.</para>

            <section id="section.creating.threads">
               <title>Creating Threads</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Thread</primary>

                  <secondary>creating</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>The following example illustrates how to create a thread
               that will execute a free function called
               <function>run()</function> that takes no arguments. The
               prototype for <function>run()</function> is:</para>

               <programlisting>void run();</programlisting>

               <para>This will be the same across all platforms. The thread
               creation code is then:</para>

               <programlisting>vpr::Thread* thread;

thread = new vpr::Thread(run);</programlisting>

               <para>At this point, a newly spawned thread is executing the
               code in <function>run()</function>. It is advisable to hang
               onto the variable <varname>thread</varname> so that the thread
               may be controlled as necessary.</para>

               <para>That was pretty easy. What if you want to pass one or
               more arguments to <function>run()</function> so that its
               behavior can be modified based on some variables? One approach
               is to define the function so that it takes a parameter that is
               an aggregate type (a struct or a class). The data needed by the
               function is then collected into this aggregate type and
               packaged with the function pointer. A common way to do this is
               as follows:</para>

               <programlisting>struct ThreadArgs
{
   int id;
   std::string name;
   // And so on...
};

void run(const ThreadArgs&amp; args)
{
   // Do work ...
}

void someFunc()
{
   // Other code ...

   ThreadArgs args;
   args.id = 50;
   args.name = "My Thread";
   // And so on ...

   vpr::Thread* thread;
   thread = new vpr::Thread(boost::bind(run, args);
}</programlisting>

               <para>When creating a single thread, this works beautifully. If
               multiple threads are needed, all taking the same type of
               argument, there would usually have to be a separate argument
               structure instance for each one. A bunch of objects can be
               declared, or the same objects can be reused over and
               over.</para>

               <para>The preceding example made use of <ulink
               url="http://www.boost.org/libs/bind/bind.html">Boost.Bind</ulink>
               to couple the <function>run()</function> function with a struct
               instance. Instead of declaring a struct to bundle all the
               arguments together, we could take advantage of the flexibility
               of Boost.Bind to couple multiple arguments with the function.
               This is shown below:</para>

               <programlisting>void run(int id, char* name)
{
   // Do work ...
}

void someFunc()
{
   // Other code ...

   vpr::Thread* thread;
   thread = new vpr::Thread(boost::bind(run, 50, "My Thread"));
}</programlisting>

               <para>There is a limit to the number of parameters that can be
               passed in this way, so this approach must be used judiciously.
               We will explain more about function objects and Boost.Bind in
               <xref linkend="section.thread.functors" />.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Waiting for a Thread to Complete</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Thread</primary>

                  <secondary>joining threads</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>Once we have a thread running, it is often useful to
               synchronize another thread so that its execution halts until
               the running thread has completed. This is called <quote>joining
               threads</quote>. The following example illustrates how this can
               be done:</para>

               <programlisting>vpr::Thread* thread;

thread = new vpr::Thread(run);

// Do other things while the thread is going ...

thread-&gt;join();

// Now that the thread is done, continue.</programlisting>

               <para>Here, the creator of thread can be another
               <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>, or it can be the main
               thread of execution. In other words, any thread can create more
               threads and control them. What happens in this example is that
               thread is created and begins running. Meanwhile, the creator
               thread continues to do some more work and then must wait for
               <varname>thread</varname> to finish its work before continuing.
               It calls the <methodname>join()</methodname> method, a blocking
               call, and it will not return until <varname>thread</varname>
               has completed.</para>

               <para>While it is not demonstrated here, the
               <methodname>join()</methodname> method can take a single
               argument of type <type>void**</type>. It is a pointer to a
               pointer where the exit status of the joined thread is stored.
               The operating system fills the pointed to pointer with the exit
               status when the thread exits.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Suspending and Resuming a Thread's Execution</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Thread</primary>

                  <secondary>suspend, resume</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>Sometimes, it may be necessary to suspend the execution
               of a running thread and resume it again later. There are two
               methods in the <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> interface
               that do just this. Assuming that there is already a running
               thread pointed to by the object <varname>thread</varname>, it
               can be suspended as follows:</para>

               <programlisting>thread-&gt;suspend();</programlisting>

               <para>Resuming execution of the suspended thread is just as
               easy:</para>

               <programlisting>thread-&gt;resume();</programlisting>

               <para>If something goes wrong when suspending or resuming,
               <exceptionname>vpr::IllegalArgumentException</exceptionname><indexterm>
                     <primary>exceptions</primary>

                     <secondary>vpr::IllegalArgumentException</secondary>
                  </indexterm> is thrown. Otherwise, these methods return
               nothing upon successful completion.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Getting and Setting a Thread's Priority</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Thread</primary>

                  <secondary>priority</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>Changing the priority of a thread tells the underlying
               operating system how important a thread is and gives it hints
               about how to schedule the threads. If no value for the priority
               is given to the constructor, all
               <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>s are created with the
               default priority for all threads. Values higher than 0 for the
               priority request a higher priority when the thread is
               created.</para>

               <para>Besides being able to set the priority when the thread is
               created, it is possible to query and to adjust the priority of
               a running thread. Assuming that there is already a running
               thread pointed to by the object <varname>thread</varname>, its
               priority can be requested as follows:</para>

               <programlisting>int prio;

thread-&gt;getPrio(&amp;prio);</programlisting>

               <para>The thread's priority is stored in
               <varname>prio</varname> and returned via the pointer passed to
               the <methodname>getPrio()</methodname> method. Setting that
               thread's priority is also easy:</para>

               <programlisting>int prio;

// Assign some priority value to prio ...

thread-&gt;setPrio(prio);</programlisting>

               <para>If something goes wrong when querying or changing the
               priority of the thread,
               <exceptionname>vpr::IllegalArgumentException</exceptionname><indexterm>
                     <primary>exceptions</primary>

                     <secondary>vpr::IllegalArgumentException</secondary>
                  </indexterm> is thrown. Otherwise, these methods return
               nothing upon successful completion.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Sending Signals to a Thread</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Thread</primary>

                  <secondary>sending signals</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>On UNIX-based systems, a signal is sent to a process
               using the <function>kill(2)</function> system call. With POSIX
               threads, signals are sent using
               <function>pthread_kill(3)</function>. VPR's thread interface
               implements these ideas using a <methodname>kill()</methodname>
               method. There are two ways to call this method: with an
               argument naming the signal to be delivered to the thread or
               without an argument which cancels the thread's execution. The
               first of these is described in this section, and the second is
               described in the next section.</para>

               <para>A problem does arise here, unfortunately. Signals are not
               supported on all operating systems (notably, Win32). The
               interface is consistent, but code written on IRIX will not
               compile on Win32 if, for example, it sends a
               <constant>SIGHUP</constant> to a thread. An improved thread
               interface is being designed to overcome problems such as this
               one. For now, we describe this part of the interface as though
               it is supported completely on all platforms.</para>

               <para>As usual, assume there is a running thread, a pointer to
               which is stored in <varname>thread</varname>. To send it a
               signal (<constant>SIGINT</constant>, for example), use the
               following:</para>

               <programlisting>thread-&gt;kill(SIGINT);</programlisting>

               <para>The signal will be delivered to the thread by the
               operating system, and the thread is expected to handle it
               properly. This version of the <methodname>kill()</methodname>
               method throws
               <exceptionname>vpr::IllegalArgumentException</exceptionname><indexterm>
                     <primary>exceptions</primary>

                     <secondary>vpr::IllegalArgumentException</secondary>
                  </indexterm> if an error occurs. Otherwise, this method
               returns nothing upon successful compltion.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Canceling a Thread's Execution</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Thread</primary>

                  <secondary>canceling</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>As described in the previous section, using the
               <methodname>kill()</methodname> method with no argument cancels
               the execution of the thread. When using POSIX threads, this is
               actually implemented using
               <methodname>pthread_cancel(3)</methodname>. The syntax for
               using this method is basically the same as in the previous
               section, but it is repeated to make that clear. Again assuming
               that there is a running thread with a pointer to its
               <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> object stored in
               <varname>thread</varname>, use the following:</para>

               <programlisting>thread-&gt;kill();</programlisting>

               <para>Unlike the syntax used to send a signal to a thread, this
               version of <methodname>kill()</methodname> does not have a
               return value.</para>

               <para>Users of POSIX threads may be wondering if the
               <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> API provides a way to set
               cancellation points in the code. Unfortunately, it does not at
               this time. Extending the interface in this way is being
               considered, but cancellation points do not have meaning with
               all thread implementations.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Requesting the Current Thread's Identifier</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Thread</primary>

                  <secondary>self</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>Lastly, it is common to request the currently running
               thread's identifier. This only makes sense when called from a
               point on that thread's flow of execution. (In POSIX threads,
               this is the notion of <quote>self</quote>.) The
               <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> API provides a static method
               that can be called at any time in the thread that is currently
               running. It returns a pointer to a
               <classname>vpr::BaseThread</classname> (the basic type from
               which <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> inherits its
               interface). The syntax is as follows:</para>

               <programlisting>vpr::BaseThread* my_id;

my_id = vpr::Thread::self();</programlisting>

               <para>The returned pointer can then be used to perform all of
               the previously described operations on the current
               thread.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>The Gory Details</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Thread</primary>

                  <secondary>details</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>The current threading implementation in VPR is a little
               difficult to understand. The code is not complicated at all,
               but because all platform-specific implementations are referred
               to as <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>s, the details can get
               lost in the shuffle. To begin, the current list of
               platform-specific thread implementation wrapper classes
               are:</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para><classname>vpr::ThreadPosix</classname>: A wrapper
                     around POSIX threads (both Draft 4 and Draft 10 of the
                     standard are supported)</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para><classname>vpr::ThreadNSPR</classname>: A wrapper
                     around Netscape Portable Runtime threads</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para><classname>vpr::ThreadWin32</classname>: A wrapper
                     around Win32 threads</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>

               <para>The interface itself is defined in
               <classname>vpr::BaseThread</classname>, and all of the above
               classes inherit from that class.</para>

               <para>The threading implementation used is chosen when VPR is
               compiled. To use a certain type of thread system, be sure that
               the version of VPR in use was compiled with the type of threads
               desired. When the VPR build is configured, preprocessor
               <function>#define</function> statements are made in
               <filename>vpr/vprDefines.h</filename> that describe the
               threading system to use. Based on that, the header file
               <filename>vpr/Thread/Thread.h</filename> makes several
               <type>typedef</type>s that set up one of the platform-specific
               thread implementations to act as the
               <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> interface. For example, if
               compiling on Win32, the class
               <classname>vpr::ThreadWin32</classname> is
               <type>typedef</type>'d to be
               <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>. Since the interface is
               consistent among all the wrappers, everything works as though
               that was the way it was written to behave.</para>

               <para>The current implementation is modeled after the POSIX
               thread API for the most part. When designing it, we approached
               it with the idea that having a more complete API was more
               important than having a
               <quote>lowest-common-denominator</quote> API. That is, just
               because not all threading implementations support a specific
               feature does not mean that the API should suffer by not having
               that feature. Whether this was a good approach or not is an
               open debate.</para>

               <note>
                  <para>VPR has a wrapper around <ulink
                  url="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/nspr/index.html">Netscape
                  Portable Runtime</ulink> (NSPR) threads<indexterm>
                        <primary>NSPR</primary>
                     </indexterm>. NSPR threads do not support all the
                  features we have, however, because they took the
                  lowest-common-denominator approach. As with all technology,
                  there is a trade-off in relieving some of our work load by
                  using an existing cross-platform thread implementation: our
                  interface becomes limited to what features that
                  implementation provides. It remains to be seen exactly how
                  much of VPR's threading subsystem will be removed, and those
                  programmers who choose to use it should be careful to watch
                  the mailing lists for discussions and announcements about
                  changes.</para>
               </note>
            </section>
         </section>

         <section id="section.thread.functors">
            <title>Thread Functors</title>

            <para>In this section, we explain the concept and use of
            <glossterm linkend="gloss.functor">functors</glossterm>. A functor
            is a high-level concept that encapsulates something quite simple.
            A functor is defined as <quote>something that performs an
            operation or a function.</quote> In VPR functors are used as the
            code executed by a thread (refer to <xref
            linkend="section.vprThread" /> for more detail on the topic of
            <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>s). This section describes how
            to use functors for exactly that purpose.</para>

            <important>
               <para>Users of the VPR 1.0 thread API are encouraged to read
               this section very carefully. At the end, there is an
               explanation of how to update VPR 1.0 code to use the new thread
               functor interface. The flexibility offered by the new approach
               in VPR 1.1 and beyond should offer programmers many new
               opportunities for how they handle and utilize threads in their
               software.</para>
            </important>

            <section>
               <title>High-Level Description</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::BaseThreadFunctor</primary>

                  <secondary>description of</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>functor</primary>

                  <secondary>use with vpr::Thread</secondary>

                  <seealso>vpr::Thread</seealso>
               </indexterm>

               <para>As mentioned, a functor<indexterm>
                     <primary>functor</primary>
                  </indexterm> is used in VPR with
               <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>s<indexterm>
                     <primary>classes</primary>

                     <secondary>vpr::Thread</secondary>
                  </indexterm>. VPR threads utilize <ulink
               url="http://www.boost.org/doc/html/function.html">Boost.Function</ulink>
               as the functor implementation. A Boost.Function object is a
               callable object, meaning that it has an overload of
               <function>operator()</function> that takes zero or more
               arguments. Earlier in <xref
               linkend="section.creating.threads" />, we saw how to use raw
               function pointers. Boost.Function can wrap four different types
               of callable types:</para>

               <orderedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>Free functions</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>Static class functions</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>Non-static member functions</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>Objects overloading the member function
                     <function>operator()</function></para>
                  </listitem>
               </orderedlist>

               <para>Programmers already familiar with the use of
               Boost.Function and Boost.Bind can skip this entire section
               about thread functors. The remainder of this section is an
               overview of how to use Boost.Function and Boost.Bind for
               programmers who are unfamiliar with these tools.</para>

               <para>Getting back to functors, a functor is simply another
               object type that happens to encapsulate a user-defined
               function. The details on how this is done are not important
               here. What is important to know is that a functor can be
               thought of as a normal function. When using them, programmers
               usually just implement a function and then pass the function
               pointer to the Boost.Function constructor. Boost.Function does
               the rest.</para>

               <para>The functor must behave as a function that returns
               nothing and takes no parameters. In terms of function pointers,
               the type must be <type>void(*)(void)</type>. A more readable
               form of this is the Boost.Function type:
               <type>boost::function&lt;void()&gt;</type>. Yet another form is
               the portable Boost.Function type used for older compilers:
               <type>boost::function0&lt;void&gt;</type>. Remember that we are
               not restricted to using function pointers to create functions.
               We are describing here callable objects that
               <emphasis>behave</emphasis> as functions.</para>

               <para>If the functor needs to be passed arguments, then <ulink
               url="http://www.boost.org/libs/bind/bind.html">Boost.Bind</ulink>
               must used to couple parameters with the functor. Those
               parameters will be passed into the function later when the
               functor is invoked. Boost.Bind is very powerful, and the full
               usage of it is beyond the scope of this document. We will
               demonstrate its use more fully later in this section, but we
               provide some uses in <xref
               linkend="example.quick.boost.bind" />.</para>

               <example id="example.quick.boost.bind">
                  <title>Using Boost.Bind to Create Thread Functors</title>

                  <programlisting>struct ThreadArgs
{
   int id;
   std::string name;
};

void run1(const ThreadArgs&amp; args);
void run2(const int id, const std::string&amp; name);

class MyClass
{
public:
   // Bind a free function with an instance of an aggregate type.
   void spawnThread1()
   {
      ThreadArgs args = { 50, "My Thread" };
      mThread = new vpr::Thread(boost::bind(run1, args));
   }

   // Bind a free function with an instanced of an aggregate type that
   // is a data member.
   void spawnThread2()
   {
      // Copies mArgs.
      mThread = new vpr::Thread(boost::bind(run1, mArgs));

      // Passes a reference to mArgs.
      mThread = new vpr::Thread(boost::bind(run1, boost::ref(mArgs)));
   }

   // Bind a free function with multiple parameters.
   void spawnThread2()
   {
      mThread =
         new vpr::Thread(boost::bind(run2, 50,
                                     std::string("My Thread")));
   }

   // Bind a static member function with an argument.
   void spawnThread3()
   {
      mThread = new vpr::Thread(boost::bind(MyClass::staticRun, 10));
   }

   // Bind a non-static member function.
   void spawnThread4()
   {
      mThread = new vpr::Thread(boost::bind(&amp;MyClass::run, this));
   }

   // Bind a non-static member function with multiple parameters.
   void spawnThread5()
   {
      mThread = new vpr::Thread(boost::bind(&amp;MyClass::run, this,
                                            3.14159f, 16));
   }

private:
   static void staticRun(int id);

   void run();

   void otherRun(const float someParam, short otherParam);

   vpr::Thread* mThread;
   ThreadArgs   mArgs;
};</programlisting>
               </example>

               <para>Once a functor object exists, it is passed to the
               <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> constructor, and the new
               thread will execute the functor (which knows what to do with
               its held callable). The end result is the same as using a
               normal C/C++ free function or a static class member function,
               but there is one special benefit: with functors, non-static
               class member functions can be passed. In many cases, there
               arises a need to run a member function in a separate thread,
               but making it static is infeasible or awkward. Thus, it would
               be best to pass a non-static member function to the created
               thread. To get access to the non-static data members, however,
               the C++ <varname>this</varname> pointer must be available to
               the thread. By using Boost.Bind with Boost.Function, that is
               all handled behind the scenes so that passing a non-static
               member function is straightforward. We have seen how to do this
               in the methods <methodname>MyClass::spawnThread4()</methodname>
               and <methodname>MyClass::spawnThread5()</methodname>.</para>

               <para>Before getting into specifics, there is a header file
               that must be included to use Boost.Function VPR thread
               functors. In this case, the header is
               <filename>boost/function.hpp</filename>. If Boost.Bind is
               needed, then <filename>boost/bind.hpp</filename> must be
               included. Finally, if <function>boost::ref()</function> is
               needed, then <filename>boost/ref.hpp</filename> must be
               included.</para>
            </section>

            <section id="section.functor.member">
               <title>Functors from (Non-Static) Member Functions</title>

               <indexterm zone="section.functor.member">
                  <primary>functors</primary>

                  <secondary>non-static member functions</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <indexterm zone="section.functor.member">
                  <primary>functors</primary>

                  <secondary>member functions</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>We have already seen examples of how to create a
               Boost.Function functor for a member function. In this section,
               we will review in more detail using Boost.Function and
               Boost.Bind to accomplish this. Just as with free functions, the
               member functions (heretofore referred to as
               <quote>methods</quote>) must have the following
               prototype:</para>

               <programlisting>void methodName();</programlisting>

               <para>A common example of using
               <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> with a member function as
               the functor callable is shown in <xref
               linkend="example.functor.member1" />. The key aspect in this
               example is the implementation of the method
               <methodname>MyObject::start()</methodname>. The usage of
               Boost.Bind here is required because the object pointer has to
               be bound with the member function pointer in order for it to be
               invoked properly. Fortunately, this use is very simple—much
               simpler than the use of
               <classname>vpr::ThreadMemberFunctor&lt;T&gt;</classname> in VPR
               1.0.</para>

               <note>
                  <para>This is not the only way of using
                  <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>, nor is it strictly a
                  recommended way of using it. It is simply an example. One
                  missing aspect is protection of <varname>mRunning</varname>
                  using a synchronization primitive such as a condition
                  variable.</para>
               </note>

               <example id="example.functor.member1">
                  <title>Member Function for Thread Functor (1)</title>

                  <programlisting>class MyObject
{
public:
   MyObject()
      : mThread(NULL)
      , mRunning(false)
   {
   }

   ~MyObject()
   {
      if ( mRunning )
      {
         stop();
      }

      if ( NULL != mThread )
      {
         delete mThread;
         mThread = NULL;
      }
   }

   void start()
   {
      mThread  = new vpr::Thread(boost::bind(&amp;MyObject::run, this));
      mRunning = true;
   }

   void stop()
   {
      mRunning = false;
      mThread-&gt;join();
   }

private:
   void run()
   {
      while ( mRunning )
      {
         // Do work ...
      }
   }

   vpr::Thread* mThread;
   bool         mRunning;
};</programlisting>
               </example>

               <para>Now let us say that there is the method
               <methodname>MyObject::run()</methodname> needs to take one or
               more arguments. Boost.Bind makes this possible, and it is just
               as easy as what we have seen in the previous example. We simply
               have to bind the method arguments along with the
               <varname>this</varname> pointer, as shown in <xref
               linkend="example.functor.member2" />. For the purposes of this
               example, we have changed
               <methodname>MyObject::start()</methodname> so that it takes an
               argument that specifies how many iterations the thread loop
               will perform before exiting.</para>

               <example id="example.functor.member2">
                  <title>Member Function for Thread Functor (2)</title>

                  <programlisting>void MyObject::start(const int runCount)
{
   mThread = vpr::Thread(boost::bind(&amp;MyObject::run, this, runCount));
}

void MyObject::run(const int runCount)
{
   for ( int i = 0; i &lt; runCount; ++i )
   {
      // Do work ...
   }
}</programlisting>
               </example>

               <para>What if the thread spawning is happening externally to
               the class that does the work? Once again, Boost.Bind will be
               necessary, and as we will see, the usage is familiar. Instead
               of using <varname>this</varname>, we use the object instance
               created by the external code. We will change the declaration of
               <classname>MyObject</classname> and assume that there is an
               aggregate type <type>thread_args_t</type> declared somewhere.
               The code shown in <xref linkend="example.functor.member3" />
               demonstrates how we make this happen, though it is a contrived
               example. Note that the memory allocated for
               <varname>args</varname> would have to be deleted at some point
               after the thread is done using the data. That could be done at
               the end of <methodname>MyObject::run()</methodname> or after
               the thread is known to have completed its execution.</para>

               <example id="example.functor.member3">
                  <title>Member Function for Thread Functor (3)</title>

                  <programlisting>struct thread_args_t;

class MyObject
{
public:
   void run(thread_args_t* args)
   {
      // Do work ...
   }
};

void spawnThread()
{
   MyObject* my_obj = new MyObject();
   thread_args_t* args = new thread_args_t();
   // Fill in the arguments to be passed to the thread...

   vpr::Thread* thread = new vpr::Thread(boost::bind(&amp;MyObject::run,
                                                     my_obj, args));
}</programlisting>
               </example>

               <para>Creating so many heap-allocated objects is rather a
               hassle. Parameters passed to <function>boost::bind()</function>
               are copied by default. This allows the memory to be coupled
               with the functor so that it is available when the functor is
               invoked later. This means that it is safe to use
               stack-allocated memory when calling
               <function>boost::bind()</function>. It is not always desirable
               to have all the data copied, and that is where
               <function>boost::ref()</function> comes into the picture. In
               <xref linkend="example.functor.member4" />, we see an example
               of using <function>boost::ref()</function> to create a
               reference to the instance of <classname>MyObject</classname>
               while copying in the object of type <type>thread_args_t</type>.
               Since <varname>my_obj</varname> is passed by reference, the
               memory should not actually be allocated on the heap. Rather, it
               would normally be a data member for the class creating the
               thread. More generally, <varname>my_obj</varname> cannot be
               deleted before the created thread exits. If
               <varname>my_obj</varname> is deleted while the thread is
               running, the application will crash. This is true of all data
               bound to the function called by the spawned thread.</para>

               <example id="example.functor.member4">
                  <title>Member Function for Thread Functor (4)</title>

                  <programlisting>MyObject my_obj;
thread_args_t args;

// Fill in the arguments to be passed to the thread...

vpr::Thread* thread = new vpr::Thread(boost::bind(&amp;MyObject::run,
                                                  boost::ref(my_obj),
                                                  args));</programlisting>
               </example>

               <important>
                  <para>Objects bound as parameters to a function call through
                  <function>boost::bind()</function> may be copied many, many
                  times. If this copying of objects will be expensive,
                  strongly consider using <function>boost::ref()</function> to
                  prevent this from happening. Bear in mind that memory may
                  have to be managed differently to ensure that the referenced
                  bound parameter does not get deleted prematurely.</para>
               </important>
            </section>

            <section id="section.functor.static.member">
               <title>Functors from Static Member Functions</title>

               <indexterm zone="section.functor.static.member">
                  <primary>functors</primary>

                  <secondary>static member functions</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <example id="example.functor.static.member1">
                  <title>Static Member Function for Thread Functor (1)</title>

                  <programlisting>class MyObject
{
public:
   MyObject()
      : mThread(NULL)
   {
   }

   ~MyObject()
   {
      // Need to ensure that the thread is not running.
      if ( NULL != mThread )
      {
         delete mThread;
         mThread = NULL;
      }
   }

   void start()
   {
      mThread  = new vpr::Thread(MyObject::run);
   }

   void stop()
   {
      // Tell the thread to exit ...
      mThread-&gt;join();
   }

private:
   static void run()
   {
      // Do work ...
   }

   vpr::Thread* mThread;
};</programlisting>
               </example>

               <example id="example.functor.static.member2">
                  <title>Static Member Function for Thread Functor (2)</title>

                  <programlisting>void MyObject::start(const int runCount)
{
   mThread = vpr::Thread(boost::bind(MyObject::run, runCount));
}

void MyObject::run(const int runCount)
{
   for ( int i = 0; i &lt; runCount; ++i )
   {
      // Do work ...
   }
}</programlisting>
               </example>

               <example id="example.functor.static.member3">
                  <title>Static Member Function for Thread Functor (3)</title>

                  <programlisting>struct thread_args_t;

class MyObject
{
public:
   static void run(thread_args_t* args)
   {
      // Do work ...
   }
};

void spawnThread()
{
   thread_args_t* args = new thread_args_t();
   // Fill in the arguments to be passed to the thread...

   vpr::Thread* thread = new vpr::Thread(boost::bind(MyObject::run,
                                                     args));
}</programlisting>
               </example>
            </section>

            <section id="section.functor.non.member">
               <title>Functors from Non-Member Functions</title>

               <indexterm zone="section.functor.non.member">
                  <primary>functors</primary>

                  <secondary>non-member functions</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>Functors for threads can be created for non-member
               functions. The process is basically the same as for using
               static member functions. The only real difference is that the
               class scoping does not need to be used since the non-member
               functions will not be in a class. A simple example of this is
               shown in <xref linkend="example.functor.non.member" />. As
               usual, proper memory management would be needed for the
               allocated <classname>vpr::Thread</classname> object. And, of
               course, parameters to the non-member function can be bound to
               the function using Boost.Bind.</para>

               <example id="example.functor.non.member">
                  <title>Non-Member Function for Thread Functor</title>

                  <programlisting>void run()
{
   // Do some work ...
}

void startThread()
{
   vpr::Thread* thread = new vpr::Thread(run);
}</programlisting>
               </example>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Functors from Callable Objects</title>

               <para>A new capability not (easily) available with VPR 1.0 is
               the use of callable objects as functors. This means using an
               instance of a type that overloads
               <function>operator()</function> as the callable handled by
               Boost.Function. One way of doing this is shown in <xref
               linkend="example.functor.callable1" />. Note that a
               <emphasis>copy</emphasis> of <varname>c</varname> will be made
               for use when the functor is invoked in the spawned
               thread.</para>

               <example id="example.functor.callable1">
                  <title>Callable Object for Thread Functor (1)</title>

                  <programlisting>class Callable
{
public:
   void operator()()
   {
      // Do some work ...
   }
};

void startThread()
{
   Callable c;
   vpr::Thread* thread = new vpr::Thread(c);
}</programlisting>
               </example>

               <para>A more interesting use of a callable object would be one
               that has state. There are two ways of using a stateful callable
               object. The first is to use data members in the class (or
               struct) declaration that are then accessed by the overload of
               <function>operator()</function>. This is a very simple thing to
               do since having data members in a class is so common.</para>

               <para>The other is to use our old friend Boost.Bind, though it
               is not as simple as in previous cases. Since Boost.Bind is
               designed for binding parameters to function pointers, we have
               to use a proper function pointer—or use Boost.Function. In
               <xref linkend="example.functor.callable2" />, we see how
               Boost.Bind is used to bind the parameter value 5 to the
               invocation of <function>c.operator()(int)</function>. This is
               not nearly as simple as what was shown in <xref
               linkend="example.functor.callable1" />, even if data members of
               <classname>Callable</classname> had to be initialized.</para>

               <example id="example.functor.callable2">
                  <title>Callable Object for Thread Functor (2)</title>

                  <programlisting>class Callable
{
public:
   void operator()(int arg)
   {
      // Do some work ...
   }
};

void startThread()
{
   Callable c;
   vpr::Thread* thread =
      new vpr::Thread(boost::bind(&amp;Callable::operator(), c, 5));
}</programlisting>
               </example>

               <para>Since we are working with a callable object, it stands to
               reason that we should be able to leverage Boost.Function
               somehow. In <xref linkend="example.functor.callable3" />, we
               see how <classname>boost::function&lt;T&gt;</classname> can be
               used to reduce the apparent complexity of binding the parameter
               value 5 to the invocation of
               <function>c.operator()(int)</function>. To some, this may look
               a little more friendly since there is no member function
               pointer required. Ultimately, it requires slightly more typing
               than the previous example. Either way, neither of these
               approaches are very pleasing to the eye, but they do work. One
               of these approaches may be necessary to use a legacy callable
               type with <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>.</para>

               <example id="example.functor.callable3">
                  <title>Callable Object for Thread Functor (3)</title>

                  <programlisting>class Callable
{
public:
   void operator()(int arg)
   {
      // Do some work ...
   }
};

void startThread()
{
   Callable c;
   vpr::Thread* thread =
      new vpr::Thread(boost::bind(boost::function&lt;void(int)&gt;(c), 5));
}</programlisting>
               </example>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Updating from VPR 1.0</title>

               <para>In VPR 1.0, thread functors were handled by subclasses of
               <classname>vpr::BaseThreadFunctor</classname>. While this
               approach worked, it was not anywhere near as flexible as what
               is possible with Boost.Function and Boost.Bind. What has been
               presented here is for VPR 1.1 and beyond. For those users
               updating from VPR 1.0, we now present the simple process of
               changing code using the VPR 1.0 thread API to the VPR 1.1
               API.</para>

               <para>First, the signature for the function called by the
               spawned thread in VPR 1.0 took a single <type>void*</type>
               parameter. In VPR 1.1, the function takes no argument. This
               change was made for two reasons. First, most functions ignored
               this parameter, so it was wasted memory on the stack. Second,
               <type>void*</type> is a notoriously poor choice for a type
               since it can point to anything. C++ is a strongly typed
               language, and we should be taking advantage of that feature.
               However, since the presence of the parameter acknowledged that
               it was often necessary to pass data into the thread function,
               it is still possible to do this using Boost.Bind. What this
               means is that the callable invoked by the functor can have
               <emphasis>any</emphasis> signature, but the default behavior is
               for it to return nothing and take no parameters.</para>

               <para>Next, the types
               <classname>vpr::ThreadNonMemberFunctor</classname>,
               <classname>vpr::ThreadMemberFunctor&lt;T&gt;</classname>, and
               <classname>vpr::ThreadRunFunctor&lt;T&gt;</classname> have been
               removed, as has the header file
               <filename>vpr/Thread/ThreadFunctor.h</filename>. The
               functionality provided by those types has been offloaded to
               <ulink
               url="http://www.boost.org/doc/html/function.html">Boost.Function</ulink>
               and <ulink
               url="http://www.boost.org/libs/bind/bind.html">Boost.Bind</ulink>.
               In so doing, the flexibility of how threads are spawned has
               been increased immensely while actually making it simpler to
               spawn them.</para>

               <para>For uses of
               <classname>vpr::ThreadNonMemberFunctor</classname>, quite a bit
               less code has to be written to spawn a thread. We see in <xref
               linkend="example.functor.static.member.vpr10" /> how this type
               was used with VPR 1.0 to spawn a thread that executed a static
               member function. Then, in <xref
               linkend="example.functor.static.member.vpr11" />, we see the
               equivalent code using the VPR 1.1 (and newer) interface. No
               longer must a functor object to instantiated on the heap and
               stored for later deletion<footnote>
                     <para>Leaking the instantiated functor was an
                     all-too-common error with VPR 1.0.</para>
                  </footnote>. Moreover, there is no need to pass
               <literal>NULL</literal> as the parameter value, though if a
               parameter value is needed, then Boost.Bind must be used. Refer
               to <xref linkend="section.functor.static.member" /> for more
               details on this topic.</para>

               <example id="example.functor.static.member.vpr10">
                  <title>VPR 1.0 Use of Thread Non-Member Functor</title>

                  <programlisting>#include &lt;vpr/Thread/ThreadFunctor.h&gt;
#include &lt;vpr/Thread/Thread.h&gt;

class MyClass_VPR10
{
public:
   void start()
   {
      mFunctor =
         new vpr::ThreadNonMemberFunctor(MyClass_VPR10::run, NULL);
      mThread = new vpr::Thread(mFunctor);
   }

private:
   static void run(void* args)
   {
      // Do some work ...
   }

   vpr::ThreadNonMemberFunctor* mFunctor;
   vpr::Thread* mThread;
};</programlisting>
               </example>

               <example id="example.functor.static.member.vpr11">
                  <title>Updated Use of Static Member Function for Thread
                  Functor</title>

                  <programlisting>#include &lt;vpr/Thread.h&gt;

class MyClass
{
public:
   void start()
   {
      mThread = new vpr::Thread(MyClass::run);
   }

private:
   static void run()
   {
      // Do some work ...
   }

   vpr::Thread* mThread;
};</programlisting>
               </example>

               <para>To use a non-static member function, either
               <classname>vpr::ThreadMemberFunctor&lt;T&gt;</classname> or
               <classname>vpr::ThreadRunFunctor&lt;T&gt;</classname> was used
               with VPR 1.0, as shown in <xref
               linkend="example.functor.non.static.member.vpr10" />. Now,
               Boost.Bind comes to our rescue and vastly simplifies the code
               needed to accomplish the very same thing. In <xref
               linkend="example.functor.non.static.member.vpr11" />, we see
               just how much less code is required. The nice thing is that the
               parameters that were passed to the
               <classname>vpr::ThreadMemberFunctor&lt;T&gt;</classname>
               constructor are nearly the same as what must be passed to
               <function>boost::bind()</function>. The order for the
               <varname>this</varname> pointer and the member function pointer
               are simply reversed—and the <literal>NULL</literal> value for
               the function argument is removed. If arguments need to be
               passed to the function, pass them in as arguments to
               <function>boost::bind()</function> after the
               <varname>this</varname> pointer. Refer to <xref
               linkend="section.functor.member" /> for more details on this
               topic.</para>

               <example id="example.functor.non.static.member.vpr10">
                  <title>VPR 1.0 Use of Thread Member Functor</title>

                  <programlisting>#include &lt;vpr/Thread/ThreadFunctor.h&gt;
#include &lt;vpr/Thread/Thread.h&gt;

class MyClass_VPR10
{
public:
   void start()
   {
      mFunctor =
         new vpr::ThreadMemberFunctor&lt;MyClass_VPR10&gt;(
            this, &amp;MyClass_VPR10::run, NUL
         );
      mThread = new vpr::Thread(mFunctor);
   }

private:
   void run(void* args)
   {
      // Do some work ...
   }

   vpr::ThreadMemberFunctor&lt;MyClass_VPR10&gt;* mFunctor;
   vpr::Thread* mThread;
};</programlisting>
               </example>

               <example id="example.functor.non.static.member.vpr11">
                  <title>Updated Use of Member Function for Thread
                  Functor</title>

                  <programlisting>#include &lt;boost/bind.hpp&gt;
#include &lt;vpr/Thread/Thread.h&gt;

class MyClass
{
public:
   void start()
   {
      mThread = new vpr::Thread(boost::bind(&amp;MyClass::run, this));
   }

private:
   void run()
   {
      // Do some work ...
   }

   vpr::Thread* mThread;
};</programlisting>
               </example>
            </section>
         </section>
      </chapter>

      <chapter id="chapter.synchronization">
         <title>Synchronization</title>

         <para>When multiple processes or threads have access to the same
         data, synchronization of reads and writes becomes an important
         concern. For example, if one thread writes to a shared variable when
         another thread is reading, the value read will be corrupted. If two
         threads try to write to the same shared variable at the same time,
         one of the two writes will be lost. These situations can lead to
         unexpected, and often undesirable, program execution. For that
         reason, it is important to understand how to protect access to shared
         data so that the multi-threaded software will execute
         correctly.</para>

         <section id="section.using.vprSemaphore">
            <title>Semaphores: Using
            <classname>vpr::Semaphore</classname></title>

            <indexterm>
               <primary>vpr::Semaphore</primary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>The most important part of multi-threaded programming is
            proper thread synchronization so that access to shared data is
            controlled. Doing so results in consistency among all threads.
            Semaphores are a very common synchronization mechanism and have
            been used widely in concurrent systems. This section describes the
            cross-platform semaphore interface provided with and used by VPR.
            It does not explain what semaphores are or how to use them—it is
            assumed that readers are already familiar with the topic lest they
            probably would not be reading this chapter at all.</para>

            <section>
               <title>High-Level Description</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Semaphore</primary>

                  <secondary>description of</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>As with threads, a cross-platform abstraction layer has
               been written to provide a consistent way to use semaphores on
               all supported platforms. The primary goal behind the interface
               design is to provide the common <emphasis>P</emphasis>
               (acquire) and <emphasis>V</emphasis> (release) operations. The
               interface does include methods for read/write semaphores, but
               as of this writing, that part of the interface is not complete.
               Because of that, the use section does not cover that part of
               the interface. When the implementation is complete, this
               section will be expanded.</para>

               <para>As always, there is a header file that must be included
               to use <classname>vpr::Semaphore</classname>. This time around,
               the file is <filename>vpr/Sync/Semaphore.h</filename>. Do not
               include any of the platform-specific implementation files. That
               is all handled appropriately within
               <filename>vpr/Sync/Semaphore.h</filename>.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Creating a Semaphore</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Semaphore</primary>

                  <secondary>creating</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>When creating a <classname>vpr::Semaphore</classname>
               object, give the initial value that represents the number of
               resources being controlled by the semaphore. If no value is
               given, the default is 1 which of course gives a binary
               semaphore. Binary semaphores are better known as mutexes (see
               <xref linkend="section.using.vprMutex" /> for more information
               about mutex use in VPR). An example of creating a simple
               semaphore to control access to five resources is as
               follows:</para>

               <programlisting>vpr::Semaphore sema(5);</programlisting>

               <para>This creates a semaphore capable of controlling
               concurrent access to five resources. At some point, if there is
               a need to change the number of resources, a method called
               <methodname>reset()</methodname><indexterm>
                     <primary>vpr::Semaphore</primary>

                     <secondary>reset() method</secondary>
                  </indexterm> is provided. Pass the new number of resources,
               and the semaphore object is updated appropriately:</para>

               <programlisting>sema.reset(4);</programlisting>

               <para>The semaphore <varname>sema</varname> now controls access
               to only four resources.</para>

               <para>Creation of a semaphore can fail, and if it does, the
               <classname>vpr::Semaphore</classname> constructor throws an
               exception of type
               <exceptionname>vpr::ResourceException</exceptionname><indexterm>
                     <primary>exceptions</primary>

                     <secondary>vpr::ResourceException</secondary>
                  </indexterm>. If creation of the semaphore succeeds, then
               lock and unlock operations on that semaphore are guaranteed to
               succeed.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Locking a Semaphore</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Semaphore</primary>

                  <secondary>locking</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>When a thread needs to acquire access to shared data, it
               locks a semaphore. In the <classname>vpr::Semaphore</classname>
               interface, this is accomplished using the
               <methodname>acquire()</methodname> method:</para>

               <programlisting>sema.acquire();</programlisting>

               <para>As expected, <methodname>acquire()</methodname> is a
               blocking call, so if the semaphore's value is less than or
               equal to 0, the thread requesting the lock will block until the
               semaphore's value is greater than 0. If the acquisition of the
               semaphore would cause a deadlock (because the thread already
               holds the semaphore lock),
               <exceptionname>vpr::DeadlockException</exceptionname><indexterm>
                     <primary>exceptions</primary>

                     <secondary>vpr::DeadlockException</secondary>
                  </indexterm> is thrown. Otherwise, the method is guaranteed
               to return when the lock is acquired.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Releasing a Locked Semaphore</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Semaphore</primary>

                  <secondary>releasing</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>Finally, when access to the critical section is complete,
               the semaphore is released using the
               <methodname>release()</methodname> method:</para>

               <programlisting>sema.release();</programlisting>

               <para>This method is guaranteed to return successfully.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>The Gory Details</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Semaphore</primary>

                  <secondary>details</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>Those who have read the Gory Details section for
               <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>s will find this section very
               familiar. As with <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>s, there
               are several platform-specific semaphore implementation wrapper
               classes:</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para><classname>vpr::SemaphoreSGI</classname>: A wrapper
                     around IRIX shared-arena semaphores (refer to the
                     <function>usnewsema(3P)</function> and related manual
                     pages for more information)</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para><classname>vpr::SemaphorePosix</classname>: A
                     wrapper around POSIX real-time semaphores (POSIX.1b,
                     formerly POSIX.4)</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para><classname>vpr::SemaphoreNSPR</classname>: An
                     implementation of semaphores using NSPR primitives</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para><classname>vpr::SemaphoreWin32</classname>: A
                     wrapper around Win32 semaphores</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>

               <para>Unlike <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>, however, there
               is no base interface from which these implementations inherit.
               Performance decreases caused by virtual functions are avoided
               this way.</para>

               <para>The semaphore implementation used is chosen when VPR is
               compiled and will always match the thread implementation being
               used. When the VPR build is configured, preprocessor
               <symbol>#define</symbol> statements are made in
               <filename>vpr/vprDefines.h</filename> that describe the
               threading system and thus the semaphores to use. Based on that,
               the header file <filename>vpr/Sync/Semaphore.h</filename> makes
               several <type>typedef</type>s that set up one of the
               platform-specific implementations to act as the
               <classname>vpr::Semaphore</classname> interface. For example,
               if compiling on Linux, the class
               <classname>vpr::SempahorePosix</classname> is
               <type>typedef</type>'d to
               <classname>vpr::Semaphore</classname>. Since the interface is
               consistent among all the wrappers, everything works as though
               that was the way it was written to behave.</para>
            </section>
         </section>

         <section id="section.using.vprMutex">
            <title>Mutual Exclusion: Using
            <classname>vpr::Mutex</classname></title>

            <indexterm>
               <primary>vpr::Mutex</primary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>In addition to cross-platform semaphores, VPR provides an
            abstraction for cross-platform mutexes. Mutexes are a special type
            of semaphore known as a binary semaphore. Exactly one thread can
            hold the lock at any time. This very short section, however, is
            not about mutexes but rather about the
            <classname>vpr::Mutex</classname> interface provided with and used
            by VPR.</para>

            <section>
               <title>High-Level Description</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Mutex</primary>

                  <secondary>description of</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>The cross-platform mutex abstraction in VPR is critical
               for synchronizing access to shared data. Those who have read
               the section on <classname>vpr::Semaphore</classname><indexterm>
                     <primary>classes</primary>

                     <secondary>vpr::Semaphore</secondary>
                  </indexterm> will find this section very, very familiar. The
               interface for <classname>vpr::Mutex</classname> is a subset of
               that for <classname>vpr::Semaphore</classname> since mutexes
               are binary semaphores. They can be locked and unlocked. That is
               all there is to know. The <classname>vpr::Mutex</classname>
               interface does include some methods for read/write mutexes, but
               this implementation is incomplete and is not documented here
               for that reason. When the implementation is finished, this
               documentation will be expanded.</para>

               <para>The header file to include for using
               <classname>vpr::Mutex</classname> is
               <filename>vpr/Sync/Mutex.h</filename>. As with other classes
               discussed in this chapter, it is important not to include the
               platform-specific header files.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Creating a Mutex</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Mutex</primary>

                  <secondary>creating</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>When creating a <classname>vpr::Mutex</classname> object,
               there are no special parameters to pass or considerations to be
               made. An example of creating a mutex is as follows:</para>

               <programlisting>vpr::Mutex mutex;</programlisting>

               <para>Creation of a mutex can fail, and if it does, the
               <classname>vpr::Mutex</classname> constructor throws an
               exception of type
               <exceptionname>vpr::ResourceException</exceptionname><indexterm>
                     <primary>exceptions</primary>

                     <secondary>vpr::ResourceException</secondary>
                  </indexterm>. If creation of the mutex succeeds, then lock
               and unlock operations on that mutex are guaranteed to
               succeed.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Locking a Mutex</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Mutex</primary>

                  <secondary>locking</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>When a thread needs to acquire access to shared data, it
               can lock a mutex. In the <classname>vpr::Mutex</classname>
               interface, this is accomplished using the
               <methodname>acquire()</methodname> method:</para>

               <programlisting>mutex.acquire();</programlisting>

               <para>As expected, <methodname>acquire()</methodname> is a
               blocking call, so if the mutex is already locked by another
               thread, the thread requesting the lock will block until the
               mutex is released by the other thread. If the acquisition of
               the mutex would cause a deadlock (because the thread already
               holds the mutex),
               <exceptionname>vpr::DeadlockException</exceptionname><indexterm>
                     <primary>exceptions</primary>

                     <secondary>vpr::DeadlockException</secondary>
                  </indexterm> is thrown. Otherwise, the method is guaranteed
               to return when the lock is acquired.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Attempting to Lock a Mutex</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Mutex</primary>

                  <secondary>locking</secondary>

                  <tertiary>without blocking</tertiary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>If there is a need to lock a mutex only when the call
               would <emphasis>not</emphasis> block, a method is provided to
               do this. It is called <methodname>tryAcquire()</methodname>,
               and it will not block if the mutex is already locked. It works
               as follows:</para>

               <programlisting>const bool locked = mutex.tryAcquire();</programlisting>

               <para>If the mutex is locked, <constant>true</constant> is
               returned. Otherwise, <constant>false</constant> is returned.
               The call does not block.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Testing the State of a Mutex</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Mutex</primary>

                  <secondary>testing state</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>In addition to conditional locking, the state of a mutex
               can be tested to see if it is locked or unlocked. This is done
               using the <methodname>test()</methodname> method as
               follows:</para>

               <programlisting>const bool locked = mutex.test();</programlisting>

               <para>If the mutex is <emphasis>not</emphasis> locked,
               <constant>false</constant> is returned. Otherwise,
               <constant>true</constant> is returned.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Releasing a Locked Mutex</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Mutex</primary>

                  <secondary>releasing</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>When access to the critical section is complete, a locked
               mutex is released using the <methodname>release()</methodname>
               method:</para>

               <programlisting>mutex.release();</programlisting>

               <para>This method is guaranteed to return successfully.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>The Gory Details</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::Mutex</primary>

                  <secondary>details</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>Those who have read the Gory Details sections for
               <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>s or for
               <classname>vpr::Semaphore</classname>s will find this last
               section very familiar (and probably uninteresting at this
               point). As with <classname>vpr::Thread</classname>s and
               <classname>vpr::Semaphore</classname>s, there are several
               platform-specific mutex implementation wrapper classes:</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para><classname>vpr::MutexSGI</classname>: A wrapper
                     around IRIX shared-arena mutexes (refer to the
                     <function>usnewlock(3P)</function> and related manual
                     pages for more information)</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para><classname>vpr::MutexPosix</classname>: A wrapper
                     around POSIX real-time mutexes (POSIX.1b, formerly
                     POSIX.4)</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para><classname>vpr::MutexNSPR</classname>: A wrapper
                     around NSPR mutexes</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para><classname>vpr::MutexWin32</classname>: A wrapper
                     around Win32 mutexes</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>

               <para>Similar to <classname>vpr::Semaphore</classname>, there
               is no base interface from which these implementations inherit.
               Performance issues caused by virtual functions are avoided by
               doing this.</para>

               <para>The mutex implementation used is chosen when VPR is
               compiled and will always match the thread implementation being
               used. When the VPR build is configured, preprocessor
               <symbol>#define</symbol> statements are made in
               <filename>vpr/vprDefines.h</filename> that describe the
               threading system and thus the mutexes to use. Based on that,
               the header file <filename>vpr/Sync/Mutex.h</filename> makes
               several <type>typedef</type>s that set up one of the
               platform-specific implementations to act as the
               <classname>vpr::Mutex</classname> interface. For example, if
               compiling on Solaris, the class
               <classname>vpr::MutexPosix</classname> is
               <type>typedef</type>'d to be <classname>vpr::Mutex</classname>.
               Since the interface is consistent among all the wrappers,
               everything works as though that was the way it was written to
               behave.</para>
            </section>
         </section>

         <section id="section.using.vprCondVar">
            <title>Condition Variables: Using
            <classname>vpr::CondVar</classname></title>

            <indexterm>
               <primary>vpr::CondVar</primary>
            </indexterm>

            <para>Condition variables are a helpful extension to mutexes.
            Every condition variable has an associated mutex, and thus they
            can be used to control mutually exclusive access to some resource.
            A condition variable adds the ability to test a condition and wait
            for its state to change in some meaningful way. Waiting threads
            are awakened when the state of the variable changes or when a time
            interval expires. When awoken, the relevant condition is tested.
            If the state has changed to the desired result, the thread
            continues its execution. If not, it goes back into the waiting
            state until it is awakened again to repeat the process.</para>

            <section>
               <title>High-Level Description</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::CondVar</primary>

                  <secondary>description of</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>The interface for
               <classname>vpr::CondVar</classname><indexterm>
                     <primary>classes</primary>

                     <secondary>vpr::CondVar</secondary>
                  </indexterm> is very similar to that of
               <classname>vpr::Mutex</classname><indexterm>
                     <primary>classes</primary>

                     <secondary>vpr::Mutex</secondary>
                  </indexterm>. This is because every instance of
               <classname>vpr::CondVar</classname> contains an instance of
               <classname>vpr::Mutex</classname>. Thus, acquiring and
               releasing a condition variable actually acquires and releases
               the contained mutex.</para>

               <para>The header file to include for using
               <classname>vpr::CondVar</classname> is
               <filename>vpr/Sync/CondVar.h</filename>. As with other classes
               discussed in this chapter, it is important not to include the
               platform-specific header files.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Creating a Condition Variable</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::CondVar</primary>

                  <secondary>creating</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>When creating a <classname>vpr::CondVar</classname>
               object, there are no special parameters to pass or
               considerations to be made. An example of creating a condition
               variable is as follows:</para>

               <programlisting>vpr::CondVar cv;</programlisting>

               <para>Creation of a condition variable can fail, and if it
               does, the <classname>vpr::CondVar</classname> constructor
               throws an exception of type
               <exceptionname>vpr::ResourceException</exceptionname><indexterm>
                     <primary>exceptions</primary>

                     <secondary>vpr::ResourceException</secondary>
                  </indexterm>. If creation of the condition variable
               succeeds, then lock and unlock operations on that condition
               variable are guaranteed to succeed.</para>

               <para>In addition to the <classname>vpr::CondVar</classname>
               instance, there is usually some associated variable whose value
               will be tested and modified by various threads. For our
               purposes, we will use a boolean variable:</para>

               <programlisting>bool state_var;</programlisting>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Locking a Condition Variable</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::CondVar</primary>

                  <secondary>locking</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>When a thread needs to acquire access to shared data, it
               can lock a condition variable. In the
               <classname>vpr::CondVar</classname> interface, this is
               accomplished using the <methodname>acquire()</methodname>
               method:</para>

               <programlisting>cv.acquire();</programlisting>

               <para>As expected, <methodname>acquire()</methodname> is a
               blocking call, so if the condition variable's mutex is already
               locked by another thread, the thread requesting the lock will
               block until the mutex is released by the other thread. If the
               acquisition of the condition variable's lock would cause a
               deadlock (because the thread already holds the lock),
               <exceptionname>vpr::DeadlockException</exceptionname><indexterm>
                     <primary>exceptions</primary>

                     <secondary>vpr::DeadlockException</secondary>
                  </indexterm> is thrown. Otherwise, the method is guaranteed
               to return when the lock is acquired.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Attempting to Lock a Condition Variable</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::CondVar</primary>

                  <secondary>locking</secondary>

                  <tertiary>without blocking</tertiary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>If there is a need to lock a condition variable's mutex
               only when the call would <emphasis>not</emphasis> block, a
               method is provided to do this. It is called
               <methodname>tryAcquire()</methodname>, and it will not block if
               the mutex is already locked. It works as follows:</para>

               <programlisting>const bool locked = cv.tryAcquire();</programlisting>

               <para>If the condition variable's mutex is locked,
               <constant>true</constant> is returned. Otherwise,
               <constant>false</constant> is returned. The call does not
               block.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Releasing a Locked Condition Variable</title>

               <indexterm>
                  <primary>vpr::CondVar</primary>

                  <secondary>releasing</secondary>
               </indexterm>

               <para>When access to the critical section is complete, a locked
               condition variable is released using the
               <methodname>release()</methodname> method:</para>

               <programlisting>cv.release();</programlisting>

               <para>This method is guaranteed to return successfully.</para>

               <para>Prior to calling
               <methodname>vpr::CondVar::release()</methodname>, it is almost
               always necessary to call
               <methodname>vpr::CondVar::signal()</methodname> (or
               <methodname>vpr::CondVar::broadcast()</methodname>) to inform
               any waiting threads that the condition on which they are
               waiting may have changed. The next section describes this
               procedure in greater detail.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Putting Condition Variables to Use</title>

               <para>So far, we have seen how to lock and unlock a condition
               variable, but we have not seen how to <emphasis>use</emphasis>
               a condition variable. Let us say that we have two threads
               running concurrently. One thread is performing an operation,
               and the other thread must wait until that operation is
               complete. Condition variables work wonderfully in such a
               situation. For the following description, we will call the
               first thread the worker thread and the second thread the
               waiting thread. For the example, we will use the condition
               variable <varname>cv</varname> and the boolean flag
               <varname>state_var</varname>, introduced above. Initially,
               <varname>state_var</varname> will be set to
               <literal>false</literal> to indicate that the worker thread has
               not done its job yet.</para>

               <section>
                  <title>The Waiting Thread</title>

                  <para>While it may seem more logical to focus on the worker
                  thread first, our example will flow better if we start with
                  the waiting thread. That way, the waiting thread can be in
                  its waiting state (at least conceptually) when we talk about
                  the worker thread. The waiting thread will of course be
                  waiting for the condition (the value of
                  <varname>state_var</varname>) to change.</para>

                  <para>In order for the waiting thread to be waiting, it must
                  have tested the value of <varname>state_var</varname>.
                  Because <varname>state_var</varname> is shared data, the
                  condition variable must be locked before it can read the
                  current value of <varname>state_var</varname>. Depending on
                  the current value, the waiting thread will either wait or
                  continue its execution. The usual process for doing this is
                  shown below:</para>

                  <programlisting>cv.acquire();
{
   while ( state_var == false )
   {
      cv.wait();
   }
}
cv.release();</programlisting>

                  <para>The call to
                  <methodname>vpr::CondVar::wait()</methodname> is special:
                  the mutex associated with <varname>cv</varname> is unlocked
                  so that other threads can manipulate
                  <varname>state_var</varname>, but the waiting thread will
                  block. When the waiting thread is awakened, it will regain
                  the lock it previously held on the condition variable. The
                  thread will test <varname>state_var</varname> again, and if
                  its value is now <literal>true</literal>, the waiting thread
                  will exit the loop and release the condition variable. If
                  the value of <varname>state_var</varname> is still
                  <literal>false</literal>, the waiting thread will go back to
                  its waiting state.</para>
               </section>

               <section>
                  <title>The Worker Thread</title>

                  <para>The worker thread has some task to perform that is
                  critical to the proper execution of the two active threads.
                  In order to inform the waiting thread about the current
                  status of the task, we will use the condition variable
                  <varname>cv</varname> and the boolean flag
                  <varname>state_var</varname>, shown above. While the worker
                  thread is performing its task, it must hold the lock on the
                  condition variable, as shown below:</para>

                  <programlisting>cv.acquire();
{
   // Perform our critical task ...

   state_var = true;
   cv.signal();
}
cv.release();</programlisting>

                  <para>Once the <quote>critical task</quote> is complete, the
                  value of <varname>state_var</varname> is changed to
                  <literal>true</literal> to indicate that the job is done.
                  Then, <methodname>vpr::CondVar::signal()</methodname> is
                  invoked. This will wake up the waiting thread, and the
                  condition variable is released. The result is that the
                  waiting thread will wake up to discover that the job has
                  been completed, and it will continue with its
                  execution.</para>

                  <note>
                     <para>The method
                     <methodname>vpr::CondVar::signal()</methodname> will wake
                     up at most one waiting thread. Which thread is awakened
                     is determined by the operating system scheduling
                     algorithms. To wake up all threads, use
                     <methodname>vpr::CondVar::broadcast()</methodname>. Of
                     course, each waiting thread will have to wait its turn to
                     get exclusive access to test the condition, but this can
                     be useful when it is known that many threads are all
                     waiting on the same result.</para>
                  </note>
               </section>
            </section>
         </section>
      </chapter>

      <chapter id="chapter.signal.handling">
         <title>Signal Handling</title>

         <para>VPR contains an abstraction for allowing cross-platform signal
         handling. The interface is based on that used in the <ulink
         url="http://www.cs.wustl.edu/~schmidt/ACE.html">ADAPTIVE
         Communication Environment</ulink> (ACE). The basic idea is that a set
         of signals is associated with a signal handler. The handler is
         registered with the operating system, and whenever one of the signals
         in the signal set is delivered to the process (thread), the handler
         is invoked.</para>

         <para>The signal set is encapsulated within an instance of
         <classname>vpr::SignalSet</classname>, and a signal handler is simply
         a callback function. The two are combined using the concept of a
         signal action which is implemented in the class
         <classname>vpr::SignalAction</classname>. The signal action registers
         the handler for the given set of signals with the operating
         system.</para>
      </chapter>
   </part>

   <part>
      <title>Miscellaneous Utilities</title>

      <chapter id="chapter.sim.sockets">
         <title>Simulated Sockets</title>

         <para>The simulated sockets (often referred to as <quote>sim
         sockets</quote>) in VPR are designed to allow testing of network
         algorithms without requiring the use of a physical computer network.
         All communication between <quote>nodes</quote> occurs in memory by
         simulating the actual process of sending and receiving data on a
         network. This is done through a discrete event simulation where the
         events are the arrival of a message (packet) at a node in the
         network. Because we have chosen the message arrival event as the step
         size, the simulation can proceed at a very high rate. Within the
         network, timing calculations are performed so that messages are
         delivered based on the constraints of the network (bandwidth and
         transmission latency are the primary constraints in the current
         version).</para>

         <section>
            <title>Sim Socket Interface</title>

            <para>The interface for sim sockets is identical to that of the
            operating system abstraction layer for sockets, namely
            <classname>vpr::Socket</classname>,
            <classname>vpr::SocketStream</classname>, and
            <classname>vpr::SocketDatagram</classname>. Indeed, user code
            actually uses instances of those classes. The use of sim sockets
            versus real sockets is made when VPR is compiled, in the same way
            that the threading abstraction (NSPR versus POSIX versus Win32) is
            chosen at compile time. Ideally, user code should not have to
            change at all to use sim sockets, thus making it possible to test
            network algorithms with exactly the same code as would be used
            with real sockets.</para>

            <para>Of course, the real world is not ideal. While it is very
            true that most code does not have to change to use sim sockets,
            there is one major exception. Because the sim sockets are based on
            an event-driven simulation, something must be driving the
            simulation. When using sim sockets, user code must have a separate
            thread running that makes use of the singleton
            <classname>vpr::sim::Controller</classname>. The thread contains a
            loop that invokes
            <methodname>vpr::sim::Controller::processNextEvent()</methodname>
            or <methodname>vpr::sim::Controller::processEvents()</methodname>
            at each iteration.</para>

            <para>Another aspect of the current sim socket implementation is
            that it is designed to execute in a single thread using
            non-blocking socket semantics. We have chosen this design because
            we felt that the complexity of writing a multi-threaded socket
            simulation that allowed sockets to block would be far too
            difficult. Future versions may allow blocking or non-blocking
            semantics to be chosen by user code, but such a feature is not
            expected in the near future.</para>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Sim Socket Implementation</title>

            <para>The implementation of the sim socket code is based on the
            <ulink url="http://www.boost.org/libs/graph/doc/">Boost Graph
            Library</ulink>. Vertices represent network nodes (also known as
            hosts), and edges represent network lines. The network topology is
            constructed using output from the <ulink
            url="http://www.geocities.com/ResearchTriangle/3867/sourcecode.html">Tiers
            software</ulink>. Once constructed, an in-memory network serves as
            the backend for the higher level socket API. Messages (blocks of
            memory) are passed between nodes until they reach their
            destination.</para>
         </section>
      </chapter>

      <chapter id="chapter.guid">
         <title>Globally Unique Identifiers</title>

         <para>Globally unique identifiers (GUIDs), also known as universally
         unique identifiers (UUIDs), provide 128-bit identifiers that are
         guaranteed to be unique (speaking statistically). These are based on
         an Internet draft written by Paul L. Leach at Microsoft. The
         likelihood of two identifiers being the same varies depending on the
         generation mechanism used. In VPR, we define the type
         <classname>vpr::GUID</classname><indexterm>
               <primary>classes</primary>

               <secondary>vpr::GUID</secondary>
            </indexterm> as a cross-platform wrapper around the process of
         generating GUIDs and the process of serializing GUIDs for network
         transmission.</para>

         <section>
            <title>GUID Creation</title>

            <para>Creating GUIDs is easy. The default
            <classname>vpr::GUID</classname> constructor will create a
            <quote>null</quote> GUID. A fresh identifier can be generated by
            invoking the method <methodname>vpr::GUID::generate()</methodname>
            on the newly created null GUID. To create a constant GUID, the
            string representation of the GUID can be passed to the
            <classname>vpr::GUID</classname> constructor. Such a string can be
            created using a command-line utility such as
            <command>uuidgen</command>.</para>

            <para>The GUID specification describes creating identifiers using
            a <quote>namespace</quote> concept. The last
            <classname>vpr::GUID</classname> constructor takes two arguments:
            a namespace GUID and a string name. The namespace GUID is the same
            for all GUIDs created in the namespace. The string name is used to
            create a hash value that makes the GUID unique for that name
            within the namespace. The full algorithm and semantics of GUID
            namespaces are beyond the scope of this document, but the
            functionality is provided to offer a complete (cross-platform)
            implementation of the specification.</para>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>GUID Operations</title>

            <para>The <classname>vpr::GUID</classname> interface provides
            overloaded methods for comparison operations (equality and
            less-than) between two <classname>vpr::GUID</classname> instances.
            A function is also provided for generating a hash value for a
            given GUID so that they may be used in STL indexed
            containers.</para>

            <para>Serialization of <classname>vpr::GUID</classname> objects
            uses the same mechanisms described in <xref
            linkend="chapter.data.marshaling" />.</para>
         </section>
      </chapter>

      <chapter id="chapter.intervals">
         <title>Intervals</title>

         <para>The <classname>vpr::Interval</classname><indexterm>
               <primary>classes</primary>

               <secondary>vpr::Interval</secondary>
            </indexterm> class defines a high-resolution interval that is
         based on an unsigned, always-increasing counter. These intervals are
         only valid for about twelve (12) hours, which implies that they are
         only useful for a range of roughly six hours. When the internal
         counter reaches its maximum value, the interval overflows. The
         overloaded <methodname>operator-</methodname> will deal with
         overflows so that two intervals can be compared.</para>

         <section>
            <title>Interval Creation</title>

            <para>Intervals are constructed with a constant value and a time
            unit, either microseconds, milliseconds, or seconds. Otherwise, an
            empty interval (whose internal counter is initialized to zero) can
            be created using the default value. The internal counter of any
            interval instance is modified using one of the
            <quote>setter</quote> methods.</para>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Interval Operations</title>

            <para>The set methods take various forms. For example, the method
            <methodname>vpr::Interval::setNow()</methodname> sets the internal
            counter to the current time. The variants of
            <methodname>vpr::Interval::set()</methodname> (including
            <methodname>vpr::Interval::setf()</methodname> and
            <methodname>vpr::Interval::setd()</methodname>) set the counter to
            an explicit value. As with the constructor, these take a second
            argument that determines the time units. There are helper methods
            such as <methodname>vpr::Interval::sec(vpr::Uint64)</methodname>
            and <methodname>vpr::Interval::usecf(float)</methodname> that use
            the correct time unit internally. Use of these can be less error
            prone than giving both the time and the unit, but which version to
            use is up to the user.</para>

            <para>The value of an interval is queried to return using a
            specific time unit. For example,
            <methodname>vpr::Interval::msecf()</methodname> returns the
            interval value as a floating-point number representing
            milliseconds. The <quote>base</quote> counter value can be
            returned. Conceptually, this is a unit-less value. Strictly
            speaking, its units are defined by platform-specific details that
            determine how accurate the counter can be.</para>

            <para>Mathematical operations can be performed on
            <classname>vpr::Interval</classname> instances. The allow
            addition, subtraction, and comparison. As mentioned above, the
            overloaded subtraction operator will deal with overflow to allow
            proper comparison of two <classname>vpr::Interval</classname>
            instances. However, users should always bear in mind the fact that
            the intervals are only good for ranges of about six (6)
            hours.</para>
         </section>
      </chapter>

      <chapter id="chapter.singleton">
         <title>Singletons</title>

         <para>A <firstterm>singleton</firstterm> is a common design pattern
         <xref linkend="ref.design.patterns" />. VPR offers two ways to
         implement a singleton, both of which come from the header
         <filename>vpr/Util/Singleton.h</filename>. Libraries such as <ulink
         url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/loki-lib/">Loki</ulink> offer
         other approaches.</para>

         <para>The first way of creating a singleton using VPR is to use the C
         preprocessor approach. In this case, we utilize two macros:
         <literal>vprSingletonHeader()</literal><indexterm>
               <primary>macros</primary>

               <secondary>vprSingletonHeader</secondary>
            </indexterm> and <literal>vprSingletonImp()</literal><indexterm>
               <primary>macros</primary>

               <secondary>vprSingletonImp</secondary>
            </indexterm>. One goes in the class declaration (in the header
         file), and the other goes with the class definition (in the
         <filename>.cpp</filename> file). The basic usage of these macros is
         shown in <xref linkend="example.vprSingletonHeader" /> and <xref
         linkend="example.vprSingletonImp" />.</para>

         <example id="example.vprSingletonHeader">
            <title>Use of <literal>vprSingletonHeader()</literal></title>

            <programlisting>#include &lt;boost/noncopyable.hpp&gt;
#include &lt;vpr/Util/Singleton.h&gt;

class MySingleton : boost::noncopyable
{
public:
   // Public operations ...
   void doSomething();

private:
   // Prevent instantiation by user code.
   MySingleton()
   {
      // Some constructor actions ...
   }

   // Bring in the singleton declaration pieces.
   vprSingletonHeader(MySingleton);
};</programlisting>
         </example>

         <example id="example.vprSingletonImp">
            <title>Use of <literal>vprSingletonImp()</literal></title>

            <programlisting>#include "MySingleton.h"

// Bring in the singleton definition pieces.
vprSingletonImp(MySingleton);

void MySingleton::doSomething()
{
   // Do something ...
}</programlisting>
         </example>

         <para>In some cases, an object may need to perform some
         initialization steps after being instantiated. In that case, use the
         macro <literal>vprSingletonHeaderWithInitFunc()</literal><indexterm>
               <primary>macros</primary>

               <secondary>vprSingletonHeaderWithInitFunc</secondary>
            </indexterm> instead of <literal>vprSingletonHeader()</literal>
         and <literal>vprSingletonImpWithInitFunc()</literal><indexterm>
               <primary>macros</primary>

               <secondary>vprSingletonImpWithInitFunc</secondary>
            </indexterm> instead of <literal>vprSingletonImp()</literal>. An
         example of this is shown in <xref
         linkend="example.vprSingletonHeaderWithInitFunc" /> and <xref
         linkend="example.vprSingletonImpWithInitFunc" />. The initialization
         method must take no parameters and return nothing.</para>

         <example id="example.vprSingletonHeaderWithInitFunc">
            <title>Use of
            <literal>vprSingletonHeaderWithInitFunc()</literal></title>

            <programlisting>#include &lt;boost/noncopyable.hpp&gt;
#include &lt;vpr/Util/Singleton.h&gt;

class MySingleton : boost::noncopyable
{
public:
   // Public operations ...
   void doSomething();

private:
   // Prevent instantiation by user code.
   MySingleton()
   {
      // Some constructor actions ...
   }

   void init()
   {
      // Perform initialization operations ...
   }

   // Bring in the singleton declaration pieces.
   vprSingletonHeaderWithInitFunc(MySingleton, init);
};</programlisting>
         </example>

         <example id="example.vprSingletonImpWithInitFunc">
            <title>Use of
            <literal>vprSingletonImpWithInitFunc()</literal></title>

            <programlisting>#include "MySingleton.h"

// Bring in the singleton definition pieces.
vprSingletonImp(MySingleton);

void MySingleton::doSomething()
{
   // Do something ...
}</programlisting>
         </example>

         <para>In VPR 1.1 and beyond, the destructor for singleton objects is
         called when the application exits. This can result in some
         undesirable behavior if one singleton depends on another, thus
         meaning that the order in which they are deleted can make a
         difference. Without any specific ordering being imposed, singleton
         objects are deleted in the reverse order in which they were
         instantiated. Since it is not always possible to control the order of
         instantiation, it can be useful to control the order of destruction.
         This can be done by setting the <quote>lifetime</quote> or
         <quote>longevity</quote> of a singleton. The higher the longevity,
         the later that the singleton will be deleted when the application is
         exiting. This is accomplished using either
         <literal>vprSingletonImpLifetime()</literal><indexterm>
               <primary>macros</primary>

               <secondary>vprSingletonImpLifetime</secondary>
            </indexterm> or
         <literal>vprSingletonImpLifetimeWithInitFunc()</literal><indexterm>
               <primary>macros</primary>

               <secondary>vprSingletonImpLifetimeWithInitFunc</secondary>
            </indexterm>. The macro used must be paired with either
         <literal>vprSingletonHeader()</literal> or
         <literal>vprSingletonHeaderWithInitFunc()</literal>. Usage of
         <literal>vprSingletonImpLifetime()</literal> is shown in <xref
         linkend="example.vprSingletonImpLifetime" />.</para>

         <example id="example.vprSingletonImpLifetime">
            <title>Use of <literal>vprSingletonImpLifetime()</literal></title>

            <programlisting>#include "MySingleton.h"

// Bring in the singleton definition pieces. Delete it early
// in the application exit process.
vprSingletonImpLifetime(MySingleton, 10);

void MySingleton::doSomething()
{
   // Do something ...
}</programlisting>
         </example>

         <para>The other approach uses a template class called
         <classname>vpr::Singleton&lt;T&gt;<indexterm>
               <primary>classes</primary>

               <secondary>vpr::Singleton&lt;T&gt;</secondary>
            </indexterm></classname>. An example of its use is shown in <xref
         linkend="example.vpr.Singleton.template" />.</para>

         <example id="example.vpr.Singleton.template">
            <title>Use of
            <classname>vpr::Singleton&lt;T&gt;</classname></title>

            <programlisting linenumbering="numbered">#include &lt;boost/noncopyable.hpp&gt;
#include &lt;vpr/Util/Singleton.h&gt;

class MySingleton
   : public vpr::Singleton&lt;MySingleton&gt;
   , boost::noncopyable
{
public:
   // Public operations ...
   void doSomething()
   {
      // Do something ...
   }

private:
   // Required so that vpr::Singleton can instantiate this class.
   friend class vpr::Singleton&lt;MySingleton&gt;;

   // Prevent instantiation by user code.
   MySingleton()
   {
      // Some constructor actions ...
   }
};</programlisting>
         </example>

         <warning>
            <para>Singletons implemented using
            <classname>vpr::Singleton&lt;T&gt;</classname> do not work across
            DLLs on <productname class="registered">Microsoft
            Windows</productname> or shared libraries
            (<filename>.dylib</filename> files) on Mac OS X. If the singleton
            is for internal use only, such as in the case of an application,
            then using <classname>vpr::Singleton&lt;T&gt;</classname> is fine.
            Otherwise, the C preprocessor approach must be used.</para>
         </warning>

         <para>In all singleton implementations, getting a reference to the
         singleton object (and calling the
         <methodname>doSomething()</methodname> method) is then done using the
         following syntax:</para>

         <programlisting>MySingleton::instance()-&gt;doSomething();</programlisting>
      </chapter>

      <chapter id="chapter.factory">
         <title>Factories</title>

         <para></para>
      </chapter>

      <chapter>
         <title id="chapter.perfmon">Performance Monitoring</title>

         <para>The Performance Monitoring part of the VPR library enables
         users to obtain and use performance metrics easily. The basic concept
         for VPR's performance monitoring is that there is a manager that is
         in charge of keeping track of all the different data coming in. This
         is called the Profile Manager (from the class
         <classname>vpr::ProfileManager</classname>).</para>

         <para>The Profile Manager keeps a one-to-many tree of the different
         metrics (instances of <classname>vpr::ProfileSample</classname>)
         being used. When the Profile Manager starts profiling a section of
         code, it looks to see if it had been profiled before and if so adds
         another sample to that profile otherwise it is added to the tree .
         Upon the completion of the function the destructor asks the Profile
         Manager to stop profiling.</para>

         <para>Along with being able to keep track of the named profiles,
         there is an ability to keep a specified number of samples so the
         Profile Manager will keep more than just the last sample obtained.
         There are also two macros provided for ease of use and to minimize
         the intrusiveness of the API. These are the
         <methodname>VPR_PROFILE_GUARD(name)</methodname> and
         <methodname>VPR_PROFILE_GUARD_HISTORY(name, queue_size)</methodname>
         macros. These can be simply added at the top of functions that are to
         be profiled. Also, these macros give the ability at compile time to
         disable all profiling by way of the variable
         <varname>VPR_DISABLE_PROFILE</varname>. All of the profiling data is
         obtained by using the <classname>vpr::Interval</classname> class to
         measure the time spent in a particular piece of code using the
         highest precision timer available to the VPR.</para>

         <para>Calls may be made to
         <methodname>vpr::ProfileManager::startProfile("name")</methodname>
         and to <methodname>vpr::ProfileManager::stopProfile()</methodname> so
         that just a certain part of the code may be profiled. A name needs to
         be specified when a profile is started but when
         <methodname>vpr::ProfileManager::stopProfile()</methodname> is called
         it simply stops the last profile that was started. Starts and stops
         can be nested within a function or even a program as long as their is
         a corresponding start with every stop.</para>

         <para>An iterator class is provided to allow the user to use the
         captured data for statistic calculations, overloaded output stream
         operator for printing out, etc. The iterator class is what the user
         can use to collect information about the tree structure and
         interpreting the tree structure for hierarchical calls within the
         profiles. For profiles that contain more than one sample there are
         functions provided to get the short term average. Also, to quickly
         just print out the statistics at any point the user may call
         <function>VPR_PROFILE_RESULTS()</function> and the current status of
         all profiles will be printed out via
         <classname>vpr::DEBUG</classname>.</para>
      </chapter>
   </part>

   <part>
      <title>Appendices</title>

      <appendix id="appendix.io.impl">
         <title>I/O Implementation Information</title>

         <para>All of the buffered I/O code is based around a Bridge pattern
         <xref linkend="ref.design.patterns" />, though the actual
         implementation of the bridge is not as straightforward as described
         in the literature. However, the implementation can be divided into
         the platform-specific wrapper classes (e.g.,
         <classname>vpr::SocketStreamImplNSPR</classname><indexterm>
               <primary>classes</primary>

               <secondary>vpr::SocketStreamImplNSPR</secondary>
            </indexterm>) and <quote>containers</quote> for those classes
         (e.g., <classname>vpr::SocketStream_t&lt;T&gt;</classname><indexterm>
               <primary>classes</primary>

               <secondary>vpr::SocketStream_t&lt;T&gt;</secondary>
            </indexterm>). Ultimately, the type seen in user code (e.g.,
         <classname>vpr::SocketStream</classname><indexterm>
               <primary>classes</primary>

               <secondary>vpr::SocketStream</secondary>
            </indexterm>) is a <token>typedef</token> for a specific container
         class instantiation.</para>

         <para>The <token>typedef</token> is based on the concept of a
         platform-specific <quote>domain</quote>, as specified in the header
         <filename>vpr/vprDomain.h</filename>. These domains allow a form of
         parameterization of VPR components using the C preprocessor. For
         example, when compiling on IRIX with POSIX threads, the domain
         defines the use of the POSIX threading subsystem, BSD sockets, and
         termios serial I/O. When compiling on Windows, where a mixture of
         NSPR and the Win32 API is used, the domain specifies the use of
         native Win32 serial I/O and NSPR for socket I/O. Moreover, the
         simulated sockets can be mixed with any of the threading subsystems
         using this paradigm.</para>
      </appendix>

      <appendix id="appendix.gfdl">
         <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>

         <subtitle>Version 1.2, November 2002</subtitle>

         <blockquote id="fsf-copyright">
            <title>FSF Copyright note</title>

            <para>Copyright (C) 2000,2001,2002 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
            59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307 USA Everyone is
            permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies of this license
            document, but changing it is not allowed.</para>
         </blockquote>

         <section id="gfdl-0">
            <title>PREAMBLE</title>

            <para>The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook,
            or other functional and useful document "free" in the sense of
            freedom: to assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and
            redistribute it, with or without modifying it, either commercially
            or noncommercially. Secondarily, this License preserves for the
            author and publisher a way to get credit for their work, while not
            being considered responsible for modifications made by
            others.</para>

            <para>This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that
            derivative works of the document must themselves be free in the
            same sense. It complements the GNU General Public License, which
            is a copyleft license designed for free software.</para>

            <para>We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals
            for free software, because free software needs free documentation:
            a free program should come with manuals providing the same
            freedoms that the software does. But this License is not limited
            to software manuals; it can be used for any textual work,
            regardless of subject matter or whether it is published as a
            printed book. We recommend this License principally for works
            whose purpose is instruction or reference.</para>
         </section>

         <section id="gfdl-1">
            <title>APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS</title>

            <para id="gfdl-doc">This License applies to any manual or other
            work, in any medium, that contains a notice placed by the
            copyright holder saying it can be distributed under the terms of
            this License. Such a notice grants a world-wide, royalty-free
            license, unlimited in duration, to use that work under the
            conditions stated herein. The "Document", below, refers to any
            such manual or work. Any member of the public is a licensee, and
            is addressed as "you". You accept the license if you copy, modify
            or distribute the work in a way requiring permission under
            copyright law.</para>

            <para id="gfdl-mod-ver">A "Modified Version" of the Document means
            any work containing the Document or a portion of it, either copied
            verbatim, or with modifications and/or translated into another
            language.</para>

            <para id="gfdl-secnd-sect">A "Secondary Section" is a named
            appendix or a front-matter section of the Document that deals
            exclusively with the relationship of the publishers or authors of
            the Document to the Document's overall subject (or to related
            matters) and contains nothing that could fall directly within that
            overall subject. (Thus, if the Document is in part a textbook of
            mathematics, a Secondary Section may not explain any mathematics.)
            The relationship could be a matter of historical connection with
            the subject or with related matters, or of legal, commercial,
            philosophical, ethical or political position regarding
            them.</para>

            <para id="gfdl-inv-sect">The "Invariant Sections" are certain
            Secondary Sections whose titles are designated, as being those of
            Invariant Sections, in the notice that says that the Document is
            released under this License. If a section does not fit the above
            definition of Secondary then it is not allowed to be designated as
            Invariant. The Document may contain zero Invariant Sections. If
            the Document does not identify any Invariant Sections then there
            are none.</para>

            <para id="gfdl-cov-text">The "Cover Texts" are certain short
            passages of text that are listed, as Front-Cover Texts or
            Back-Cover Texts, in the notice that says that the Document is
            released under this License. A Front-Cover Text may be at most 5
            words, and a Back-Cover Text may be at most 25 words.</para>

            <para id="gfdl-transparent">A "Transparent" copy of the Document
            means a machine-readable copy, represented in a format whose
            specification is available to the general public, that is suitable
            for revising the document straightforwardly with generic text
            editors or (for images composed of pixels) generic paint programs
            or (for drawings) some widely available drawing editor, and that
            is suitable for input to text formatters or for automatic
            translation to a variety of formats suitable for input to text
            formatters. A copy made in an otherwise Transparent file format
            whose markup, or absence of markup, has been arranged to thwart or
            discourage subsequent modification by readers is not Transparent.
            An image format is not Transparent if used for any substantial
            amount of text. A copy that is not "Transparent" is called
            "Opaque".</para>

            <para>Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include
            plain ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input
            format, SGML or XML using a publicly available DTD, and
            standard-conforming simple HTML, PostScript or PDF designed for
            human modification. Examples of transparent image formats include
            PNG, XCF and JPG. Opaque formats include proprietary formats that
            can be read and edited only by proprietary word processors, SGML
            or XML for which the DTD and/or processing tools are not generally
            available, and the machine-generated HTML, PostScript or PDF
            produced by some word processors for output purposes only.</para>

            <para id="gfdl-title-page">The "Title Page" means, for a printed
            book, the title page itself, plus such following pages as are
            needed to hold, legibly, the material this License requires to
            appear in the title page. For works in formats which do not have
            any title page as such, "Title Page" means the text near the most
            prominent appearance of the work's title, preceding the beginning
            of the body of the text.</para>

            <para id="gfdl-entitled">A section "Entitled XYZ" means a named
            subunit of the Document whose title either is precisely XYZ or
            contains XYZ in parentheses following text that translates XYZ in
            another language. (Here XYZ stands for a specific section name
            mentioned below, such as "Acknowledgements", "Dedications",
            "Endorsements", or "History".) To "Preserve the Title" of such a
            section when you modify the Document means that it remains a
            section "Entitled XYZ" according to this definition.</para>

            <para>The Document may include Warranty Disclaimers next to the
            notice which states that this License applies to the Document.
            These Warranty Disclaimers are considered to be included by
            reference in this License, but only as regards disclaiming
            warranties: any other implication that these Warranty Disclaimers
            may have is void and has no effect on the meaning of this
            License.</para>
         </section>

         <section id="gfdl-2">
            <title>VERBATIM COPYING</title>

            <para>You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium,
            either commercially or noncommercially, provided that this
            License, the copyright notices, and the license notice saying this
            License applies to the Document are reproduced in all copies, and
            that you add no other conditions whatsoever to those of this
            License. You may not use technical measures to obstruct or control
            the reading or further copying of the copies you make or
            distribute. However, you may accept compensation in exchange for
            copies. If you distribute a large enough number of copies you must
            also follow the conditions in section 3.</para>

            <para>You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated
            above, and you may publicly display copies.</para>
         </section>

         <section id="gfdl-3">
            <title>COPYING IN QUANTITY</title>

            <para>If you publish printed copies (or copies in media that
            commonly have printed covers) of the Document, numbering more than
            100, and the Document's license notice requires Cover Texts, you
            must enclose the copies in covers that carry, clearly and legibly,
            all these Cover Texts: Front-Cover Texts on the front cover, and
            Back-Cover Texts on the back cover. Both covers must also clearly
            and legibly identify you as the publisher of these copies. The
            front cover must present the full title with all words of the
            title equally prominent and visible. You may add other material on
            the covers in addition. Copying with changes limited to the
            covers, as long as they preserve the title of the Document and
            satisfy these conditions, can be treated as verbatim copying in
            other respects.</para>

            <para>If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to
            fit legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit
            reasonably) on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto
            adjacent pages.</para>

            <para>If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document
            numbering more than 100, you must either include a
            machine-readable Transparent copy along with each Opaque copy, or
            state in or with each Opaque copy a computer-network location from
            which the general network-using public has access to download
            using public-standard network protocols a complete Transparent
            copy of the Document, free of added material. If you use the
            latter option, you must take reasonably prudent steps, when you
            begin distribution of Opaque copies in quantity, to ensure that
            this Transparent copy will remain thus accessible at the stated
            location until at least one year after the last time you
            distribute an Opaque copy (directly or through your agents or
            retailers) of that edition to the public.</para>

            <para>It is requested, but not required, that you contact the
            authors of the Document well before redistributing any large
            number of copies, to give them a chance to provide you with an
            updated version of the Document.</para>
         </section>

         <section id="gfdl-4">
            <title>MODIFICATIONS</title>

            <para>You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the
            Document under the conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided
            that you release the Modified Version under precisely this
            License, with the Modified Version filling the role of the
            Document, thus licensing distribution and modification of the
            Modified Version to whoever possesses a copy of it. In addition,
            you must do these things in the Modified Version:</para>

            <orderedlist id="gfdl-modif-cond" numeration="upperalpha">
               <title>GNU FDL Modification Conditions</title>

               <listitem>
                  <simpara>Use in the Title Page (and on the covers, if any) a
                  title distinct from that of the Document, and from those of
                  previous versions (which should, if there were any, be
                  listed in the History section of the Document). You may use
                  the same title as a previous version if the original
                  publisher of that version gives permission.</simpara>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <simpara>List on the Title Page, as authors, one or more
                  persons or entities responsible for authorship of the
                  modifications in the Modified Version, together with at
                  least five of the principal authors of the Document (all of
                  its principal authors, if it has fewer than five), unless
                  they release you from this requirement.</simpara>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <simpara>State on the Title page the name of the publisher
                  of the Modified Version, as the publisher.</simpara>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <simpara>Preserve all the copyright notices of the
                  Document.</simpara>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <simpara>Add an appropriate copyright notice for your
                  modifications adjacent to the other copyright
                  notices.</simpara>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <simpara>Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a
                  license notice giving the public permission to use the
                  Modified Version under the terms of this License, in the
                  form shown in the <link
                  linkend="gfdl-addendum">Addendum</link> below.</simpara>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <simpara>Preserve in that license notice the full lists of
                  Invariant Sections and required Cover Texts given in the
                  Document's license notice.</simpara>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <simpara>Include an unaltered copy of this
                  License.</simpara>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <simpara>Preserve the section Entitled "History", Preserve
                  its Title, and add to it an item stating at least the title,
                  year, new authors, and publisher of the Modified Version as
                  given on the Title Page. If there is no section Entitled
                  "History" in the Document, create one stating the title,
                  year, authors, and publisher of the Document as given on its
                  Title Page, then add an item describing the Modified Version
                  as stated in the previous sentence.</simpara>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <simpara>Preserve the network location, if any, given in the
                  Document for public access to a Transparent copy of the
                  Document, and likewise the network locations given in the
                  Document for previous versions it was based on. These may be
                  placed in the "History" section. You may omit a network
                  location for a work that was published at least four years
                  before the Document itself, or if the original publisher of
                  the version it refers to gives permission.</simpara>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <simpara>For any section Entitled "Acknowledgements" or
                  "Dedications", Preserve the Title of the section, and
                  preserve in the section all the substance and tone of each
                  of the contributor acknowledgements and/or dedications given
                  therein.</simpara>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <simpara>Preserve all the Invariant Sections of the
                  Document, unaltered in their text and in their titles.
                  Section numbers or the equivalent are not considered part of
                  the section titles.</simpara>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <simpara>Delete any section Entitled "Endorsements". Such a
                  section may not be included in the Modified
                  Version.</simpara>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <simpara>Do not retitle any existing section to be Entitled
                  "Endorsements" or to conflict in title with any Invariant
                  Section.</simpara>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <simpara>Preserve any Warranty Disclaimers.</simpara>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>

            <para>If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections
            or appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no
            material copied from the Document, you may at your option
            designate some or all of these sections as invariant. To do this,
            add their titles to the list of Invariant Sections in the Modified
            Version's license notice. These titles must be distinct from any
            other section titles.</para>

            <para>You may add a section Entitled "Endorsements", provided it
            contains nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by
            various parties--for example, statements of peer review or that
            the text has been approved by an organization as the authoritative
            definition of a standard.</para>

            <para>You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover
            Text, and a passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the
            end of the list of Cover Texts in the Modified Version. Only one
            passage of Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be
            added by (or through arrangements made by) any one entity. If the
            Document already includes a cover text for the same cover,
            previously added by you or by arrangement made by the same entity
            you are acting on behalf of, you may not add another; but you may
            replace the old one, on explicit permission from the previous
            publisher that added the old one.</para>

            <para>The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by
            this License give permission to use their names for publicity for
            or to assert or imply endorsement of any Modified Version.</para>
         </section>

         <section id="gfdl-5">
            <title>COMBINING DOCUMENTS</title>

            <para>You may combine the Document with other documents released
            under this License, under the terms defined in <link
            linkend="gfdl-4">section 4</link> above for modified versions,
            provided that you include in the combination all of the Invariant
            Sections of all of the original documents, unmodified, and list
            them all as Invariant Sections of your combined work in its
            license notice, and that you preserve all their Warranty
            Disclaimers.</para>

            <para>The combined work need only contain one copy of this
            License, and multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced
            with a single copy. If there are multiple Invariant Sections with
            the same name but different contents, make the title of each such
            section unique by adding at the end of it, in parentheses, the
            name of the original author or publisher of that section if known,
            or else a unique number. Make the same adjustment to the section
            titles in the list of Invariant Sections in the license notice of
            the combined work.</para>

            <para>In the combination, you must combine any sections Entitled
            "History" in the various original documents, forming one section
            Entitled "History"; likewise combine any sections Entitled
            "Acknowledgements", and any sections Entitled "Dedications". You
            must delete all sections Entitled "Endorsements".</para>
         </section>

         <section id="gfdl-6">
            <title>COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS</title>

            <para>You may make a collection consisting of the Document and
            other documents released under this License, and replace the
            individual copies of this License in the various documents with a
            single copy that is included in the collection, provided that you
            follow the rules of this License for verbatim copying of each of
            the documents in all other respects.</para>

            <para>You may extract a single document from such a collection,
            and distribute it individually under this License, provided you
            insert a copy of this License into the extracted document, and
            follow this License in all other respects regarding verbatim
            copying of that document.</para>
         </section>

         <section id="gfdl-7">
            <title>AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS</title>

            <para>A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other
            separate and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of
            a storage or distribution medium, is called an "aggregate" if the
            copyright resulting from the compilation is not used to limit the
            legal rights of the compilation's users beyond what the individual
            works permit. When the Document is included in an aggregate, this
            License does not apply to the other works in the aggregate which
            are not themselves derivative works of the Document.</para>

            <para>If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to
            these copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than
            one half of the entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts may
            be placed on covers that bracket the Document within the
            aggregate, or the electronic equivalent of covers if the Document
            is in electronic form. Otherwise they must appear on printed
            covers that bracket the whole aggregate.</para>
         </section>

         <section id="gfdl-8">
            <title>TRANSLATION</title>

            <para>Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
            distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section
            4. Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires special
            permission from their copyright holders, but you may include
            translations of some or all Invariant Sections in addition to the
            original versions of these Invariant Sections. You may include a
            translation of this License, and all the license notices in the
            Document, and any Warranty Disclaimers, provided that you also
            include the original English version of this License and the
            original versions of those notices and disclaimers. In case of a
            disagreement between the translation and the original version of
            this License or a notice or disclaimer, the original version will
            prevail.</para>

            <para>If a section in the Document is Entitled "Acknowledgements",
            "Dedications", or "History", the requirement (section 4) to
            Preserve its Title (section 1) will typically require changing the
            actual title.</para>
         </section>

         <section id="gfdl-9">
            <title>TERMINATION</title>

            <para>You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the
            Document except as expressly provided for under this License. Any
            other attempt to copy, modify, sublicense or distribute the
            Document is void, and will automatically terminate your rights
            under this License. However, parties who have received copies, or
            rights, from you under this License will not have their licenses
            terminated so long as such parties remain in full
            compliance.</para>
         </section>

         <section id="gfdl-10">
            <title>FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE</title>

            <para>The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised
            versions of the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time.
            Such new versions will be similar in spirit to the present
            version, but may differ in detail to address new problems or
            concerns. See http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/.</para>

            <para>Each version of the License is given a distinguishing
            version number. If the Document specifies that a particular
            numbered version of this License "or any later version" applies to
            it, you have the option of following the terms and conditions
            either of that specified version or of any later version that has
            been published (not as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation.
            If the Document does not specify a version number of this License,
            you may choose any version ever published (not as a draft) by the
            Free Software Foundation.</para>
         </section>

         <section id="gfdl-addendum">
            <title>ADDENDUM: How to use this License for your
            documents</title>

            <para>To use this License in a document you have written, include
            a copy of the License in the document and put the following
            copyright and license notices just after the title page:</para>

            <blockquote id="copyright-sample">
               <title>Sample Invariant Sections list</title>

               <para>Copyright (c) YEAR YOUR NAME. Permission is granted to
               copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of
               the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 or any later
               version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
               Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover
               Texts. A copy of the license is included in the section
               entitled "GNU Free Documentation License".</para>
            </blockquote>

            <para>If you have Invariant Sections, Front-Cover Texts and
            Back-Cover Texts, replace the "with...Texts." line with
            this:</para>

            <blockquote id="inv-cover-sample">
               <title>Sample Invariant Sections list</title>

               <para>with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with
               the Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts
               being LIST.</para>
            </blockquote>

            <para>If you have Invariant Sections without Cover Texts, or some
            other combination of the three, merge those two alternatives to
            suit the situation.</para>

            <para>If your document contains nontrivial examples of program
            code, we recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your
            choice of free software license, such as the GNU General Public
            License, to permit their use in free software.</para>
         </section>
      </appendix>
   </part>

   <bibliography>
      <biblioentry id="ref.design.patterns">
         <abbrev>Gam95</abbrev>

         <authorgroup>
            <author>
               <firstname>Erich</firstname>

               <surname>Gamma</surname>
            </author>

            <author>
               <firstname>Richard</firstname>

               <surname>Helm</surname>
            </author>

            <author>
               <firstname>Ralph</firstname>

               <surname>Johnson</surname>
            </author>

            <author>
               <firstname>John</firstname>

               <surname>Vlissides</surname>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>

         <title>Design Patterns</title>

         <subtitle>Elements of Reusable Object-Oriented Software</subtitle>

         <publisher>
            <publishername>Addison-Wesley</publishername>
         </publisher>

         <pubdate>1995</pubdate>
      </biblioentry>

      <biblioentry id="ref.pthreads.programming">
         <abbrev>Nic96</abbrev>

         <authorgroup>
            <author>
               <firstname>Bradford</firstname>

               <surname>Nichols</surname>
            </author>

            <author>
               <firstname>Dick</firstname>

               <surname>Buttlar</surname>
            </author>

            <author>
               <firstname>Jacqueline</firstname>

               <othername>Proulx</othername>

               <surname>Farrell</surname>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>

         <title>Pthreads Programming</title>

         <subtitle>A POSIX Standard for Better Multiprocessing</subtitle>

         <publisher>
            <publishername>O'Reilly &amp; Associates</publishername>
         </publisher>

         <pubdate>1996</pubdate>
      </biblioentry>

      <biblioentry id="ref.network.patterns">
         <abbrev>Sch00</abbrev>

         <author>
            <firstname>Douglas</firstname>

            <surname>Schmidt</surname>
         </author>

         <title>Pattern-Oriented Software Architecture</title>

         <volumenum>Volume 2</volumenum>

         <subtitle>Patterns for Concurrent and Networked Objects</subtitle>

         <publisher>
            <publishername>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publishername>
         </publisher>

         <pubdate>2000</pubdate>
      </biblioentry>

      <biblioentry id="ref.advanced.prog.unix">
         <abbrev>Ste92</abbrev>

         <author>
            <firstname>W. Richard</firstname>

            <surname>Stevens</surname>
         </author>

         <title>Advanced Programming in the UNIX Environment</title>

         <publisher>
            <publishername>Addison-Wesley</publishername>
         </publisher>

         <pubdate>1992</pubdate>
      </biblioentry>

      <biblioentry id="ref.unix.network.programming">
         <abbrev>Ste98</abbrev>

         <author>
            <firstname>W. Richard</firstname>

            <surname>Stevens</surname>
         </author>

         <title>UNIX Network Programming</title>

         <volumenum>Volume 1</volumenum>

         <subtitle>Network APIs: Sockets and XTI</subtitle>

         <edition>Second Edition</edition>

         <publisher>
            <publishername>Prentice-Hall PTR</publishername>
         </publisher>

         <pubdate>1998</pubdate>
      </biblioentry>
   </bibliography>

   <glossary>
      <title>Glossary of Terms</title>

      <glossdiv>
         <title>B</title>

         <glossentry id="gloss.bsd.sockets">
            <glossterm>BSD sockets</glossterm>

            <glossdef>
               <para>The socket programming interface introduced with the
               Berkeley Software Distribution version of the UNIX operating
               system. It is made up of a collection of system calls that
               allow highly flexible socket programming. Most UNIX variants in
               use today use the BSD sockets API. Moreover, the Winsock API
               used on Windows is based on this API.</para>
            </glossdef>
         </glossentry>
      </glossdiv>

      <glossdiv>
         <title>F</title>

         <glossentry id="gloss.functor">
            <glossterm>functor</glossterm>

            <glosssee>Something that performs an operation or function. In the
            scope of object-oriented programming, a functor is an object that
            behaves similarly to a function pointer in C.</glosssee>
         </glossentry>
      </glossdiv>

      <glossdiv>
         <title>N</title>

         <glossentry id="gloss.nspr">
            <glossterm>Netscape Portable Runtime</glossterm>

            <acronym>NSPR</acronym>

            <glossdef>
               <para>More information can be found at <ulink
               url="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/nspr/index.html">http://www.mozilla.org/projects/nspr/index.html</ulink></para>
            </glossdef>
         </glossentry>
      </glossdiv>
   </glossary>

   <index></index>
</book>