<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
   <bookinfo>
      <title>VR Juggler</title>

      <subtitle>Getting Started Guide</subtitle>

      <copyright>
         <year>2001–2007</year>

         <holder>Iowa State University</holder>
      </copyright>

      <legalnotice>
         <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
         document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License,
         Version 1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software
         Foundation; with the Invariant Sections being <xref
         linkend="appendix.gfdl" />, with no Front-Cover Texts, and with no
         Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is included in <xref
         linkend="appendix.gfdl" />.</para>
      </legalnotice>

      <releaseinfo>Version 2.3</releaseinfo>

      <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
   </bookinfo>

   <preface>
      <title>Preface</title>

      <para>This book is for people who are just getting started with VR
      Juggler. It guides new users through getting and installing VR Juggler,
      configuring users' environment to use it, and compiling and running a
      sample application.</para>

      <para>The prerequisites for reading this book are minimal. They
      are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>Some experience with a command-line interface (i.e., a shell
            such as tcsh or the DOS shell)</para>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para>Creating and browsing directories</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Those users who want to get more involved with VR Juggler to do
      more than just run applications should be aware right away of the
      following prerequisites:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>Knowledge of C++ and object-oriented design</para>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para>Knowledge of one of VR Juggler's currently supported
            graphics APIs (<ulink url="http://www.opengl.org/">OpenGL</ulink>,
            <ulink url="http://www.sgi.com/software/performer/">OpenGL
            Performer</ulink>, <ulink
            url="http://www.opensg.org/">OpenSG</ulink>, or <ulink
            url="http://www.openscenegraph.org/">Open Scene
            Graph</ulink>)</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
   </preface>

   <chapter id="chapter.vrj.install">
      <title>Installing VR Juggler</title>

      <para>As with most Open Source projects, VR Juggler is distributed as
      compressed archive files using popular formats. Installing a
      distribution requires very little effort, but you do need to know how to
      use archiving utilities to extract the installation tree. Automation of
      the installation is a goal of the VR Juggler team, but we are still
      finalizing the details of cross-platform installation management. Before
      reading further, you should know where you want to install VR Juggler,
      and you should make sure that you have access to write to that
      directory.</para>

      <section>
         <title>Installing from a Compressed TAR File</title>

         <para>The TAR (Tape ARchive) format has been around for a long, long
         time in the UNIX world. It is simply a collection of files in a
         directory tree that are lumped into a single file suitable for
         writing to a tape or for downloading. The format is a standard, and
         the <command>tar</command>(1) utility is available on every
         UNIX-based platform and on <productname
         class="registered">Windows</productname>. A free version can be
         downloaded from <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/">the GNU
         Project</ulink>. A compressed TAR file is made for each VR Juggler
         distribution, and some distributions come in other formats as well.
         You can always count on the availability of a TAR file, though. The
         TAR files are compressed using either GZIP or BZIP2, both of which
         are standard compression formats. The <command>gzip</command>(1)
         utility is freely available from the GNU Project, and the
         <command>bzip2</command>(1) utility can be downloaded for free from
         <ulink url="http://sources.redhat.com/bzip2/">Red Hat, Inc.</ulink>.
         The GNU version of TAR has the GZIP and BZIP2 algorithms built in.
         The compression algorithm used can be determined by the file
         extension. Files compressed with GZIP end in
         <filename>.gz</filename>; files compressed with BZIP2 end in
         <filename>.bz2</filename>.</para>

         <para>Once you have downloaded a VR Juggler TAR distribution, you can
         unpack it one of two ways depending on what your platform's version
         of TAR supports. Before extracting the installation tree, make sure
         that your current directory is the one where you want to install VR
         Juggler. If your version of TAR does not have GZIP built in (it does
         not support the <option>-z</option> option), the following command
         will do the decompression and extraction:</para>

         <screen>% gzip -cd vrjuggler-distribution.tar.gz | tar -xvf -</screen>

         <para>For versions of TAR without built-in BZIP2 support (there is no
         <option>-j</option> option) the command is similar:</para>

         <screen>% bzip2 -cd vrjuggler-distribution.tar.bz2 | tar -xvf -</screen>

         <para>Here, you should fill in
         <filename>vrjuggler-distribution.tar.gz</filename> (or
         <filename>vrjuggler-distribution.tar.bz2</filename>) with the name of
         the VR Juggler distribution file you downloaded. The above commands
         will work with any shell that supports redirection of standard output
         to a pipe. If that looks too scary, you can separate the
         decompression and extraction into two commands (for GZIP):</para>

         <screen>% gunzip vrjuggler-distribution.tar.gz
% tar -xvf vrjuggler-distribution.tar</screen>

         <para>or for BZIP2:</para>

         <screen>% bunzip2 vrjuggler-distribution.tar.bz2
% tar -xvf vrjuggler-distribution.tar</screen>

         <para>Note that the distribution file in the second command does not
         have the <filename>.gz</filename> extension after
         <command>gzip</command>(1) is run. These steps also work if your
         version of <command>tar</command>(1) supports the <option>-z</option>
         option (<option>-j</option> for BZIP2), but you can simplify your
         work if that option is supported. The following illustrates how to
         decompress and extract a TAR file compressed with GZIP all in one
         step:</para>

         <screen>% tar -xzvf vrjuggler-distribution.tar.gz</screen>

         <para>The following would be used for a TAR file compressed with
         BZIP2:</para>

         <screen>% tar -xjvf vrjuggler-distribution.tar.bz2</screen>

         <para>In either case, while the command runs, you will see the name
         of each file as it is written to disk. This is because of the
         <option>-v</option> option to <command>tar</command>(1) that tells it
         to be verbose in its efforts. <command>tar</command>(1) takes care of
         creating all the directories in the installation tree, so you only
         need to have the base directory (for example,
         <filename>/usr/local</filename>) when you start. For more information
         about these utilities, please refer to the <command>tar</command>(1)
         and <command>gzip</command>(1) manual pages.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Installing from a ZIP File (<productname
         class="registered">Windows</productname> only)</title>

         <para>On the <productname class="registered">Windows</productname>
         family of platforms, the ZIP format rules. In the old days, you would
         use the PKZIP utility to decompress and extract a ZIP file. Nowadays,
         most people use Windows Explorer, <ulink
         url="http://www.winzip.com/">WinZip</ulink>, or some other comparable
         graphical interface. This documentation covers only the use of WinZip
         when extracting a ZIP file.</para>

         <para>Once you have downloaded the VR Juggler ZIP file, the easiest
         way to extract it is to double-click on its icon in the open folder
         window as shown in <xref
         linkend="figure.windows.temp.folder.view" />.</para>

         <figure id="figure.windows.temp.folder.view">
            <title>Windows Folder View of ZIP File</title>

            <mediaobject>
               <imageobject>
                  <imagedata align="center"
                             fileref="figures/Window.Download.png"
                             format="PNG" />
               </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
         </figure>

         <para>Double-clicking opens the main WinZip window, as shown in <xref
         linkend="figure.winzip.main" />.</para>

         <figure id="figure.winzip.main">
            <title>Open WinZip Window</title>

            <mediaobject>
               <imageobject>
                  <imagedata align="center"
                             fileref="figures/Window.WinZip.png" format="PNG"
                             scalefit="1" />
               </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
         </figure>

         <para>Note that in this screen shot, the
         <guibutton>Extract</guibutton> button is highlighted. Click this
         button to open the following window. Note that in this screen shot,
         the <guibutton>Extract</guibutton> button is highlighted. Click this
         button to open the dialog box shown in <xref
         linkend="figure.winzip.extract" />.</para>

         <figure id="figure.winzip.extract">
            <title>WinZip Extract Dialog</title>

            <mediaobject>
               <imageobject>
                  <imagedata align="center"
                             fileref="figures/Window.WinZip.Extract.png"
                             format="PNG" />
               </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
         </figure>

         <para>In this window, choose the directory where VR Juggler will be
         installed and click <guibutton>Extract</guibutton>. WinZip will then
         proceed to extract the ZIP file into the directory you named. That is
         all there is to it.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Installing from a Disk Image (Mac OS X only)</title>

         <para>The preferred Internet distribution format for Mac OS X is the
         disk image (file extension <filename>.dmg</filename>).
         Double-clicking on the <filename>.dmg</filename> file mounts the disk
         image which can then be opened. Pre-compiled versions of VR Juggler
         for Mac OS X are distributed in this manner. Within the mounted disk
         image, there is an installer program for the VR Juggler release (file
         extension <filename>.pkg</filename>)<footnote>
               <para>Unfortunately, the complexity of VR Juggler prevents it
               from being installed using the preferred drag-and-drop
               method.</para>
            </footnote>.</para>

         <important>
            <para>Before installing, read any HTML files included with the VR
            Juggler distribution. These will contain relevant information
            about updating an existing VR Juggler installation or how to use
            the VR Juggler installer that is not covered here.</para>
         </important>

         <para>Double-clicking on the VR Juggler installer will install VR
         Juggler. The VR Juggler libraries will be installed to
         <filename>/usr/local</filename>, and the dependencies will be
         installed to <filename>/usr/local/vrjuggler-deps</filename>. The
         application bundles for the Tweek Java GUI and
         <application>VRJConfig</application> will be installed to
         <filename>/Applications</filename>. Finally, the file
         <filename>~/.MacOSX/environment.plist</filename> will be updated to
         set the VR Juggler-related environment variables (see <xref
         linkend="chapter.envvar" />).</para>

         <note>
            <para>The application bundles for the Tweek Java GUI and
            <application>VRJConfig</application> are still in the early stages
            of development. For convenience, the command line versions of
            these applications are also installed. Running
            <command>tweek</command> or <command>vrjconfig</command> from a
            terminal window will start those applications just as would be
            done on other operating systems. At some point, the command line
            versions of these applications will probably be removed on Mac OS
            X in favor of exclusive use of the application bundles.</para>
         </note>
      </section>
   </chapter>

   <chapter id="chapter.envvar">
      <title>Environment Variables</title>

      <para>There are several <firstterm>environment variables</firstterm>
      that affect the way VR Juggler works. Some of these are required to
      compile and run applications while others are optional. This chapter
      lists all such variables and explains their meanings and uses.</para>

      <section>
         <title>How to Set Environment Variables</title>

         <para>The syntax for setting or changing an environment variable
         varies with operating systems and shell interpreters. Instead of
         choosing one style of syntax that is specific to a particular shell
         type, we define our own syntax which you must then translate to your
         shell's specific syntax. Before defining this syntax, we present the
         method used to set environment variables in the three most common
         types of shells. We also provide a quick overview of how to set
         environment variables using Win32-based GUIs.</para>

         <section>
            <title>Common Conventions and Background</title>

            <para>A convention used throughout this book is to name the
            variables using all capital letters. In almost all cases,
            regardless of the shell, this is the naming convention used for
            environment variables.</para>

            <para>Setting a path with an environment variable can require
            special syntax. Because of this, the method for doing so may vary
            from shell to shell. Paths are important with VR Juggler when
            looking up the path to a shared library (dynamically linked
            library). For each shell, the syntax for setting a path is
            given.</para>

            <para>Referring to environment variables can also vary from shell
            to shell. An example of how to print the value of an environment
            variable will be given for each shell. An example of how to refer
            to an environment variable is also provided as these two
            operations may vary even within one kind of shell!</para>

            <para>In all shells, an environment variable is only available
            within that single shell instance. That is, setting an environment
            variable at a command prompt only affects that specific shell and
            will not be available from other concurrent or future shells. To
            make a setting <quote>permanent</quote>, it should be done in file
            read by all shell instances when they are started. This is
            addressed briefly as appropriate for each shell type.</para>
         </section>

         <section id="section.envvar.csh">
            <title>C-Style Shells (csh, tcsh)</title>

            <para>In a C-style shell (i.e., one whose interface is based on
            the C programming language), setting environment variables is done
            using the built-in command <command>setenv</command>. It is used
            as follows:</para>

            <screen>% setenv &lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt; &lt;value&gt;</screen>

            <para>where the string <literal>&lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;</literal>
            represents the name of the variable you are going to set and
            <literal>&lt;value&gt;</literal> represents the value assigned to
            that variable. Both are required. If the named variable did not
            exist before, it will pop into existence. Otherwise, you overwrite
            the old setting with the new one.</para>

            <para>To print the value of an environment variable, use the
            following command:</para>

            <screen>% printenv &lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;</screen>

            <para>Referring to a variable, however, is done using the
            following syntax:</para>

            <screen>% cd $VARIABLE_NAME/bin</screen>

            <para>Paths are specified as a colon-separated list. An example of
            this is:</para>

            <screen>% printenv PATH
/bin:/sbin:/usr/bin:/usr/sbin</screen>

            <para>For these types of shells, a <quote>permanent</quote>
            setting for a given variable should usually be done in your
            <filename>.cshrc</filename> file or in your
            <filename>.login</filename> file, both of which should be in your
            home directory. In most cases, it is better to use
            <filename>.cshrc</filename> because it is evaluated for every
            shell instance.</para>
         </section>

         <section id="section.envvar.sh">
            <title>sh-Derived Shells (sh, ksh, bash, zsh, etc.)</title>

            <para>In a shell based on sh, setting environment variables is
            done using the built-in command <command>export</command>. It is
            used as follows:</para>

            <screen>% export &lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;=&lt;value&gt;</screen>

            <para>or</para>

            <screen>% &lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;=&lt;value&gt;
% export &lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;</screen>

            <para>Here, the string <literal>&lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;</literal>
            represents the name of the variable you are going to set and
            <literal>&lt;value&gt;</literal> represents the value assigned to
            that variable. Both are required. Note that there is no space
            between the variable name and its value. If the named variable did
            not exist before, it will pop into existence. Otherwise, you
            overwrite the old setting with the new one. If the variable was
            already among your current shell's environment variables, the
            export command is not necessary.</para>

            <para>To print the value of an environment variable, use the
            following command:</para>

            <screen>% echo $VARIABLE_NAME</screen>

            <para>Getting the value of a variable works the same way.</para>

            <para>Paths are specified as a colon-separated list. An example of
            this is:</para>

            <screen>% echo $PATH
/bin:/sbin:/usr/bin:/usr/sbin</screen>

            <para>For these types of shells, a <quote>permanent</quote>
            setting for a given variable should usually be done in the
            <filename>.profile</filename> file in your home directory or in
            your shell's <quote>rc</quote> file. Different shells have
            different names for this file. Examples are
            <filename>.bashrc</filename> for BASH and
            <filename>.zshrc</filename> for Zsh. Please refer to your shell's
            documentation for more information. In any case, the file will be
            in your home directory.</para>
         </section>

         <section id="section.envvar.dos">
            <title>DOS Shell</title>

            <para>The typical syntax for setting an environment variable from
            the command line (in a DOS shell window) under <productname
            class="registered">Windows</productname> is:</para>

            <screen>C:\&gt; set &lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;=&lt;value&gt;</screen>

            <para>Here, <literal>&lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;</literal> is the name
            of the environment variable to be set, and
            <literal>&lt;value&gt;</literal> is the value being assigned to
            that variable. If the named variable did not exist before, it will
            pop into existence. Otherwise, you overwrite the old setting with
            the new one.</para>

            <para>To print the value of an environment variable, use the
            following command:</para>

            <screen>C:\&gt; set &lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;</screen>

            <para>Referring to a variable, however, is done using the
            following syntax:</para>

            <screen>C:\&gt; cd %VARIABLE_NAME%\bin</screen>

            <para>Paths are specified as a semicolon-separated list. An
            example of this is:</para>

            <screen>C:\&gt; set PATH
C:\WINDOWS;C:\bin;C:\</screen>

            <para>For some versions of <productname
            class="registered">Windows</productname>, a
            <quote>permanent</quote> setting for a given variable should
            usually be done in <filename>C:\AUTOEXEC.BAT</filename>. In newer
            versions (<productname class="registered">Windows</productname> ME
            in particular) and in the <productname
            class="registered">Windows</productname> NT line of operating
            systems, the setting is done using the Control Panel. Please refer
            to the next section for more information on that method.</para>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title><productname class="registered">Windows</productname>
            GUI</title>

            <para>Before reading this section, please be sure to have read
            <xref linkend="section.envvar.dos" />. This is necessary because
            the <productname class="registered">Windows</productname> GUI for
            setting environment variables is simply a front-end to that older
            method and thus uses the same conventions and syntax. The versions
            of <productname class="registered">Windows</productname> to which
            this subsection applies are indicated individually since each is a
            little different. For more detailed information, please refer to
            the <productname class="registered">Windows</productname> online
            help system and search for <quote>environment
            variables</quote>.</para>

            <section>
               <title><productname class="registered">Windows</productname>
               2000 and <productname class="registered">Windows</productname>
               XP</title>

               <para>In the Control Panel, open the <guiicon>System</guiicon>
               icon. Under the <guilabel>Advanced</guilabel> tab, there is a
               button labeled <guibutton>Environment Variables</guibutton>,
               shown in <xref linkend="figure.win2k.sysprops" /> (the
               <productname class="registered">Windows</productname> XP
               version is shown in <xref linkend="figure.winxp.sysprops" />).
               Clicking this button opens the dialog box shown in <xref
               linkend="figure.win2k.envvars" />. Here, you can set variables
               for yourself and, if you have the access privileges, for all
               users.</para>

               <figure id="figure.win2k.sysprops">
                  <title><productname class="registered">Windows</productname>
                  2000 System Properties Dialog</title>

                  <mediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="center"
                                   fileref="figures/Window.SystemProperties.png"
                                   format="PNG" />
                     </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
               </figure>

               <figure id="figure.winxp.sysprops">
                  <title><productname class="registered">Windows</productname>
                  XP System Properties Dialog</title>

                  <mediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="center"
                                   fileref="figures/Window.SystemProperties.winxp.png"
                                   format="PNG" />
                     </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
               </figure>

               <figure id="figure.win2k.envvars">
                  <title><productname class="registered">Windows</productname>
                  Environment Variable Editor Dialog</title>

                  <mediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="center"
                                   fileref="figures/Window.EnvironmentVariables.png"
                                   format="PNG" />
                     </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
               </figure>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Windows NT 4.0</title>

               <para>In the Control Panel, open the <guiicon>System</guiicon>
               icon. The window that is opened has a tab labeled
               <guilabel>Environment Variables</guilabel>. Here, you can set
               variables for yourself and, if you have the access privileges,
               for all users. The GUI is similar to that shown above for
               <productname class="registered">Windows</productname>
               2000.</para>
            </section>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Mac OS X</title>

            <para>On Mac OS X, environment variables can be set in two
            different ways, just as on <productname
            class="registered">Windows</productname>. They can be set as
            <quote>global</quote> environment variables available to all
            applications launched from the Finder, or they can be set within a
            Terminal window for use within that shell and by all applications
            launched from that shell. Refer to Apple's Technical Q&amp;A
            <ulink
            url="http://developer.apple.com/qa/qa2001/qa1067.html">QA1067</ulink>
            document for details on how to set global environment variables
            for use by the Mac OS X desktop interface. To set an environment
            variable within a Terminal window, refer to either <xref
            linkend="section.envvar.csh" /> or <xref
            linkend="section.envvar.sh" /> depending on the user's chosen
            shell (the default is tcsh).</para>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Syntax Used in this Document</title>

            <para>To avoid tying this documentation to a single style of
            environment variable creation, assignment and reference, the
            following syntax will be used exclusively from this point onward.
            Please read this carefully before proceeding.</para>

            <section>
               <title>Naming Environment Variables</title>

               <para>When naming an environment variable in the plain text of
               this document, the variable will be referred to by its name
               only. For example, to talk about the environment variable
               containing your path, we will talk about it as
               <envar>PATH</envar>.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Creating/Setting Environment Variables</title>

               <para>The syntax to set an environment variable is:</para>

               <screen>% &lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt; = &lt;value&gt;</screen>

               <para>Setting an environment variable also creates it if it is
               not already present in the current shell's environment.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Printing an the Value of an Environment Variable</title>

               <para>Printing an environment variable's value to standard
               output (stdout) is done as follows:</para>

               <screen>% echo $VARIABLE_NAME
value</screen>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Referring to the Value of an Environment
               Variable</title>

               <para>To get the value of an environment variable when it needs
               to be expanded, the following syntax will be used:</para>

               <screen>% cd $VARIABLE_NAME/bin</screen>

               <para>Here, the reference to the value is
               <envar>$VARIABLE_NAME</envar>.</para>
            </section>
         </section>
      </section>

      <section id="section.envvars.required">
         <title>Relevant Environment Variables</title>

         <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
               <term>LD_LIBRARY_PATH (UNIX/Linux only)</term>

               <term>DYLD_LIBRARY_PATH (Mac OS X only)</term>

               <listitem>
                  <para>UNIX/Linux systems use these environment variables to
                  find dynamically loaded libraries, such as
                  <filename>libvrj-2_2.so</filename>. Unless you are building
                  everything with static libraries, you will need to set these
                  to include the VR Juggler library directory. An example of
                  setting the library path is as follows:</para>

                  <screen>% LD_LIBRARY_PATH = $VJ_BASE_DIR/lib</screen>

                  <para>This is only needed if the Juggler shared libraries
                  are not found by the runtime loader by default. If the
                  Juggler modules were installed using package management such
                  as RPM, then it will not be necessary to set
                  <envar>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</envar>. Setting
                  <envar>DYLD_LIBRARY_PATH</envar> on Mac OS X will probably
                  be necessary even when using the OS X installer
                  package.</para>
               </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
               <term>PATH</term>

               <listitem>
                  <para>On <productname
                  class="registered">Windows</productname>, the
                  <envar>PATH</envar> environment variable is used in the same
                  way that <envar>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</envar> is used on platforms
                  such as Linux. Thus, the <filename>bin</filename> and
                  <filename>lib</filename> subdirectories of the VR Juggler
                  installation need to be in your path in order for the
                  Juggler DLLs and the <command>vrjconfig</command> command to
                  be found. For non-Windows platforms, it is a good idea to
                  have the Juggler <filename>bin</filename> directory in your
                  path so that the <command>vrjconfig</command> command can be
                  found from the command line.</para>
               </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
               <term>FLAGPOLL_PATH</term>

               <listitem>
                  <para>To compile any of the sample applications, the
                  directory containing the Juggler <filename>.fpc</filename>
                  files for <ulink
                  url="https://realityforge.vrsource.org/view/FlagPoll/WebHome">Flagpoll</ulink>
                  must be able to be found. By default, the
                  <command>flagpoll</command> utility searches
                  <filename>/usr/lib/flagpoll</filename>,
                  <filename>/usr/lib64/flagpoll</filename>,
                  <filename>/usr/share/flagpoll</filename>,
                  <filename>/usr/lib/pkgconfig</filename>,
                  <filename>/usr/lib64/pkgconfig</filename>, and
                  <filename>/usr/share/pkgconfig</filename>. It also scans the
                  directories listed in <envar>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</envar>
                  (<envar>DYLD_LIBRARY_PATH</envar> on Mac OS X) for
                  <filename>flagpoll</filename> and
                  <filename>pkgconfig</filename> subdirectories. If you
                  already have <envar>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</envar> (or
                  <envar>DYLD_LIBRARY_PATH</envar>) set correctly or you have
                  Juggler installed in <filename>/usr</filename>, then there
                  is no need to set <envar>FLAGPOLL_PATH</envar>.</para>

                  <screen>% PATH = $PATH:$VJ_BASE_DIR/bin</screen>

                  <para>Depending on your shell, you may need to run the
                  <command>rehash</command> command after executing the
                  above.</para>

                  <para>Windows users must also include the directories
                  <filename>$VJ_DEPS_DIR/bin</filename>,
                  <filename>$VJ_DEPS_DIR/lib</filename>, and
                  <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/lib</filename> in their
                  <envar>PATH</envar> setting. This is so that the DLLs for VR
                  Juggler and its dependencies will be found when an
                  application is executed.</para>
               </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
               <term>JDK_HOME</term>

               <listitem>
                  <para>The <envar>JDK_HOME</envar> environment variable is
                  required by the script that starts
                  <application>VRJConfig</application>, the VR Juggler
                  configuration program. If <productname>Java</productname> is
                  installed on your system, <envar>JDK_HOME</envar> may
                  already be set. If not, it needs to be set to the base of
                  the <productname>Java</productname> installation.</para>
               </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
               <term>VJ_BASE_DIR</term>

               <listitem>
                  <para>The environment variable <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar>
                  plays identifiers where VR Juggler is installed. This
                  information is used for the following purposes:</para>

                  <itemizedlist>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>Visual C++ project files used for building VR
                        Juggler sample applications on <productname
                        class="registered">Windows</productname> reference
                        <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> for the header and library
                        search paths. In this context,
                        <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> is
                        <emphasis>required</emphasis>.</para>
                     </listitem>

                     <listitem>
                        <para>Important data files and plug-ins needed for
                        proper execution are searched for at run time relative
                        to the path identified by <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar>.
                        As of VR Juggler 2.2, this usage of
                        <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> has been diminished
                        greatly. The remainder of the description of
                        <envar>Vj_BASE_DIR</envar> explains when it may need
                        to be set and when the default will be more than
                        sufficient.</para>
                     </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>

                  <para>When using a pre-packaged version of VR Juggler for
                  non-<productname class="registered">Windows</productname>
                  platforms, the installation path is at the time of package
                  construction. Therefore, there is no need for the Juggler
                  libraries to be told at run time where they are installed.
                  If VR Juggler is being used on a non-<productname
                  class="registered">Windows</productname> platform and was
                  <emphasis>not</emphasis> installed using packaging such as
                  RPM or a Mac OS X package, then <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar>
                  may be necessary to execute applications
                  successfully.</para>

                  <para>On <productname
                  class="registered">Windows</productname>, the Juggler DLLs
                  (<filename>vpr-2_0.dll</filename>,
                  <filename>jccl-1_2.dll</filename>,
                  <filename>vrj-2_2.dll</filename>, etc.) determine on their
                  own where they are installed when they are attached to the
                  application process. As such, the <productname
                  class="registered">Windows</productname> DLLs will
                  automatically set the environment variable(s) that they need
                  to function properly. If an environment variable is already
                  set, then its setting will <emphasis>not</emphasis> be
                  changed by the DLL when it is attached to the application
                  process.</para>

                  <tip>
                     <para>If problems occur at run time with
                     <filename>.jdef</filename> files or plug-ins failing to
                     be found, then setting <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> will
                     almost certainly fix the problems. If the Juggler
                     installation is corrupted or non-standard (e.g., spread
                     out across several directory trees), then using
                     <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> in conjunction with some of
                     the environment variables described below will probably
                     prove helpful.</para>
                  </tip>

                  <para>If <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> needs to be set, then it
                  must be set to the base directory of the installed Juggler
                  Suite. For example, if you downloaded a UNIX version of VR
                  Juggler 2.2 and extracted it to the directory
                  <filename>/home/software</filename>, you would set
                  <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> with this command:</para>

                  <screen>% VJ_BASE_DIR = /home/software/vrjuggler-2.2</screen>

                  <para>The last component of the path depends on the
                  particular version of Juggler you have downloaded.</para>

                  <para>If you downloaded and built VR Juggler from the source
                  code, the compilation creates a directory called
                  <filename>instlinks</filename> which can be used as a VR
                  Juggler base:</para>

                  <screen>% VJ_BASE_DIR = $HOME/juggler/my_build_dir/instlinks</screen>

                  <important>
                     <para>When working from withing the build tree and using
                     <filename>instlinks</filename>,
                     <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> is
                     <emphasis>required</emphasis>.</para>
                  </important>
               </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
               <term>VJ_DEPS_DIR</term>

               <listitem>
                  <para>In VR Juggler 2.0, the <envar>VJ_DEPS_DIR</envar>
                  environment variable was introduced as a crutch for finding
                  dependencies such as Boost and CppDOM when building and
                  running VR Juggler applications. That was before
                  <application>Flagpoll</application> and RPMs, however. Now,
                  the recommended usage of VR Juggler is to use
                  <application>Flagpoll</application> for compiling
                  applications and to install everything needed using package
                  management. <application>Flagpoll</application> can find
                  dependencies on its own, and the
                  <envar>FLAGPOLL_PATH</envar> environment variable (see
                  above) extends the search path when necessary. Thus, on
                  platforms where <application>Flagpoll</application> is being
                  used, <envar>VJ_DEPS_DIR</envar> plays no role.</para>

                  <para>This does not currently apply to <productname
                  class="registered">Windows</productname>, unfortunately.
                  Until <application>Flagpoll</application> is ready for usage
                  on <productname class="registered">Windows</productname>,
                  the primary build mechanism will continue to be Visual
                  Studio<footnote>
                        <para>Visual Studio will probably always be the
                        recommended tool for compiling VR Juggler applications
                        on <productname
                        class="registered">Windows</productname> even after
                        <application>Flagpoll</application> has <productname
                        class="registered">Windows</productname> support. The
                        idea is to support <emphasis>both</emphasis> Visual
                        Studio and <application>Flagpoll</application> on
                        <productname
                        class="registered">Windows</productname>.</para>
                     </footnote>. To make things simple in Visual C++ project
                  files, environment variables can hide path details. The
                  <envar>VJ_DEPS_DIR</envar> environment variable provides the
                  path to the complete set of bundled VR Juggler dependencies
                  (Boost, CppDOM, OpenAL, etc.). It is used by the Visual C++
                  project files that come with the sample applications. If you
                  downloaded the dependencies as a separate package, set this
                  environment variable to the path where that package was
                  installed. If the dependencies are bundled in the same tree
                  as VR Juggler, then this environment variable does not have
                  to be set.</para>
               </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
               <term>VJ_CFG_PATH</term>

               <listitem>
                  <para>This variable provides a search path for looking up
                  configuration files. It lists one or more directories where
                  VR Juggler configuration files may be found. At run time,
                  this path will be used to find configuration files that are
                  not named using absolute paths. This variable is set using a
                  platform-specific format. On Windows, DOS paths should be
                  used, and they must be separated by the semi-colon (;)
                  character. On UNIX variants and Mac OS X, the paths should
                  be separated by the colon (:) character. This is exactly the
                  way that the <envar>$PATH</envar> environment variable would
                  be set on all of these platforms. If not set, the default
                  search path for configuration files is
                  <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/configFiles</filename>.</para>

                  <note>
                     <para>The configuration files are loaded by the module
                     JCCL, and it will recognize the environment variable
                     <envar>JCCL_CFG_PATH</envar>. If
                     <envar>JCCL_CFG_PATH</envar> is set, it takes precedence
                     over <envar>VJ_CFG_PATH</envar>.</para>
                  </note>
               </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
               <term>JCCL_DEFINITION_PATH</term>

               <listitem>
                  <para>This variable <emphasis>augments</emphasis> the search
                  path for JCCL definition files (those files with the
                  extension <filename>.jdef</filename>). It is set using a
                  platform-specific format. On Windows, DOS paths should be
                  used, and they must be separated by the semi-colon (;)
                  character. On UNIX variants and Mac OS X, the paths should
                  be separated by the colon (:) character. This is exactly the
                  way that the <envar>PATH</envar> environment variable would
                  be set on these platforms.</para>

                  <para>The default search path for configuration files is
                  always
                  <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/definitions</filename>.
                  Setting the environment variable
                  <envar>JCCL_DEFINITION_PATH</envar> appends directories to
                  the default search path. It is not possible to change the
                  default search path without changing the value of
                  <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar>.</para>

                  <sidebar>
                     <para>Python programmers will find this sort of behavior
                     familiar. This functionality is based on the way that the
                     Python environment variables <envar>PYTHONHOME</envar>
                     and <envar>PYTHONPATH</envar> behave. In this case,
                     <envar>PYTHONHOME</envar> corresponds to
                     <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar>, and <envar>PYTHONPATH</envar>
                     corresponds with <envar>JCCL_DEFINITION_PATH</envar>.
                     Indeed, the behavior of
                     <envar>JCCL_DEFINITION_PATH</envar> was inspired by the
                     handling of <envar>PYTHONPATH</envar> by the Python
                     interpreter.</para>
                  </sidebar>
               </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
               <term>VPR_DEBUG_NFY_LEVEL</term>

               <listitem>
                  <para>This variable can be used to control the amount of
                  diagnostic information a VR Juggler application outputs. Its
                  value is a number between 0 (only very important messages
                  are printed) and 7 (vast amounts of data) inclusive.
                  Non-hackers are advised to use levels 0 through 3, as higher
                  debug levels become increasingly cryptic and <emphasis>can
                  severely impact application performance</emphasis>. The
                  default is level 1—only errors and critical information are
                  output. An example of setting a value for this variable
                  is:</para>

                  <screen>% VPR_DEBUG_NFY_LEVEL = 3</screen>
               </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
               <term>VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES</term>

               <listitem>
                  <para>This variable can be used to control which components
                  of VR Juggler are allowed to output diagnostic data. If for
                  some reason you set <envar>VPR_DEBUG_NFY_LEVEL</envar> to 5
                  or higher, this variable can be used to filter the output.
                  The value of <envar>VPR_DEBUG_CATEGORIES</envar> is a
                  space-separated list of Juggler debug component names
                  (defined in
                  <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/include/vrj/Util/Debug.h</filename>,
                  <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/include/vpr/Util/Debug.h</filename>,
                  <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/include/tweek/Util/Debug.h</filename>,
                  <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/include/jccl/Util/Debug.h</filename>,
                  and
                  <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/include/gadget/Util/Debug.h</filename>).
                  The default value is <quote>DBG_ALL</quote>, which performs
                  no filtering whatsoever. Examples of setting it are as
                  follows:</para>

                  <screen>% VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES = DBG_ERROR
% VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES = "DBG_KERNEL DBG_INPUT_MGR DBG_DRAW_MGR"
% VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES = "DBG_CONFIG DBG_RECONFIGURATION"</screen>
               </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
               <term>VPR_DEBUG_DISALLOW_CATEGORIES</term>

               <listitem>
                  <para>This variable is basically the opposite of
                  <envar>VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES</envar>. Instead of
                  specifying which debugging categories you want to see, you
                  specify which ones you <emphasis>do not</emphasis> want to
                  see. Its default value is empty which means that no
                  debugging categories are excluded. Examples of setting it
                  are as follows:</para>

                  <screen>% VPR_DEBUG_DISALLOW_CATEGORIES = DBG_ERROR
% VPR_DEBUG_DISALLOW_CATEGORIES = "DBG_KERNEL DBG_INPUT_MGR DBG_DRAW_MGR"
% VPR_DEBUG_DISALLOW_CATEGORIES = "DBG_CONFIG DBG_RECONFIGURATION"</screen>
               </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
               <term>NO_RTRC_PLUGIN</term>

               <listitem>
                  <para>Setting this environment variable to any value will
                  prevent the <ulink
                  url="http://www.vrjuggler.org/jccl/">JCCL</ulink> Config
                  Manager from attempting to load the remote run-time
                  reconfiguration plug-in. This plug-in is used to allow
                  VRJConfig to connect to a running VR Juggler application so
                  that the application may be reconfigured on the fly.</para>

                  <para>Setting this environment variable is useful in one key
                  scenario: when using <ulink
                  url="http://www.vrjuggler.org/pyjuggler/">PyJuggler</ulink>
                  on Mac OS X 10.3 (<quote>Panther</quote>). On Mac OS X 10.3,
                  static data initialization in omniORB fails when the omniORB
                  libraries are loaded into the Python interpreter application
                  space, and this leads to a crash. Setting this environment
                  variable allows PyJuggler applications to run correctly.
                  This crash does not occur with PyJuggler on Mac OS X 10.4
                  (<quote>Tiger</quote>).</para>
               </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
               <term>NO_PERF_PLUGIN</term>

               <listitem>
                  <para>Setting this environment variable to any value will
                  prevent the VR Juggler Performance Mediator from attempting
                  to load the remote performance visualization plug-in. This
                  plug-in is used to allow a JavaBean loaded by the <ulink
                  url="http://www.vrjuggler.org/tweek/">Tweek</ulink> Java GUI
                  to connect to a running VR Juggler application and display
                  live performance metrics.</para>

                  <para>Setting this environment variable is useful in one key
                  scenario: when using <ulink
                  url="http://www.vrjuggler.org/pyjuggler/">PyJuggler</ulink>
                  on Mac OS X 10.3 (<quote>Panther</quote>). On Mac OS X 10.3,
                  static data initialization in omniORB fails when the omniORB
                  libraries are loaded into the Python interpreter application
                  space, and this leads to a crash. Setting this environment
                  variable allows PyJuggler applications to run correctly.
                  This crash does not occur with PyJuggler on Mac OS X 10.4
                  (<quote>Tiger</quote>).</para>
               </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
         </variablelist>
      </section>
   </chapter>

   <chapter>
      <title>VR Juggler Sample Applications</title>

      <para>VR Juggler comes with several sample applications in its
      <filename>samples</filename> directory tree. Many of them are very
      simple and are designed to demonstrate a specific feature of VR Juggler
      or a technique to use when writing your own applications. This chapter
      lists the current sample applications as of this writing and gives a
      quick description of what you as a potential developer might find
      interesting in the code. Those users who just want to run applications
      can safely skip this chapter.</para>

      <section>
         <title>Tutorial Applications</title>

         <para>Some sample applications designed for getting started with VR
         Juggler are found in
         <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples/OGL/simple</filename>.
         All of these applications were designed to be used as part of courses
         teaching people how to write VR Juggler applications using OpenGL.
         They contain clear comments explaining what the code is doing, and
         they are intended to be as simple as possible. These tutorials are as
         follows:</para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>simpleInput: An application that demonstrates how to get
               input from devices. No graphics are rendered with this
               application. It is intended to be a starting point for getting
               an understanding of how user input is queried.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <para>SimpleApp: A very simple OpenGL application that draws a
               small cube in space and draws the coordinate axes for the
               cube.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <para>contextApp: An application demonstrating how to use
               OpenGL display lists in VR Juggler applications. This extends
               SimpleApp by using a display list to draw a cube and by moving
               the cube with the wand.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <para>ConfigApp: A relatively simple application that
               demonstrates how user-level code can take advantage of the VR
               Juggler configuration system, JCCL.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <para>MPApp: A more complex OpenGL application that
               demonstrates how to do multi-processing in VR Juggler
               applications. As it exists in its distributed form, no
               multi-processing is done. A more detailed lesson is available
               that explains how to extend the application to employ
               multi-processing techniques.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <para>For a step-by-step lesson how to use these applications to
         learn VR Juggler application programming, please refer to the
         <emphasis>Programmer's Guide</emphasis>. It contains sections
         explaining each of the above applications in great detail. Each
         lesson ends with an exercise where the reader extends the application
         to include some new functionality.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Advanced OpenGL Performer Applications</title>

         <para>Examples of OpenGL Performer applications can be found in
         <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples/Pf/advanced</filename>.
         These are for more advanced developers who are familiar with
         Performer and some of the more complicated aspects of VR Juggler.
         There are two main programs to be found there:</para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para>pfNav: A starting point for basic VR Juggler Performer
               applications that need to load a model and navigate through it.
               Users implement their application by inheriting from a provided
               class, <classname>simplePfNav</classname>. This may be a good
               place for intermediate-level users of OpenGL Performer to start
               because <classname>simplePfNav</classname> hides many of the
               complicated details (which actually makes that class far from
               simple).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <para>pfConfigNav: A more advanced example of a VR Juggler
               Performer application that can be given its model through a VR
               Juggler configuration element.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
      </section>
   </chapter>

   <chapter id="chapter.app.compile">
      <title>Compiling a VR Juggler Sample Program</title>

      <para>Now that you have VR Juggler installed and you have your
      environment all configured, it is time for the fun to begin. No,
      seriously. You are now ready to compile and run VR Juggler applications,
      and that is the whole point, right? This chapter explains how to compile
      the applications provided in the directory
      <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples/OGL/simple</filename>.</para>

      <section>
         <title>Required Reading</title>

         <para>Before reading any further, make sure you have already read the
         instructions on how to install VR Juggler (in <xref
         linkend="chapter.vrj.install" />) and on how to configure your
         environment (in <xref linkend="chapter.envvar" />). That information
         will not be repeated, and it is assumed that you already know what we
         mean by <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar>. You should also have a basic
         understanding of how <command>make</command>(1) works, but in these
         examples, nothing more will be necessary than typing
         <literal>make</literal> on the command line. Refer to the
         <command>make</command>(1) manual page for more information about
         it.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Compiling an Application</title>

         <para>There are two ways to compile VR Juggler applications: from the
         command line or with Microsoft Visual Studio. Compiling an
         application on the command line requires the use of GNU make (often
         installed as <command>gmake</command>) so that it will work on all
         supported platforms. Using Microsoft Visual Studio will only work on
         <productname class="registered">Windows</productname>.</para>

         <section>
            <title>Compiling from the Command Line</title>

            <para>All the sample programs in
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples</filename> use the
            same basic steps to compile unless otherwise noted. Always refer
            to the top of the sample application's
            <filename>Makefile</filename> for information that may be specific
            to building that application. In general, though, all
            applications' makefiles require the GNU version of the
            <command>make</command>(1) utility, sometimes installed as
            <command>gmake</command>.</para>

            <para>The example used here will be the MPApp tutorial application
            found in
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples/OGL/simple/MPApp</filename>.
            It is an OpenGL-based application that will compile and run on all
            platforms supported by VR Juggler. Begin by changing into the
            directory
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples/OGL/simple/MPApp</filename>
            in a command shell.</para>

            <para>To compile MPApp, simply enter the following:</para>

            <screen>% gmake</screen>

            <para>On Mac OS X, enter the following:</para>

            <screen>% make bundle</screen>

            <para>The compile process will then begin. As noted above, the use
            of GNU make is required to use the distributed makefiles. Now that
            you have a program compiled, it is time to learn how to run it.
            (Readers who are not using Visual Studio can skip ahead to <xref
            linkend="chapter.app.running" />.)</para>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Compiling Using Microsoft Visual Studio</title>

            <note>
               <para>Remember that the Netscape Portable Runtime (NSPR) is
               <emphasis>required</emphasis> to use VR Juggler on Windows. Its
               DLL directory must be in your path (via the <envar>PATH</envar>
               environment variable) for proper application execution. The
               NSPR can be downloaded from the <ulink
               url="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/nspr">NSPR home
               page</ulink>. If the pre-compiled VR Juggler dependencies are
               installed, then NSPR is already available.</para>
            </note>

            <para>All OpenGL sample applications are shipped with
            pre-configured Microsoft Visual C++ projects. This is done to help
            new users get started with compiling VR Juggler applications and
            to give experienced Visual Studio users a starting place for their
            application development. To use the workspace for the MPApp
            application, begin by opening the folder containing the source
            code and double-clicking on
            <filename>MPApp.vcproj</filename>.</para>

            <figure>
               <title>Selecting the Visual C++ Project File</title>

               <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                     <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/MPApp.dir.png"
                                format="PNG" />
                  </imageobject>
               </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>Visual Studio will open, and the MPApp project will be
            loaded. The unexpanded class view will appear as shown in <xref
            linkend="figure.visual.studio.start" /> when Visual Studio first
            loads.</para>

            <figure id="figure.visual.studio.start">
               <title>MPApp Project</title>

               <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                     <imagedata align="center"
                                fileref="figures/MPApp.visual.c++.png"
                                format="PNG" />
                  </imageobject>
               </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>In some cases, it may be necessary to change the default
            project properties. The project properties dialog can be opened in
            several ways. For example, right-clicking on the project name in
            the Solution Explorer brings up the menu shown in <xref
            linkend="figure.visual.studio.menu.project" />. We are interested
            in changing the project's properties, so we select the
            <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem> item from the popup
            menu.</para>

            <figure id="figure.visual.studio.menu.project">
               <title>Project Menu</title>

               <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                     <imagedata align="center"
                                fileref="figures/MPApp.visual.c++.properties.png"
                                format="PNG" />
                  </imageobject>
               </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>Under the MPApp project settings, the path(s) to the VR
            Juggler C++ dependencies must be filled in. This means setting
            paths to find headers and libraries. All the Visual C++ project
            files shipped with VR Juggler refer to the VR Juggler C++
            dependency installation via the <envar>VJ_DEPS_DIR</envar>
            environment variable. If this is not set or cannot be used, the
            paths must be filled in manually.</para>

            <para>Once the program properties are set, compile the
            application. Under the <guimenu>Build</guimenu> menu, choose the
            <guimenuitem>Build MPApp</guimenuitem> item as shown in <xref
            linkend="figure.visual.studio.menu.build" />. Visual C++ will
            compile the application, and if you have everything configured
            properly on your computer, the compiling will complete
            successfully.</para>

            <figure id="figure.visual.studio.menu.build">
               <title>Build <filename>MPApp.exe</filename></title>

               <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                     <imagedata align="center"
                                fileref="figures/MPApp.visual.c++.build.png"
                                format="PNG" />
                  </imageobject>
               </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>For the remainder of this book, much of the discussion will
            concentrate on running applications from the command line rather
            than from the Visual Studio GUI. Readers can follow whichever
            method they prefer.</para>
         </section>
      </section>
   </chapter>

   <chapter id="chapter.app.running">
      <title>Running a VR Juggler Sample Program</title>

      <para>It is important to note that the same VR Juggler application can
      be run in a simulator configuration or in a full-scale VR system with no
      modifications. What does change is the configuration files used when
      starting the program. In
      <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/configFiles</filename>, you
      can find many basic configuration files including those for running in
      simulator using a mouse and keyboard to simulate VR input devices and
      some example files based on those used for the VRAC C4 system. In the
      directory, you will see some files with names containing
      <quote>mixin</quote>. These are special files that provide a specific
      capability not necessarily needed by all applications. They can be mixed
      in (hence the name) with other configuration files as needed. The
      configuration files found in the <filename>configFiles</filename>
      directory will be referenced in the examples provided, so be sure you
      know where they are.</para>

      <section id="section.required.reading">
         <title>Required Reading</title>

         <para>Before reading any further, make sure you have already read the
         instructions on how to install VR Juggler (see <xref
         linkend="chapter.vrj.install" />) and on how to configure your
         environment (see <xref linkend="chapter.envvar" />). That information
         will not be repeated, and it is assumed that you already know what we
         mean by <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> and
         <envar>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</envar>, to name two environment variables. At
         this point, it is also assumed that you already have compiled an
         application (MPApp in the case of the examples provided), so you
         should be sure to have read about how to compile a sample VR Juggler
         application (in <xref linkend="chapter.app.compile" />) before
         proceeding.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="section.running.simulator">
         <title>Running an Application with a Simulator Configuration</title>

         <para>Running with a simulator configuration means that your input is
         simulated and your display windows may have limited functionality.
         (By <quote>simulated input,</quote> we mean that input is provided
         through desktop windows that take keyboard and mouse input and
         translate that into what would be provided by various types of
         physical input devices used in VR systems.) Simulator viewports are
         limited primarily in that they cannot display stereo graphics.</para>

         <para>It is important to note that a simulator viewport is a special
         kind of VR Juggler viewport within a display window. Instead of
         basing its viewpoint on the head position of one of the users, the
         viewpoint is controlled by a separate camera that is just another
         positional device. Within a simulator viewport, VR Juggler draws
         certain objects to help visualize the environment. For example, the
         heads of users are represented as blue ellipsoids with gray eyes, and
         a wand (if present) is drawn as a green pointing device. Besides
         these common simulator objects, display surfaces can be drawn. These
         semi-transparent rectangles represent projection screens or HMD
         viewing projections.</para>

         <para>As mentioned, several simulator configuration files are
         provided with a VR Juggler distribution. These files provide a
         complete simulation of an immersive environment. Please note that
         this documentation reflects the state of the configuration files at
         the time the documentation was written. For more information about
         the configuration files and how to view or modify the configuration,
         refer to the <emphasis>VRJConfig Guide</emphasis>. (Using VRJConfig
         is the best way to find out how a specific configuration file is set
         up.) The configuration files of interest for simulator configurations
         are as follows:</para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
               <para><filename>sim.base.jconf</filename> - The basic
               configuration file used with other simulator configuration
               <quote>mix-in</quote> files. It defines commonly used VR
               Juggler concepts that are beyond the scope of this particular
               book. It also defines simulated head movement using the
               keyboard. This file also contains the display configuration
               information needed by other simulator configuration mix-in
               files. It defines the display window with its simulator
               viewport where the rendering occurs.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <para><filename>sim.analog.wandmixin.jconf</filename> - A
               <quote>mix-in</quote> configuration file that defines simulated
               analog input using the keyboard. This is only required for
               applications where analog input is used and a physical analog
               input device needs to be simulated.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <para><filename>sim.analog.mixin.jconf</filename> - This
               version of the analog simulator opens its own window. See the
               previous file (<filename>sim.analog.wandmixin.jconf</filename>)
               for other details.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <para><filename>sim.c6displays.mixin.jconf</filename> - A
               <quote>mix-in</quote> configuration file that defines the
               surfaces of a six-wall <productname
               class="trade">CAVE</productname>-like VR system with two
               additional surfaces at odd angles. Each surface is rendered in
               a separate display window. This is not required for any
               application but can be used to test opening multiple display
               windows (each containing either a surface or a simulator
               viewport) before running in a multi-pipe VR system. Note,
               however, that this configuration does not leverage
               multi-threaded rendering, just multi-window rendering.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <para><filename>sim.c6viewports.mixin.jconf</filename> - A
               <quote>mix-in</quote> configuration file that defines the
               surfaces of a six-wall <productname
               class="trade">CAVE</productname>-like VR system. Each surface
               is rendered in a separate viewport within a single display
               window. This is not required for any application but can be
               used to test using multiple viewports in a single window (each
               containing either a surface or a simulator viewport).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <para><filename>sim.digital.glove.mixin.jconf</filename> - A
               <quote>mix-in</quote> configuration file that defines simulated
               digital glove input using the keyboard. This is only required
               for applications where digital glove input is used and a
               physical digital input device needs to be simulated.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <para><filename>sim.glove.mixin.jconf</filename> - A
               <quote>mix-in</quote> configuration file that defines simulated
               gesture-based glove input using the keyboard. This is only
               required for applications where gesture-based glove input is
               used and a physical glove needs to be simulated.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <para><filename>sim.wand.mixin.jconf</filename> - A
               <quote>mix-in</quote> configuration file that defines simulated
               wand input using the mouse. This is only required for
               applications where wand input is used and needs to be
               simulated. Wand input is defined as a tracked positional device
               with several digital buttons.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <para><filename>standalone.jconf</filename> - A configuration
               file that stands on its own and combines the functionality of
               <filename>sim.base.jconf</filename> and
               <filename>sim.wand.mixin.jconf</filename>. Note that it uses a
               single display window for all input.</para>
            </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

         <section>
            <title>Starting the Application</title>

            <para>Now it is time to run the application—finally! Make sure
            that all your environment variables are set properly before trying
            to start the application. Once you are ready, specify the name of
            the application and all the configuration files it needs. An
            example of this is:</para>

            <screen>% MPApp sim.base.jconf sim.wand.mixin.jconf</screen>

            <para>On Mac OS X, the command would be the following:</para>

            <screen>% MPApp.app/Contents/MacOS/MPApp sim.base.jconf sim.wand.mixin.jconf</screen>

            <para>Notice that no paths are specified for finding the
            configuration files. The full paths to the configuration files is
            not necessary because the default search path will correctly find
            these files in
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR\share\vrjuggler\data\configFiles</filename>
            on Windows or
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler-2.2/data/configFiles</filename>
            on all other platforms. Beginning users will typically want to
            reference the example configuration files in that directory. As
            you get more comfortable with VR Juggler and its configuration
            system, you may want to make your own modified files and put them
            in the directory <filename>$HOME/.vrjconfig</filename>. The
            environment variable <envar>VJ_CFG_PATH</envar> is useful in
            providing a search path for finding your configuration files.
            (Refer to <xref linkend="section.envvars.optional" /> for more
            information on using <envar>VJ_CFG_PATH</envar>). To simplify
            running applications, you may want to make a shell script (or
            batch file as appropriate) that does all the work of passing
            configuration files and common command-line arguments.</para>

            <para>As the application starts, you will see a status output
            printed to the console (more or less depending on how you have
            <envar>VPR_DEBUG_NFY_LEVEL</envar>,
            <envar>VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES</envar>, and
            <envar>VPR_DEBUG_DISALLOW_CATEGORIES</envar> set), and then one
            moderately sized simulator display window will open on the left
            side of your screen while three blank keyboard input windows open
            on the right side of your screen. The display window will be
            titled <quote>SimWindow1</quote>, and the keyboard input windows
            will be titled <quote>Head Keyboard</quote>, <quote>Sim View
            Cameras Control</quote> and <quote>Wand Keyboard</quote> (in order
            from the top of the display to the bottom). Do not worry that the
            keyboard windows are black—that is normal. The display window will
            have an animated blue mesh, a cyan ellipsoid, and a green pointer.
            The mesh is what you have come to see; the ellipsoid is the user's
            head; and the pointer is the user's hand. In <xref
            linkend="figure.MPApp.running" />, we show what this looks on a
            Red Hat Linux 7.2 desktop for comparison with what you are seeing.
            Note that the head and wand are only rendered in the simulator
            windows. They are present because head and wand input are being
            simulated, and it is typically quite helpful to see the results of
            that simulated input. To exit the application, press
            <keysym>ESC</keysym> in the window titled <quote>Head
            Window</quote>.</para>

            <figure id="figure.MPApp.running">
               <title>MPApp Running on a Linux Desktop with Multiple Input
               Windows</title>

               <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                     <imagedata align="center"
                                fileref="figures/MPApp.thumbnail.multi.png"
                                format="PNG" />
                  </imageobject>
               </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>With VR Juggler 2.0 and beyond, it is possible to use a
            single window for graphics and for input. To use such a
            configuration, execute MPApp as follows:</para>

            <screen>% MPApp standalone.jconf</screen>

            <para>On Mac OS X, execute it this way:</para>

            <screen>% MPApp.app/Contents/MacOS/MPApp standalone.jconf</screen>

            <para>This time, only a single window opens, as shown in <xref
            linkend="figure.MPApp.running.single" />. It shows the same
            graphics as before, but now it is configured to take keyboard and
            mouse input. To exit, press <keysym>ESC</keysym> in the graphics
            window.</para>

            <figure id="figure.MPApp.running.single">
               <title>MPApp Running on a Linux Desktop with One Window</title>

               <mediaobject>
                  <imageobject>
                     <imagedata align="center"
                                fileref="figures/MPApp.thumbnail.single.png"
                                format="PNG" />
                  </imageobject>
               </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <section>
               <title>Running an Application on Windows from Within Visual
               Studio</title>

               <para>To run MPApp from within the Visual Studio IDE, the
               program arguments must be set first. This is done by opening
               the properties dialog for the project. In this dialog box,
               choose the <guilabel>Debugging</guilabel> item. There will be
               an empty text entry field under the heading <guilabel>Command
               Arguments</guilabel>. Here, enter the full paths to the VR
               Juggler configuration files that will be used to run the torus
               application. To use the <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> environment
               variable (or any other environment variable), makefile syntax
               must be used. In other words, to load
               <filename>somefile.jconf</filename>, use
               <filename>$(VJ_BASE_DIR)\share\vrjuggler\data\configFiles\somefile.jconf</filename>.
               As was stated above, the full path need not be specified, so
               referencing <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> in the path to the
               example configuration files will not be necessary in most
               cases.. In <xref
               linkend="figure.visual.studio.dialog.project.settings" />, we
               see the use of <filename>standalone.jconf</filename> as the
               single command argument to MPApp.</para>

               <figure id="figure.visual.studio.dialog.project.settings">
                  <title>Setting Command Arguments</title>

                  <mediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="center"
                                   fileref="figures/MPApp.visual.c++.args.png"
                                   format="PNG" />
                     </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
               </figure>

               <para>With the application already compiled, execute the MPApp
               program by choosing the <guimenuitem>Start</guimenuitem> item
               from the <guimenu>Debug</guimenu> menu, shown below in <xref
               linkend="figure.visual.studio.menu.debug.execute" />.</para>

               <figure id="figure.visual.studio.menu.debug.execute">
                  <title>Execute <filename>MPApp.exe</filename></title>

                  <mediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="center"
                                   fileref="figures/MPApp.visual.c++.run.png"
                                   format="PNG" />
                     </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
               </figure>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Running an Application on Mac OS X with Cocoa
               Windows</title>

               <para>In VR juggler 2.2, Cocoa support has been added for Mac
               OS X usage. This gives much better results than the previous
               reliance upon the X Window System. The interface for VR Juggler
               applications on Mac OS X is noticeably different than other
               platforms, however. We will explore those differences in this
               section.</para>

               <para>There are two key differences with VR Juggler on Mac OS X
               from other platforms:</para>

               <orderedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>Applications are constructed as bundles</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>Every application has the usual Mac OS application
                     menu</para>
                  </listitem>
               </orderedlist>

               <para>The use of application bundles is required for software
               based on Cocoa. The topic of application bundles is beyond the
               scope of this document, but Apple has extensive documentation
               available for perusal. For typical VR Juggler applications, the
               bundle data files that come with VR Juggler 2.2 will suffice.
               The application bundle is constructed automatically using these
               files when the <literal>bundle</literal> target is built for
               any VR Juggler application whose build is based on Doozer 2.1.4
               and newer. For builds that are not using Doozer, see the files
               in
               <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler-2.2/data/bundle</filename>
               for a starting point.</para>

               <para>The use of application bundles offers several different
               ways of launching applications. They are as follows:</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>Double-clicking on the application bundle icon in
                     the <application>Finder</application></para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>Opening the bundle (e.g.,
                     <filename>MPApp.app</filename>) from the command line
                     using <command>open</command></para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>Executing the contained application directly from
                     the command line</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>

               <para>We have seen an example of the third option above, and in
               this document, we will always show that approach whenever
               describing how to launch a VR juggler application from the
               command line.</para>

               <para>Using the <command>open</command> command offers two
               different options of its own. It can be used to open the bundle
               in the same way as double-clicking on its icon in the
               <application>Finder</application> would work. This usage is
               shown below:</para>

               <screen>% open MPApp.app</screen>

               <para>The other usage is to open a <filename>.jconf</filename>
               file and tell the <command>open</command> command to use a VR
               Juggler application bundle to handle the file open operation.
               This is done as follows:</para>

               <screen>% open -a MPApp.app $VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler-2.2/data/configFiles/standalone.jconf</screen>

               <para>Note that the paths given to the application bundle and
               to the <filename>.jconf</filename> file must resolve correctly.
               No path searching will be performed for either in this
               case.</para>

               <para>The application menu is defined by the
               <filename>.nib</filename> contained in the application bundle.
               This is hooked up to classes in VR Juggler at run time. The
               application menu is defined with the usual operations for
               window management as well as the <menuchoice>
                     <shortcut>
                        <keycap>Cmd+O</keycap>
                     </shortcut>

                     <guimenu>File</guimenu>

                     <guimenuitem>Open...</guimenuitem>
                  </menuchoice> operation for loading
               <filename>.jconf</filename> files. This feature leverages the
               existing support for run-time reconfiguration of VR Juggler.
               Every time a <filename>.jconf</filename> file is opened using
               the <menuchoice>
                     <shortcut>
                        <keycap>Cmd+O</keycap>
                     </shortcut>

                     <guimenu>File</guimenu>

                     <guimenuitem>Open...</guimenuitem>
                  </menuchoice> operation, VR Juggler reconfigures itself.
               This is basically the same as what can be done with
               <application>VRJConfig</application> when adding new
               configuration information dynamically. It is not possible to
               remove configuration information through this interface;
               <application>VRJConfig</application> must be used for that
               purpose.</para>

               <para>When a VR Juggler application bundle is opened by
               double-clicking on its icon in the
               <application>Finder</application> or by using the first usage
               of the <command>open</command> command described above,
               <emphasis>no configuration files are loaded</emphasis>. The
               <menuchoice>
                     <shortcut>
                        <keycap>Cmd+O</keycap>
                     </shortcut>

                     <guimenu>File</guimenu>

                     <guimenuitem>Open...</guimenuitem>
                  </menuchoice> operation must be used to load configuration
               files and configure VR Juggler. (Even remote run-time
               reconfiguration through <application>VRJConfig</application>
               may not be available at this point unless omniORB was
               configured to find a CORBA Naming Service instance through the
               <envar>OMNIORB_CONFIG</envar> environment variable.)</para>

               <para>VR juggler applications on Mac OS X can be exited using
               the <menuchoice>
                     <shortcut>
                        <keycap>Cmd+Q</keycap>
                     </shortcut>

                     <guimenu>App Menu</guimenu>

                     <guimenuitem>Quit</guimenuitem>
                  </menuchoice> operation or by using the application shutdown
               sequence in the same manner as any other platform. The shutdown
               sequence and the window(s) that accept it depend on the
               configuration. Usually, this is done by pressing the
               <keysym>ESC</keysym> key in a graphics window or in the input
               window for the simulated positional device for the user's
               head.</para>

               <para>The Cocoa version of MPApp is shown executing on a Mac OS
               X desktop in <xref
               linkend="figure.MPApp.running.single.OSX.cocoa" />. Note that
               in the Dock, the VR Juggler icon is activated. Though it cannot
               be seen, the application menu is for MPApp.</para>

               <figure id="figure.MPApp.running.single.OSX.cocoa">
                  <title>MPApp Running on Mac OS X Using Cocoa with One
                  Window</title>

                  <mediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="center"
                                   fileref="figures/MPApp-OSX-Cocoa.thumbnail.single.png"
                                   format="PNG" />
                     </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
               </figure>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Running an Application on Mac OS X with the X Window
               System</title>

               <para>Prior to VR Juggler 2.2, using VR Juggler on Mac OS X
               required the use of the X Window System. VR Juggler 2.2 and
               beyond support native Cocoa windows, but the X Window System
               support still exists for those who want to use it (though it is
               not recommended). This section describes how to run VR Juggler
               applications on Mac OS X with the X Window System for people
               who may need to know about this usage. The average Mac OS X
               user can skip this section since Cocoa will be used
               instead.</para>

               <important>
                  <para>The only way to get full-screen VR juggler windows on
                  Mac OS X is to use the Cocoa windows. If nothing else, this
                  is the biggest single reason not to use the X11 window
                  support on Mac OS X.</para>
               </important>

               <para>Running a VR Juggler application on Mac OS X is slightly
               different if VR Juggler was compiled against <ulink
               url="http://www.apple.com/macosx/x11/">X11 for OS X</ulink>.
               Before starting the VR Juggler application, X11 must be
               running. This can be accomplished by double-clicking on the X11
               icon in the Applications folder. By default, X11 will open a
               standard xterm when it starts. In this xterm, the
               <envar>DISPLAY</envar> environment variable will be set
               correctly, and it is recommended that VR Juggler applications
               be launched from this xterm. From this xterm, set the necessary
               environment variables as described earlier in <xref
               linkend="section.envvars.required" />. Once this is done, the
               application can be executed from the command line just as
               described in the previous section.</para>

               <para>The X11 version of MPApp is shown executing on a Mac OS X
               desktop in <xref
               linkend="figure.MPApp.running.single.OSX.x11" />. Note that in
               the Dock, the X11 icon is activated and that the application
               menu is for an X11 application. This truly is an X11
               application running on OS X.</para>

               <figure id="figure.MPApp.running.single.OSX.x11">
                  <title>MPApp Running on Mac OS X Using X11 with One
                  Window</title>

                  <mediaobject>
                     <imageobject>
                        <imagedata align="center"
                                   fileref="figures/MPApp-OSX.thumbnail.single.png"
                                   format="PNG" />
                     </imageobject>
                  </mediaobject>
               </figure>
            </section>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Basic Desktop Configuration Controls</title>

            <para>So now you are probably wondering what you can do with this
            fancy application. Both of the preceding configurations use the
            same keyboard/mouse mappings; they vary only in which windows
            accept the keyboard and mouse input. Using the multi-window
            configuration, head movement is done with the keyboard in
            <quote>Head Keyboard</quote>; camera movement is done with the
            keyboard in <quote>Sim View Cameras Control</quote>; and wand
            movement is done with the keyboard and mouse in <quote>Wand
            Keyboard</quote>. Using the single-window configuration, all input
            is done with the keyboard and mouse in <quote>Sim Window</quote>.
            Note, however, that for the single-window configuration, the
            camera is attached to the user's head for an over-the-shoulder
            view, and hence, it does not move separately from the head. For
            information on how to verify these settings and to view the
            current configuration, refer to the <emphasis>VRJConfig
            Guide</emphasis>. The following list of tables provides all the
            keyboard and mouse controls for the simulator when using these
            particular configuration files. Note that it is possible to
            reconfigure the simulator to suit your preferences. This is
            provided mainly for those who just want something that works
            now.</para>

            <table>
               <title>Moving the simulated head</title>

               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <thead>
                     <row>
                        <entry>Transformation</entry>

                        <entry>Key Press</entry>
                     </row>
                  </thead>

                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">Move head backward</entry>

                        <entry align="left">2 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">Move head left</entry>

                        <entry align="left">4 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">Move head right</entry>

                        <entry align="left">6 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">Move head forward</entry>

                        <entry align="left">8 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">Move head down</entry>

                        <entry align="left">7 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">Move head up</entry>

                        <entry align="left">9 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">Turn head up</entry>

                        <entry align="left">CTRL+2 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">Turn head left</entry>

                        <entry align="left">CTRL+4 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">Turn head right</entry>

                        <entry align="left">CTRL+6 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">Turn head down</entry>

                        <entry align="left">CTRL+8 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">Rotate head clockwise</entry>

                        <entry align="left">1 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">Rotate head
                        counter-clockwise</entry>

                        <entry align="left">3 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>

            <table>
               <title>Moving the simulated wand</title>

               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <thead>
                     <row>
                        <entry>Transformation</entry>

                        <entry>Mouse Input/Key Press</entry>
                     </row>
                  </thead>

                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>Move wand backward</entry>

                        <entry>ALT+move mouse backward</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Move wand forward</entry>

                        <entry>ALT+move mouse forward</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Move wand left</entry>

                        <entry>CTRL+move mouse left</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Move wand right</entry>

                        <entry>CTRL+move mouse right</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Move wand up</entry>

                        <entry>CTRL+move mouse forward</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Move wand down</entry>

                        <entry>CTRL+move mouse backward</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Rotate wand left</entry>

                        <entry>SHIFT+move mouse left</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Rotate wand right</entry>

                        <entry>SHIFT+move mouse right</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Rotate wand up</entry>

                        <entry>SHIFT+move mouse backward</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Rotate wand down</entry>

                        <entry>SHIFT+move mouse forward</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Rotate wand clockwise</entry>

                        <entry>Right arrow</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Rotate wand counter-clockwise</entry>

                        <entry>Left arrow</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Wand button #1</entry>

                        <entry>Left mouse button</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Wand button #2</entry>

                        <entry>Middle mouse button</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Wand button #3</entry>

                        <entry>Right mouse button</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Wand button #4</entry>

                        <entry>4</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Wand button #5</entry>

                        <entry>5</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Wand button #6</entry>

                        <entry>6</entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>

            <table>
               <title>Moving the camera (multi-window configuration
               only)</title>

               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <thead>
                     <row>
                        <entry>Transformation</entry>

                        <entry>Key Press</entry>
                     </row>
                  </thead>

                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry>Move camera backward</entry>

                        <entry>2 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Move camera left</entry>

                        <entry>4 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Move camera right</entry>

                        <entry>6 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Move camera forward</entry>

                        <entry>8 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Move camera down</entry>

                        <entry>7 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Move camera up</entry>

                        <entry>9 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Turn camera up</entry>

                        <entry>CTRL+2 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Turn camera left</entry>

                        <entry>CTRL+4 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Turn camera right</entry>

                        <entry>CTRL+6 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Turn camera down</entry>

                        <entry>CTRL+8 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Rotate camera clockwise</entry>

                        <entry>1 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry>Rotate camera counter-clockwise</entry>

                        <entry>3 on keypad</entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>

            <para>Before continuing on to running an application in a
            full-scale VR system, we provide two asides: using a simulated
            glove and using a simulated analog device. The examples provided
            thus far have not discussed this because the information was not
            relevant to the particular sample application being used. Knowing
            how to use these simulated devices is important, however, and it
            is treated separately as a reference for your future endeavors in
            running VR Juggler applications.</para>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Using a Simulated Glove</title>

            <para>If you include the
            <filename>sim.glove.mixin.jconf</filename> file, your application
            will also have access to a simulated glove, with position and
            gesture inputs. The glove is controlled by a window titled
            <quote>Glove Keyboard</quote>. This window lets you control the
            glove position and selected gesture. Movement control of the glove
            uses the mouse and is the same as that of the wand. The mouse
            buttons are used to select gestures. The mapping of the gesture
            numbers to actual hand positions is controlled by the
            <quote>training file</quote> for the simulated glove device. The
            default training file is
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/gesture/simpleSimGestures.dat</filename>.</para>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Using a Simulated Analog Device</title>

            <para>If you include the
            <filename>sim.analog.wandmixin.jconf</filename> file, your
            application will also have access to a set of four analog devices
            (devices with a value in a range from 0.0 to 1.0). The analog
            devices are also controlled using the <quote>Wand Keyboard</quote>
            window which means that their configuration file requires the wand
            configuration file.</para>

            <note>
               <para>A separate file,
               <filename>sim.analog.mixin.jconf</filename>, is provided for
               analog input from a separate simulator window.</para>
            </note>

            <para>The key presses used for controlling the analog devices are
            listed in <xref linkend="table.sim.analog.keys" />.</para>

            <table id="table.sim.analog.keys">
               <title>Analog Device Simulator Keys</title>

               <tgroup cols="2">
                  <thead>
                     <row>
                        <entry align="center">Analog Device Action</entry>

                        <entry align="center">Key Press</entry>
                     </row>
                  </thead>

                  <tbody>
                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">VJAnalog0 increase</entry>

                        <entry align="center">Q</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">VJAnalog0 decrease</entry>

                        <entry align="center">A</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">VJAnalog1 increase</entry>

                        <entry align="center">W</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">VJAnalog1 decrease</entry>

                        <entry align="center">S</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">VJAnalog2 increase</entry>

                        <entry align="center">E</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">VJAnalog2 decrease</entry>

                        <entry align="center">D</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">VJAnalog3 increase</entry>

                        <entry align="center">R</entry>
                     </row>

                     <row>
                        <entry align="left">VJAnalog3 decrease</entry>

                        <entry align="center">F</entry>
                     </row>
                  </tbody>
               </tgroup>
            </table>
         </section>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Running an Application in a VR System</title>

         <para>Running an application full-scale in a VR system tends to be
         more complicated than running with a simulator configuration. The
         reason for this is that VR systems tend to differ in configuration
         and in available hardware. VR Juggler is flexible enough to handle
         most any configuration you throw at it, but those configurations need
         to be put together first. VR systems can be driven by a single,
         multi-pipe machine or a cluster of computers communicating over a
         network. VR Juggler supports both, and the details are captured in
         the configuration.</para>

         <para>Example configuration files for different VR system
         configurations come with VR Juggler. An example of using a single
         multi-pipe computer is shown for VRAC's C4 system when it was driven
         by a single multi-pipe SGI Onyx computer. For a cluster, there is a
         configuration file for VRAC's so-called <quote>ptah cluster</quote>
         that ran Linux. It should be noted, however, that for any particular
         VR system, custom configuration files will almost certainly have to
         be written. The idea behind this section is to provide a basic
         understanding of what is needed to get started with running in a VR
         system. Configuration topics are addressed in the VR Juggler
         <emphasis>Configuration Guide</emphasis>.</para>

         <section>
            <title>Single Machine Configuration</title>

            <para>The example configuration files in the directory
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/configFiles</filename>
            modeled after those used for VRAC's Onyx-powered C4 system are as
            follows:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para><filename>C4.closed.jconf</filename> - The single
                  configuration file that includes the other configuration
                  files necessary for loading a VR Juggler application in the
                  C4 in its closed configuration with full tracking and
                  stereoscopic graphics.</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para><filename>C4.closed.mono.jconf</filename> - The single
                  configuration file that includes the other configuration
                  files necessary for loading a VR Juggler application in the
                  C4 in its closed configuration with full tracking and
                  monoscopic graphics.</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para><filename>C4.base.jconf</filename> - The basic
                  configuration file needed by all applications when run in
                  the C4. It defines commonly used VR Juggler concepts that
                  are beyond the scope of this particular book.</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para><filename>C4.displays.closed.jconf</filename> - The
                  basic display configuration file needed to run with all four
                  walls active and rendering stereoscopic graphics. This
                  defines only the four surface displays to be opened. The
                  corners are configured for the closed position of the
                  movable walls.</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para><filename>C4.displays.closed.mono.jconf</filename> -
                  The basic display configuration file needed to run with all
                  four walls active and rendering monoscopic graphics. This
                  defines only the four surface displays to be opened. The
                  corners are configured for the closed position of the
                  movable walls.</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para><filename>C4.mstar.jconf</filename> - The Ascension
                  MotionStar configuration file that defines which bird
                  provides input for the head and for the wand.</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para><filename>C4.rfwand.jconf</filename> - The radio
                  frequency wireless mouse that acts as a wand.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>Running the application is the same as with a simulator
            configuration except that the configuration files given on the
            command line are different. For example, to run MPApp in the C4
            with stereoscopic graphics, the following command would be
            used:</para>

            <screen>% MPApp C4.closed.jconf</screen>

            <para>On Mac OS X, the following command would be used:</para>

            <screen>% MPApp.app/Contents/MacOS/MPApp C4.closed.jconf</screen>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Cluster Configuration</title>

            <important>
               <para>The usage of VR Juggler on a cluster has changed since VR
               Juggler 1.1 through 2.2. A strict client/server architecture is
               now used, and the roles of the cluster master (the server) and
               the cluster slaves (the clients) must be defined clearly in the
               configuration and when an application is run.</para>
            </important>

            <para>Clusters involve multiple machines, and running VR Juggler
            on a cluster means running the application on every node of that
            cluster. Every node must load the same configuration whether it is
            defined in multiple files or in a single file. VR Juggler (more
            specifically, Gadgeteer) sorts out which parts of the
            configuration apply to each node<footnote>
                  <para>The details of how to configure a cluster are beyond
                  the scope of this document; readers are directed to the VR
                  Juggler <emphasis>Configuration Guide</emphasis>.</para>
               </footnote>.</para>

            <para>The way that any given cluster-ready VR Juggler application
            works is up to the people who created the application.
            Applications may use varying command line options depending on the
            role of the node in the cluster, or different applications may be
            run on each node, again depending on the role of the node. Two
            things remain consistent, however:</para>

            <orderedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>A command line option is required to indicate whether
                  the node is the cluster master
                  (<option>--vrjmaster</option>) or a cluster slave
                  (<option>--vrjslave</option>), and</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para>The VR Juggler configuration files are loaded
                  <emphasis>only</emphasis> by the cluster master.</para>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>

            <para>For MPApp, the usage on a cluster is the same as what we
            have shown previously. The only things that change are the
            configuration files that are loaded and the execution of the
            <command>MPApp</command> binary on <emphasis>all nodes of the
            cluster</emphasis>. If we were to use the example configuration
            <filename>ptah.cluster.jconf</filename>, the usage on the cluster
            master would be as follows:</para>

            <screen>% MPApp --vrjmaster ptah.cluster.jconf</screen>

            <para>On all the cluster slave nodes, the usage would be the
            following:</para>

            <screen>% MPApp --vrjslave</screen>

            <para>On Mac OS X, the following command would be used on the
            cluster master:</para>

            <screen>% MPApp.app/Contents/MacOS/MPApp --vrjmaster ptah.cluster.jconf</screen>

            <para>On the cluster slaves, the command is as follows:</para>

            <screen>% MPApp.app/Contents/MacOS/MPApp --vrjslave</screen>

            <para>Note that the cluster slave nodes do not load any VR Juggler
            configuration files. The relevant parts of the configuration are
            distributed over the network by the cluster master to each of the
            cluster slaves.</para>
         </section>
      </section>
   </chapter>

   <appendix id="appendix.gfdl">
      <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>

      <subtitle>Version 1.2, November 2002</subtitle>

      <blockquote id="fsf-copyright">
         <title>FSF Copyright note</title>

         <para>Copyright (C) 2000,2001,2002 Free Software Foundation, Inc. 59
         Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307 USA Everyone is
         permitted to copy and distribute verbatim copies of this license
         document, but changing it is not allowed.</para>
      </blockquote>

      <section id="gfdl-0">
         <title>PREAMBLE</title>

         <para>The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or
         other functional and useful document "free" in the sense of freedom:
         to assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it,
         with or without modifying it, either commercially or noncommercially.
         Secondarily, this License preserves for the author and publisher a
         way to get credit for their work, while not being considered
         responsible for modifications made by others.</para>

         <para>This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that
         derivative works of the document must themselves be free in the same
         sense. It complements the GNU General Public License, which is a
         copyleft license designed for free software.</para>

         <para>We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals
         for free software, because free software needs free documentation: a
         free program should come with manuals providing the same freedoms
         that the software does. But this License is not limited to software
         manuals; it can be used for any textual work, regardless of subject
         matter or whether it is published as a printed book. We recommend
         this License principally for works whose purpose is instruction or
         reference.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="gfdl-1">
         <title>APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS</title>

         <para id="gfdl-doc">This License applies to any manual or other work,
         in any medium, that contains a notice placed by the copyright holder
         saying it can be distributed under the terms of this License. Such a
         notice grants a world-wide, royalty-free license, unlimited in
         duration, to use that work under the conditions stated herein. The
         "Document", below, refers to any such manual or work. Any member of
         the public is a licensee, and is addressed as "you". You accept the
         license if you copy, modify or distribute the work in a way requiring
         permission under copyright law.</para>

         <para id="gfdl-mod-ver">A "Modified Version" of the Document means
         any work containing the Document or a portion of it, either copied
         verbatim, or with modifications and/or translated into another
         language.</para>

         <para id="gfdl-secnd-sect">A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix
         or a front-matter section of the Document that deals exclusively with
         the relationship of the publishers or authors of the Document to the
         Document's overall subject (or to related matters) and contains
         nothing that could fall directly within that overall subject. (Thus,
         if the Document is in part a textbook of mathematics, a Secondary
         Section may not explain any mathematics.) The relationship could be a
         matter of historical connection with the subject or with related
         matters, or of legal, commercial, philosophical, ethical or political
         position regarding them.</para>

         <para id="gfdl-inv-sect">The "Invariant Sections" are certain
         Secondary Sections whose titles are designated, as being those of
         Invariant Sections, in the notice that says that the Document is
         released under this License. If a section does not fit the above
         definition of Secondary then it is not allowed to be designated as
         Invariant. The Document may contain zero Invariant Sections. If the
         Document does not identify any Invariant Sections then there are
         none.</para>

         <para id="gfdl-cov-text">The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages
         of text that are listed, as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in
         the notice that says that the Document is released under this
         License. A Front-Cover Text may be at most 5 words, and a Back-Cover
         Text may be at most 25 words.</para>

         <para id="gfdl-transparent">A "Transparent" copy of the Document
         means a machine-readable copy, represented in a format whose
         specification is available to the general public, that is suitable
         for revising the document straightforwardly with generic text editors
         or (for images composed of pixels) generic paint programs or (for
         drawings) some widely available drawing editor, and that is suitable
         for input to text formatters or for automatic translation to a
         variety of formats suitable for input to text formatters. A copy made
         in an otherwise Transparent file format whose markup, or absence of
         markup, has been arranged to thwart or discourage subsequent
         modification by readers is not Transparent. An image format is not
         Transparent if used for any substantial amount of text. A copy that
         is not "Transparent" is called "Opaque".</para>

         <para>Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include
         plain ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input format,
         SGML or XML using a publicly available DTD, and standard-conforming
         simple HTML, PostScript or PDF designed for human modification.
         Examples of transparent image formats include PNG, XCF and JPG.
         Opaque formats include proprietary formats that can be read and
         edited only by proprietary word processors, SGML or XML for which the
         DTD and/or processing tools are not generally available, and the
         machine-generated HTML, PostScript or PDF produced by some word
         processors for output purposes only.</para>

         <para id="gfdl-title-page">The "Title Page" means, for a printed
         book, the title page itself, plus such following pages as are needed
         to hold, legibly, the material this License requires to appear in the
         title page. For works in formats which do not have any title page as
         such, "Title Page" means the text near the most prominent appearance
         of the work's title, preceding the beginning of the body of the
         text.</para>

         <para id="gfdl-entitled">A section "Entitled XYZ" means a named
         subunit of the Document whose title either is precisely XYZ or
         contains XYZ in parentheses following text that translates XYZ in
         another language. (Here XYZ stands for a specific section name
         mentioned below, such as "Acknowledgements", "Dedications",
         "Endorsements", or "History".) To "Preserve the Title" of such a
         section when you modify the Document means that it remains a section
         "Entitled XYZ" according to this definition.</para>

         <para>The Document may include Warranty Disclaimers next to the
         notice which states that this License applies to the Document. These
         Warranty Disclaimers are considered to be included by reference in
         this License, but only as regards disclaiming warranties: any other
         implication that these Warranty Disclaimers may have is void and has
         no effect on the meaning of this License.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="gfdl-2">
         <title>VERBATIM COPYING</title>

         <para>You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium, either
         commercially or noncommercially, provided that this License, the
         copyright notices, and the license notice saying this License applies
         to the Document are reproduced in all copies, and that you add no
         other conditions whatsoever to those of this License. You may not use
         technical measures to obstruct or control the reading or further
         copying of the copies you make or distribute. However, you may accept
         compensation in exchange for copies. If you distribute a large enough
         number of copies you must also follow the conditions in section
         3.</para>

         <para>You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated
         above, and you may publicly display copies.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="gfdl-3">
         <title>COPYING IN QUANTITY</title>

         <para>If you publish printed copies (or copies in media that commonly
         have printed covers) of the Document, numbering more than 100, and
         the Document's license notice requires Cover Texts, you must enclose
         the copies in covers that carry, clearly and legibly, all these Cover
         Texts: Front-Cover Texts on the front cover, and Back-Cover Texts on
         the back cover. Both covers must also clearly and legibly identify
         you as the publisher of these copies. The front cover must present
         the full title with all words of the title equally prominent and
         visible. You may add other material on the covers in addition.
         Copying with changes limited to the covers, as long as they preserve
         the title of the Document and satisfy these conditions, can be
         treated as verbatim copying in other respects.</para>

         <para>If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to
         fit legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit
         reasonably) on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto adjacent
         pages.</para>

         <para>If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document
         numbering more than 100, you must either include a machine-readable
         Transparent copy along with each Opaque copy, or state in or with
         each Opaque copy a computer-network location from which the general
         network-using public has access to download using public-standard
         network protocols a complete Transparent copy of the Document, free
         of added material. If you use the latter option, you must take
         reasonably prudent steps, when you begin distribution of Opaque
         copies in quantity, to ensure that this Transparent copy will remain
         thus accessible at the stated location until at least one year after
         the last time you distribute an Opaque copy (directly or through your
         agents or retailers) of that edition to the public.</para>

         <para>It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors
         of the Document well before redistributing any large number of
         copies, to give them a chance to provide you with an updated version
         of the Document.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="gfdl-4">
         <title>MODIFICATIONS</title>

         <para>You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the Document
         under the conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided that you
         release the Modified Version under precisely this License, with the
         Modified Version filling the role of the Document, thus licensing
         distribution and modification of the Modified Version to whoever
         possesses a copy of it. In addition, you must do these things in the
         Modified Version:</para>

         <orderedlist id="gfdl-modif-cond" numeration="upperalpha">
            <title>GNU FDL Modification Conditions</title>

            <listitem>
               <simpara>Use in the Title Page (and on the covers, if any) a
               title distinct from that of the Document, and from those of
               previous versions (which should, if there were any, be listed
               in the History section of the Document). You may use the same
               title as a previous version if the original publisher of that
               version gives permission.</simpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <simpara>List on the Title Page, as authors, one or more
               persons or entities responsible for authorship of the
               modifications in the Modified Version, together with at least
               five of the principal authors of the Document (all of its
               principal authors, if it has fewer than five), unless they
               release you from this requirement.</simpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <simpara>State on the Title page the name of the publisher of
               the Modified Version, as the publisher.</simpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <simpara>Preserve all the copyright notices of the
               Document.</simpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <simpara>Add an appropriate copyright notice for your
               modifications adjacent to the other copyright
               notices.</simpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <simpara>Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a
               license notice giving the public permission to use the Modified
               Version under the terms of this License, in the form shown in
               the <link linkend="gfdl-addendum">Addendum</link>
               below.</simpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <simpara>Preserve in that license notice the full lists of
               Invariant Sections and required Cover Texts given in the
               Document's license notice.</simpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <simpara>Include an unaltered copy of this License.</simpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <simpara>Preserve the section Entitled "History", Preserve its
               Title, and add to it an item stating at least the title, year,
               new authors, and publisher of the Modified Version as given on
               the Title Page. If there is no section Entitled "History" in
               the Document, create one stating the title, year, authors, and
               publisher of the Document as given on its Title Page, then add
               an item describing the Modified Version as stated in the
               previous sentence.</simpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <simpara>Preserve the network location, if any, given in the
               Document for public access to a Transparent copy of the
               Document, and likewise the network locations given in the
               Document for previous versions it was based on. These may be
               placed in the "History" section. You may omit a network
               location for a work that was published at least four years
               before the Document itself, or if the original publisher of the
               version it refers to gives permission.</simpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <simpara>For any section Entitled "Acknowledgements" or
               "Dedications", Preserve the Title of the section, and preserve
               in the section all the substance and tone of each of the
               contributor acknowledgements and/or dedications given
               therein.</simpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <simpara>Preserve all the Invariant Sections of the Document,
               unaltered in their text and in their titles. Section numbers or
               the equivalent are not considered part of the section
               titles.</simpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <simpara>Delete any section Entitled "Endorsements". Such a
               section may not be included in the Modified Version.</simpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <simpara>Do not retitle any existing section to be Entitled
               "Endorsements" or to conflict in title with any Invariant
               Section.</simpara>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
               <simpara>Preserve any Warranty Disclaimers.</simpara>
            </listitem>
         </orderedlist>

         <para>If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections or
         appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no material
         copied from the Document, you may at your option designate some or
         all of these sections as invariant. To do this, add their titles to
         the list of Invariant Sections in the Modified Version's license
         notice. These titles must be distinct from any other section
         titles.</para>

         <para>You may add a section Entitled "Endorsements", provided it
         contains nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by various
         parties--for example, statements of peer review or that the text has
         been approved by an organization as the authoritative definition of a
         standard.</para>

         <para>You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover
         Text, and a passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the
         end of the list of Cover Texts in the Modified Version. Only one
         passage of Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be added
         by (or through arrangements made by) any one entity. If the Document
         already includes a cover text for the same cover, previously added by
         you or by arrangement made by the same entity you are acting on
         behalf of, you may not add another; but you may replace the old one,
         on explicit permission from the previous publisher that added the old
         one.</para>

         <para>The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by this
         License give permission to use their names for publicity for or to
         assert or imply endorsement of any Modified Version.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="gfdl-5">
         <title>COMBINING DOCUMENTS</title>

         <para>You may combine the Document with other documents released
         under this License, under the terms defined in <link
         linkend="gfdl-4">section 4</link> above for modified versions,
         provided that you include in the combination all of the Invariant
         Sections of all of the original documents, unmodified, and list them
         all as Invariant Sections of your combined work in its license
         notice, and that you preserve all their Warranty Disclaimers.</para>

         <para>The combined work need only contain one copy of this License,
         and multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced with a
         single copy. If there are multiple Invariant Sections with the same
         name but different contents, make the title of each such section
         unique by adding at the end of it, in parentheses, the name of the
         original author or publisher of that section if known, or else a
         unique number. Make the same adjustment to the section titles in the
         list of Invariant Sections in the license notice of the combined
         work.</para>

         <para>In the combination, you must combine any sections Entitled
         "History" in the various original documents, forming one section
         Entitled "History"; likewise combine any sections Entitled
         "Acknowledgements", and any sections Entitled "Dedications". You must
         delete all sections Entitled "Endorsements".</para>
      </section>

      <section id="gfdl-6">
         <title>COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS</title>

         <para>You may make a collection consisting of the Document and other
         documents released under this License, and replace the individual
         copies of this License in the various documents with a single copy
         that is included in the collection, provided that you follow the
         rules of this License for verbatim copying of each of the documents
         in all other respects.</para>

         <para>You may extract a single document from such a collection, and
         distribute it individually under this License, provided you insert a
         copy of this License into the extracted document, and follow this
         License in all other respects regarding verbatim copying of that
         document.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="gfdl-7">
         <title>AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS</title>

         <para>A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other
         separate and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of a
         storage or distribution medium, is called an "aggregate" if the
         copyright resulting from the compilation is not used to limit the
         legal rights of the compilation's users beyond what the individual
         works permit. When the Document is included in an aggregate, this
         License does not apply to the other works in the aggregate which are
         not themselves derivative works of the Document.</para>

         <para>If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to
         these copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than one
         half of the entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts may be
         placed on covers that bracket the Document within the aggregate, or
         the electronic equivalent of covers if the Document is in electronic
         form. Otherwise they must appear on printed covers that bracket the
         whole aggregate.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="gfdl-8">
         <title>TRANSLATION</title>

         <para>Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
         distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section 4.
         Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires special
         permission from their copyright holders, but you may include
         translations of some or all Invariant Sections in addition to the
         original versions of these Invariant Sections. You may include a
         translation of this License, and all the license notices in the
         Document, and any Warranty Disclaimers, provided that you also
         include the original English version of this License and the original
         versions of those notices and disclaimers. In case of a disagreement
         between the translation and the original version of this License or a
         notice or disclaimer, the original version will prevail.</para>

         <para>If a section in the Document is Entitled "Acknowledgements",
         "Dedications", or "History", the requirement (section 4) to Preserve
         its Title (section 1) will typically require changing the actual
         title.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="gfdl-9">
         <title>TERMINATION</title>

         <para>You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the
         Document except as expressly provided for under this License. Any
         other attempt to copy, modify, sublicense or distribute the Document
         is void, and will automatically terminate your rights under this
         License. However, parties who have received copies, or rights, from
         you under this License will not have their licenses terminated so
         long as such parties remain in full compliance.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="gfdl-10">
         <title>FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE</title>

         <para>The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised versions
         of the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time. Such new
         versions will be similar in spirit to the present version, but may
         differ in detail to address new problems or concerns. See
         http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/.</para>

         <para>Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version
         number. If the Document specifies that a particular numbered version
         of this License "or any later version" applies to it, you have the
         option of following the terms and conditions either of that specified
         version or of any later version that has been published (not as a
         draft) by the Free Software Foundation. If the Document does not
         specify a version number of this License, you may choose any version
         ever published (not as a draft) by the Free Software
         Foundation.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="gfdl-addendum">
         <title>ADDENDUM: How to use this License for your documents</title>

         <para>To use this License in a document you have written, include a
         copy of the License in the document and put the following copyright
         and license notices just after the title page:</para>

         <blockquote id="copyright-sample">
            <title>Sample Invariant Sections list</title>

            <para>Copyright (c) YEAR YOUR NAME. Permission is granted to copy,
            distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU
            Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 or any later version
            published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant
            Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of
            the license is included in the section entitled "GNU Free
            Documentation License".</para>
         </blockquote>

         <para>If you have Invariant Sections, Front-Cover Texts and
         Back-Cover Texts, replace the "with...Texts." line with this:</para>

         <blockquote id="inv-cover-sample">
            <title>Sample Invariant Sections list</title>

            <para>with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with
            the Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts
            being LIST.</para>
         </blockquote>

         <para>If you have Invariant Sections without Cover Texts, or some
         other combination of the three, merge those two alternatives to suit
         the situation.</para>

         <para>If your document contains nontrivial examples of program code,
         we recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your choice
         of free software license, such as the GNU General Public License, to
         permit their use in free software.</para>
      </section>
   </appendix>
</book>