<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>VR Juggler</title>

    <subtitle>Getting Started Guide</subtitle>

    <releaseinfo>Version 2.0 Alpha 1</releaseinfo>

    <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
  </bookinfo>

  <preface>
    <title>Preface</title>

    <para>This book is for people who are just getting started with VR
    Juggler. It guides new users through getting and installing VR Juggler,
    configuring users&#39; environment to use it, and compiling and running a
    sample application.</para>

    <para>The prerequisites for reading this book are minimal. They are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Some experience with a command-line interface (i.e., a shell
        such as tcsh or the DOS shell)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Creating and browsing directories</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Those users who want to get more involved with VR Juggler to do more
    than just run applications should be aware right away of the following
    prerequisites:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Knowledge of C++ and object-oriented design</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Knowledge of one of VR Juggler&#39;s currently supported
        graphics APIs (<ulink url="http://www.opengl.org/">OpenGL</ulink>,
        <ulink url="http://www.sgi.com/software/performer/">OpenGL Performer</ulink>,
        <ulink url="http://www.opensg.org/">OpenSG</ulink>, or <ulink
        url="http://www.openscenegraph.org/">Open Scene Graph</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </preface>

  <chapter id="install.vrj.chapter">
    <title>Installing VR Juggler</title>

    <para>As with most Open Source projects, VR Juggler is distributed as
    compressed archive files using popular formats. Installing a distribution
    requires very little effort, but you do need to know how to use archiving
    utilities to extract the installation tree. Automation of the installation
    is a goal of the VR Juggler team, but we are still finalizing the details
    of cross-platform installation management. Before reading further, you
    should know where you want to install VR Juggler, and you should make sure
    that you have access to write to that directory.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Installing from a Compressed TAR File</title>

      <para>The TAR (Tape ARchive) format has been around for a long, long
      time in the UNIX world. It is simply a collection of files in a
      directory tree that are lumped into a single file suitable for writing
      to a tape or for downloading. The format is a standard, and the
      <command>tar</command>(1) utility is available on every UNIX-based
      platform and on Win32. A free version can be downloaded from <ulink
      url="http://www.gnu.org/">the GNU Project</ulink>. A compressed TAR file
      is made for each VR Juggler distribution, and some distributions come in
      other formats as well. You can always count on the availability of a TAR
      file, though. The TAR files are compressed using either GZIP or BZIP2,
      both of which are standard compression formats. The <command>gzip</command>(1)
      utility is freely available from the GNU Project, and the
      <command>bzip2</command>(1) utility can be downloaded for free from
      <ulink url="http://sources.redhat.com/bzip2/">RedHat, Inc.</ulink>. The
      GNU version of TAR has the GZIP and BZIP2 algorithms built in. The
      compression algorithm used can be determined by the file extension.
      Files compressed with GZIP end in <filename>.gz</filename>; files
      compressed with BZIP2 end in <filename>.bz2</filename>.</para>

      <para>Once you have downloaded a VR Juggler TAR distribution, you can
      unpack it one of two ways depending on what your platform&#39;s version
      of TAR supports. Before extracting the installation tree, make sure that
      your current directory is the one where you want to install VR Juggler.
      If your version of TAR does not have GZIP built in (it does not support
      the <option>-z</option> option), the following command will do the
      decompression and extraction:</para>

      <screen>% gzip -cd vrjuggler-distribution.tar.gz | tar -xvf -</screen>

      <para>For versions of TAR without built-in BZIP2 support (there is no
      <option>-j</option> option) the command is similar:</para>

      <screen>% bzip2 -cd vrjuggler-distribution.tar.bz2 | tar -xvf -</screen>

      <para>Here, you should fill in <filename>vrjuggler-distribution.tar.gz</filename>
      (or <filename>vrjuggler-distribution.tar.bz2</filename>) with the name
      of the VR Juggler distribution file you downloaded. The above commands
      will work with any shell that supports redirection of standard output to
      a pipe. If that looks too scary, you can separate the decompression and
      extraction into two commands (for GZIP):</para>

      <screen>% gunzip vrjuggler-distribution.tar.gz
% tar -xvf vrjuggler-distribution.tar</screen>

      <para>or for BZIP2:</para>

      <screen>% bunzip2 vrjuggler-distribution.tar.bz2
% tar -xvf vrjuggler-distribution.tar</screen>

      <para>Note that the distribution file in the second command does not
      have the <filename>.gz</filename> extension after <command>gzip</command>(1)
      is run. These steps also work if your version of <command>tar</command>(1)
      supports the <option>-z</option> option (<option>-j</option> for BZIP2),
      but you can simplify your work if that option is supported. The
      following illustrates how to decompress and extract a TAR file
      compressed with GZIP all in one step:</para>

      <screen>% tar -xzvf vrjuggler-distribution.tar.gz</screen>

      <para>The following would be used for a TAR file compressed with BZIP2:</para>

      <screen>% tar -xjvf vrjuggler-distribution.tar.bz2</screen>

      <para>In either case, while the command runs, you will see the name of
      each file as it is written to disk. This is because of the
      <option>-v</option> option to <command>tar</command>(1) that tells it to
      be verbose in its efforts. <command>tar</command>(1) takes care of
      creating all the directories in the installation tree, so you only need
      to have the base directory (for example, <filename>/usr/local</filename>)
      when you start. For more information about these utilities, please refer
      to the <command>tar</command>(1) and <command>gzip</command>(1) manual
      pages.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installing from a ZIP File (Win32 only)</title>

      <para>On the Win32 family of platforms, the ZIP format rules. In the old
      days, you would use the PKZIP utility to uncompress and extract a ZIP
      file. Nowadays, most people use <ulink url="http://www.winzip.com/">WinZip</ulink>
      or some other comparable graphical interface. This documentation covers
      only the use of WinZip when extracting a ZIP file.</para>

      <para>Once you have downloaded the VR Juggler ZIP file, the easiest way
      to extract it is to double-click on its icon in the open folder window
      as shown in <xref linkend="windows.temp.folder-view.figure" />.</para>

      <figure id="windows.temp.folder-view.figure">
        <title>Windows Folder View of ZIP File</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/Window.Download.png"
            format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Double-clicking opens the main WinZip window, as shown in <xref
      linkend="winzip.main.figure" />.</para>

      <figure id="winzip.main.figure">
        <title>Open WinZip Window</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/Window.WinZip.png"
            format="PNG" scalefit="1" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Note that in this screen shot, the <guibutton>Extract</guibutton>
      button is highlighted. Click this button to open the following window.
      Note that in this screen shot, the <guibutton>Extract</guibutton> button
      is highlighted. Click this button to open the dialog box shown in <xref
      linkend="winzip.extract.figure" />.</para>

      <figure id="winzip.extract.figure">
        <title>WinZip Extract Dialog</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
            fileref="figures/Window.WinZip.Extract.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>In this window, choose the directory where VR Juggler will be
      installed and click <guibutton>Extract</guibutton>. WinZip will then
      proceed to extract the ZIP file into the directory you named. That is
      all there is to it.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="envvar.chapter">
    <title>Environment Variables</title>

    <para>There are several <firstterm>environment variables</firstterm> that
    affect the way VR Juggler works. Some of these are required to compile and
    run applications while others are optional. This chapter lists all such
    variables and explains their meanings and uses.</para>

    <section>
      <title>How to Set Environment Variables</title>

      <para>The syntax for setting or changing an environment variable varies
      with operating systems and shell interpreters. Instead of choosing one
      style of syntax that is specific to a particular shell type, we define
      our own syntax which you must then translate to your shell&#39;s
      specific syntax. Before defining this syntax, we present the method used
      to set environment variables in the three most common types of shells.
      We also provide a quick overview of how to set environment variables
      using Win32-based GUIs.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Common Conventions and Background</title>

        <para>A convention used throughout this book is to name the variables
        using all capital letters. In almost all cases, regardless of the
        shell, this is the naming convention used for environment variables.</para>

        <para>Setting a path with an environment variable can require special
        syntax. Because of this, the method for doing so may vary from shell
        to shell. Paths are important with VR Juggler when looking up the path
        to a shared library (dynamically linked library). For each shell, the
        syntax for setting a path is given.</para>

        <para>Referring to environment variables can also vary from shell to
        shell. An example of how to print the value of an environment variable
        will be given for each shell. An example of how to refer to an
        environment variable is also provided as these two operations may vary
        even within one kind of shell!</para>

        <para>In all shells, an environment variable is only available within
        that single shell instance. That is, setting an environment variable
        at a command prompt only affects that specific shell and will not be
        available from other concurrent or future shells. To make a setting
        <quote>permanent</quote>, it should be done in file read by all shell
        instances when they are started. This is addressed briefly as
        appropriate for each shell type.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>C-Style Shells (csh, tcsh)</title>

        <para>In a C-style shell (i.e., one whose interface is based on the C
        programming language), setting environment variables is done using the
        built-in command <command>setenv</command>. It is used as follows:</para>

        <screen>% setenv &#60;VARIABLE_NAME&#62; &#60;value&#62;</screen>

        <para>where the string <literal>&#60;VARIABLE_NAME&#62;</literal>
        represents the name of the variable you are going to set and
        <literal>&#60;value&#62;</literal> represents the value assigned to
        that variable. Both are required. If the named variable did not exist
        before, it will pop into existence. Otherwise, you overwrite the old
        setting with the new one.</para>

        <para>To print the value of an environment variable, use the following
        command:</para>

        <screen>% printenv &#60;VARIABLE_NAME&#62;</screen>

        <para>Referring to a variable, however, is done using the following
        syntax:</para>

        <screen>% cd $VARIABLE_NAME/bin</screen>

        <para>Paths are specified as a colon-separated list. An example of
        this is:</para>

        <screen>% printenv PATH
/bin:/sbin:/usr/bin:/usr/sbin</screen>

        <para>For these types of shells, a <quote>permanent</quote> setting
        for a given variable should usually be done in your .cshrc file or in
        your <filename>.login</filename> file, both of which should be in your
        home directory. In most cases, it is better to use
        <filename>.cshrc</filename> because it is evaluated for every shell
        instance.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>sh-Derived Shells (sh, ksh, bash, zsh, etc.)</title>

        <para>In a shell based on sh, setting environment variables is done
        using the built-in command <command>export</command>. It is used as
        follows:</para>

        <screen>% export &#60;VARIABLE_NAME&#62;=&#60;value&#62;</screen>

        <para>or</para>

        <screen>% &#60;VARIABLE_NAME&#62;=&#60;value&#62;
% export &#60;VARIABLE_NAME&#62;</screen>

        <para>Here, the string <literal>&#60;VARIABLE_NAME&#62;</literal>
        represents the name of the variable you are going to set and
        <literal>&#60;value&#62;</literal> represents the value assigned to
        that variable. Both are required. Note that there is no space between
        the variable name and its value. If the named variable did not exist
        before, it will pop into existence. Otherwise, you overwrite the old
        setting with the new one. If the variable was already among your
        current shell&#39;s environment variables, the export command is not
        necessary.</para>

        <para>To print the value of an environment variable, use the following
        command:</para>

        <screen>% echo $VARIABLE_NAME</screen>

        <para>Getting the value of a variable works the same way.</para>

        <para>Paths are specified as a colon-separated list. An example of
        this is:</para>

        <screen>% echo $PATH
/bin:/sbin:/usr/bin:/usr/sbin</screen>

        <para>For these types of shells, a <quote>permanent</quote> setting
        for a given variable should usually be done in the
        <filename>.profile</filename> file in your home directory or in your
        shell&#39;s <quote>rc</quote> file. Different shells have different
        names for this file. Examples are <filename>.bashrc</filename> for
        BASH and <filename>.zshrc</filename> for Zsh. Please refer to your
        shell&#39;s documentation for more information. In any case, the file
        will be in your home directory.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="envvar.dos.section">
        <title>DOS Shell</title>

        <para>The typical syntax for setting an environment variable from the
        command line (in a DOS shell window) under Win32 is:</para>

        <screen>C:\&#62; set &#60;VARIABLE_NAME&#62;=&#60;value&#62;</screen>

        <para>Here, <literal>&#60;VARIABLE_NAME&#62;</literal> is the name of
        the environment variable to be set, and <literal>&#60;value&#62;</literal>
        is the value being assigned to that variable. If the named variable
        did not exist before, it will pop into existence. Otherwise, you
        overwrite the old setting with the new one.</para>

        <para>To print the value of an environment variable, use the following
        command:</para>

        <screen>C:\&#62; set &#60;VARIABLE_NAME&#62;</screen>

        <para>Referring to a variable, however, is done using the following
        syntax:</para>

        <screen>C:\&#62; cd %VARIABLE_NAME%\bin</screen>

        <para>Paths are specified as a semicolon-separated list. An example of
        this is:</para>

        <screen>C:\&#62; set PATH
C:\WINDOWS;C:\bin;C:\</screen>

        <para>For some versions of Windows, a <quote>permanent</quote> setting
        for a given variable should usually be done in <filename>C:\AUTOEXEC.BAT</filename>.
        In newer versions (Windows ME in particular) and in the Windows NT
        line of operating systems, the setting is done using the Control
        Panel. Please refer to the next section for more information on that
        method.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Win 32 GUI</title>

        <para>Before reading this section, please be sure to have read <xref
        linkend="envvar.dos.section" />. This is necessary because the Win32
        GUI for setting environment variables is simply a front-end to that
        older method and thus uses the same conventions and syntax. The
        versions of Windows to which this subsection applies are indicated
        individually since each is a little different. For more detailed
        information, please refer to the Windows online help system and search
        for <quote>environment variables</quote>.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Windows 2000</title>

          <para>In the Control Panel, open the <guiicon>System</guiicon> icon.
          Under the <guilabel>Advanced</guilabel> tab, there is a button
          labeled <guibutton>Environment Variables</guibutton> (shown in <xref
          linkend="figure.win2k.sysprops" />). Clicking this button opens the
          dialog box shown in <xref linkend="figure.win2k.envvars" />. Here,
          you can set variables for yourself and, if you have the access
          privileges, for all users.</para>

          <figure id="figure.win2k.sysprops">
            <title>Windows 2000 System Properties Dialog</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center"
                fileref="figures/Window.SystemProperties.png" format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <figure id="figure.win2k.envvars">
            <title>Windows 2000 Environment Variable Editor Dialog</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center"
                fileref="figures/Window.EnvironmentVariables.png" format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>To set up VR Juggler, the environment variable <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar>
          needs to be set, probably for all users, though it depends very much
          on local system requirements. For this example, let us say that the
          Win32 version of VR Juggler is installed in the
          <filename>D:\</filename> directory. As such, we will set
          <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> as shown in <xref
          linkend="figure.win2k.envvar.set" />. Note that we use a forward
          slash (/) instead of a backslash (\) for the directory separator.
          This is not required, though it is helpful in reducing confusion
          with respect to other examples.</para>

          <figure id="figure.win2k.envvar.set">
            <title>Setting <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> on Windows 2000</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center"
                fileref="figures/Window.EnvironmentVariables.VJ_BASE_DIR.png"
                format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Windows NT 4.0</title>

          <para>In the Control Panel, open the <guiicon>System</guiicon> icon.
          The window that is opened has a tab labeled <guilabel>Environment
          Variables</guilabel>. Here, you can set variables for yourself and,
          if you have the access privileges, for all users. The GUI is similar
          to that shown above for Windows 2000.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Syntax Used in this Document</title>

        <para>To avoid tying this documentation to a single style of
        environment variable creation, assignment and reference, the following
        syntax will be used exclusively from this point onward. Please read
        this carefully before proceeding.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Naming Environment Variables</title>

          <para>When naming an environment variable in the plain text of this
          document, the variable will be referred to by its name only. For
          example, to talk about the environment variable containing your
          path, we will talk about it as <envar>PATH</envar>.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Creating/Setting Environment Variables</title>

          <para>The syntax to set an environment variable is:</para>

          <screen>% &#60;VARIABLE_NAME&#62; = &#60;value&#62;</screen>

          <para>Setting an environment variable also creates it if it is not
          already present in the current shell&#39;s environment.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Printing an the Value of an Environment Variable</title>

          <para>Printing an environment variable&#39;s value to standard
          output (stdout) is done as follows:</para>

          <screen>% echo $VARIABLE_NAME
value</screen>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Referring to the Value of an Environment Variable</title>

          <para>To get the value of an environment variable when it needs to
          be expanded, the following syntax will be used:</para>

          <screen>% cd $VARIABLE_NAME/bin</screen>

          <para>Here, the reference to the value is <envar>$VARIABLE_NAME</envar>.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Required Environment Variables</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>VJ_BASE_DIR</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The environment variable <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> tells a
            VR Juggler application where to find important data files. It is
            required to compile and run any Juggler application. It should be
            set to the base directory of the installed VR Juggler library. For
            example, if you downloaded a UNIX version of VR Juggler 2.0 and
            extracted it to the directory <filename>/home/software/</filename>,
            you would set <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> with this command:</para>

            <screen>% VJ_BASE_DIR = /home/software/vrjuggler-2.0</screen>

            <para>The last component of the path depends on the particular
            version of Juggler you have downloaded.</para>

            <para>If you downloaded and built VR Juggler from the source code,
            the compilation creates a directory called <filename>instlinks</filename>
            which can be used as a VR Juggler base:</para>

            <screen>% VJ_BASE_DIR = $HOME/juggler/my_build_dir/instlinks</screen>

            <para>In any case, on a Win32 platform, you should use /&#39;s as
            the path separator for <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> rather than
            \&#39;s. The compiler tools can handle either, and the utilities
            in <filename>juggler-tools</filename> will behave much better if
            UNIX-style paths are used. It is safe to use the drive letter at
            the start of the path (e.g., <filename>C:/software/vrjuggler-2.0</filename>).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>PATH</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>To compile any of the sample applications, the
            <envar>$VJ_BASE_DIR/bin</envar> directory must be added to your
            <envar>PATH</envar> as follows:</para>

            <screen>% PATH = $PATH:$VJ_BASE_DIR/bin</screen>

            <para>Depending on your shell, you may need to run the
            <command>rehash</command> command after executing the above.</para>

            <para>Windows users must also include the <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/lib</filename>
            directory in their <envar>PATH</envar> setting. This is so that
            the VR Juggler DLLs will be found when an application is executed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>JDK_HOME</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <envar>JDK_HOME</envar> environment variable is required
            by the script that starts VRJConfig, the VR Juggler configuration
            program. If Java is installed on your system, <envar>JDK_HOME</envar>
            may already be set. If not, it needs to be set to the base of the
            Java installation.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>LD_LIBRARY_PATH (UNIX/Linux only)</term>

          <term>DYLD_LIBRARY_PATH (Darwin/Mac OS X only)</term>

          <term>LD_LIBRARYN32_PATH (IRIX only)</term>

          <term>LD_LIBRARY64_PATH (IRIX only)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>UNIX/Linux systems use these environment variables to find
            dynamically loaded libraries, such as <filename>libJuggler.so</filename>.
            Unless you are building everything with static libraries, you will
            need to set these to include the VR Juggler library directory
            (under <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar>). IRIX supports several
            Application Binary Interfaces (ABIs). VR Juggler supports only the
            N32 and 64 formats, and there are different library path variables
            for each. The N32 ABI uses the <envar>LD_LIBRARYN32_PATH</envar>
            variable, and the 64 ABI uses <envar>LD_LIBRARY64_PATH</envar>. An
            example of setting the library path is as follows:</para>

            <screen>% LD_LIBRARY_PATH = $VJ_BASE_DIR/lib</screen>

            <note>
              <para>On some SGI systems running IRIX, users of the MIPSpro
              Compilers (version 7.3) will need to add another directory as
              follows:</para>

              <screen>% LD_LIBRARY_PATH = $LD_LIBRARY_PATH:/usr/lib32/cmplrs:$VJ_BASE_DIR</screen>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Optional Related Environment Variables</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>VPR_DEBUG_NFY_LEVEL</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This variable can be used to control the amount of
            diagnostic information a VR Juggler application outputs. Its value
            is a number between 0 (only very important messages are printed)
            and 7 (vast amounts of data) inclusive. Non-hackers are advised to
            use levels 0 through 3, as higher debug levels become increasingly
            cryptic and <emphasis>can severely impact application performance</emphasis>.
            The default is level 1—only errors and critical information are
            output. An example of setting a value for this variable is:</para>

            <screen>% VPR_DEBUG_NFY_LEVEL = 3</screen>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This variable can be used to control which components of VR
            Juggler are allowed to output diagnostic data. If for some reason
            you set <envar>VPR_DEBUG_NFY_LEVEL</envar> to 5 or higher, this
            variable can be used to filter the output. The value of
            <envar>VPR_DEBUG_CATEGORIES</envar> is a space-separated list of
            Juggler debug component names (defined in <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/include/vrj/Util/Debug.h</filename>,
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/include/vpr/Util/Debug.h</filename>,
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/include/tweek/Util/Debug.h</filename>,
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/include/jccl/Util/Debug.h</filename>, and
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/include/gadget/Util/Debug.h</filename>).
            The default value is <quote>DBG_ALL</quote>, which performs no
            filtering whatsoever. Examples of setting it are as follows:</para>

            <screen>% VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES = DBG_ERROR
% VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES = &#34;DBG_KERNEL DBG_INPUT_MGR DBG_DRAW_MGR&#34;
% VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES = &#34;DBG_CONFIG DBG_RECONFIGURATION&#34;</screen>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>VPR_DEBUG_DISALLOW_CATEGORIES</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This variable is basically the opposite of <envar>VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES</envar>.
            Instead of specifying which debugging categories you want to see,
            you specify which ones you <emphasis>do not</emphasis> want to
            see. Its default value is empty which means that no debugging
            categories are excluded. Examples of setting it are as follows:</para>

            <screen>% VPR_DEBUG_DISALLOW_CATEGORIES = DBG_ERROR
% VPR_DEBUG_DISALLOW_CATEGORIES = &#34;DBG_KERNEL DBG_INPUT_MGR DBG_DRAW_MGR&#34;
% VPR_DEBUG_DISALLOW_CATEGORIES = &#34;DBG_CONFIG DBG_RECONFIGURATION&#34;</screen>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>VR Juggler Sample Applications</title>

    <para>VR Juggler comes with several sample applications in its
    <filename>samples</filename> directory tree. Many of them are very simple
    and are designed to demonstrate a specific feature of VR Juggler or a
    technique to use when writing your own applications. This chapter lists
    the current sample applications as of this writing and gives a quick
    description of what you as a potential developer might find interesting in
    the code. Those users who just want to run applications can safely skip
    this chapter.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Tutorial Applications</title>

      <para>Some sample applications designed for getting started with VR
      Juggler are found in <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples/OGL/simple</filename>.
      All of these applications were designed to be used as part of courses
      teaching people how to write VR Juggler applications using OpenGL. They
      contain clear comments explaining what the code is doing, and they are
      intended to be as simple as possible. These tutorials are as follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>simpleInput: An application that demonstrates how to get input
          from devices. No graphics are rendered with this application. It is
          intended to be a starting point for getting an understanding of how
          user input is queried.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SimpleApp: A very simple OpenGL application that draws a small
          cube in space and draws the coordinate axes for the cube.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>contextApp: An application demonstrating how to use OpenGL
          display lists in VR Juggler applications. This extends SimpleApp by
          using a display list to draw a cube and by moving the cube with the
          wand.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ConfigApp: A relatively simple application that demonstrates
          how user-level code can take advantage of the VR Juggler
          configuration system, JCCL.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>MPApp: A more complex OpenGL application that demonstrates how
          to do multi-processing in VR Juggler applications. As it exists in
          its distributed form, no multi-processing is done. A more detailed
          lesson is available that explains how to extend the application to
          employ multi-processing techniques.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For a step-by-step lesson how to use these applications to learn
      VR Juggler application programming, please refer to the
      <emphasis>Programmer&#39;s Guide</emphasis>. It contains sections
      explaining each of the above applications in great detail. Each lesson
      ends with an exercise where the reader extends the application to
      include some new functionality.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Advanced OpenGL Performer Applications</title>

      <para>Examples of OpenGL Performer applications can be found in
      <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples/Pf/advanced</filename>.
      These are for more advanced developers who are familiar with Performer
      and some of the more complicated aspects of VR Juggler. There are two
      main programs to be found there:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>pfNav: A starting point for basic VR Juggler Performer
          applications that need to load a model and navigate through it.
          Users implement their application by inheriting from a provided
          class, <classname>simplePfNav</classname>. This may be a good place
          for intermediate-level users of OpenGL Performer to start because
          <classname>simplePfNav</classname> hides many of the complicated
          details (which actually makes that class far from simple).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>pfConfigNav: A more advanced example of a VR Juggler Performer
          application that can be given its model through a VR Juggler
          configuration element.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="app.compile.chapter">
    <title>Compiling a VR Juggler Sample Program</title>

    <para>Now that you have VR Juggler installed and you have your environment
    all configured, it is time for the fun to begin. No, seriously. You are
    now ready to compile and run VR Juggler applications, and that is the
    whole point, right? This chapter explains how to compile the applications
    provided in the directory <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples/OGL/simple</filename>.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Required Reading</title>

      <para>Before reading any further, make sure you have already read the
      instructions on how to install VR Juggler (in <xref
      linkend="install.vrj.chapter" />) and on how to configure your
      environment (in <xref linkend="envvar.chapter" />). That information
      will not be repeated, and it is assumed that you already know what we
      mean by <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar>. You should also have a basic
      understanding of how <command>make</command>(1) works, but in these
      examples, nothing more will be necessary than typing <literal>make</literal>
      on the command line. Refer to the <command>make</command>(1) manual page
      for more information about it.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Compiling an Application</title>

      <para>There are two ways to compile VR Juggler applications: from the
      command line or with Microsoft Visual Studio. Compiling an application
      on the command line requires the use of GNU make (often installed as
      <command>gmake</command>) so that it will work on all supported
      platforms including Win32. Using Microsoft Visual Studio will only work
      on Win32.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Compiling from the Command Line</title>

        <para>All the sample programs in <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples</filename>
        use the same basic steps to compile unless otherwise noted. Always
        refer to the top of the sample application&#39;s <filename>Makefile</filename>
        for information that may be specific to building that application. In
        general, though, all applications&#39; makefiles require the GNU
        version of the <command>make</command>(1) utility, sometimes installed
        as <command>gmake</command>.</para>

        <para>The example used here will be the MPApp tutorial application
        found in <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples/OGL/simple/MPApp</filename>.
        It is an OpenGL-based application that will compile and run on all
        platforms supported by VR Juggler. Begin by changing into the
        directory <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples/OGL/simple/MPApp</filename>
        in a command shell.</para>

        <para>To compile MPApp, simply enter the following:</para>

        <screen>% gmake</screen>

        <para>The compile process will then begin. As noted above, the use of
        GNU make is required to use the distributed makefiles. With Cygwin,
        GNU make is simply <command>make</command>. If you have your system
        set up properly, it will complete with an executable
        <filename>MPApp</filename> file (or <filename>MPApp.exe</filename> on
        Win32) in the directory. Now that you have a program compiled, it is
        time to learn how to run it. (Readers who are not using Visual Studio
        can skip ahead to <xref linkend="running.app.chapter" />.)</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Compiling Using Microsoft Visual Studio</title>

        <note>
          <para>Remember that the Netscape Portable Runtime (NSPR) is
          <emphasis>required</emphasis> to use VR Juggler on Windows. Its DLL
          directory must be in your path (via the <envar>PATH</envar>
          environment variable) for proper application execution. The NSPR can
          be downloaded from the <ulink
          url="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/nspr">NSPR home page</ulink>.</para>
        </note>

        <para>All OpenGL sample applications are shipped with pre-configured
        Microsoft Visual C++ projects. This is done to help new users get
        started with compiling VR Juggler applications and to give experienced
        Visual Studio users a starting place for their application
        development. To use the workspace for the MPApp application, begin by
        opening the folder containing the source code and double-clicking on
        <filename>MPApp.vcproj</filename>.</para>

        <tip>
          <para>We strongly recommend that users set an environment variable
          called <envar>NSPR_ROOT</envar> to point to the root directory of
          their NSPR installation. This environment variable will be
          referenced below to simplify our examples and to reduce the amount
          of typing required.</para>
        </tip>

        <figure>
          <title>Selecting the Visual C++ Project File</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/MPApp.dir.png"
              format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Visual Studio will open, and the MPApp project will be loaded.
        The unexpanded class view will appear as shown in <xref
        linkend="visual.studio.start.figure" /> when Visual Studio first
        loads.</para>

        <figure id="visual.studio.start.figure">
          <title>MPApp Project</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/MPApp.visual.c++.png"
              format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Before proceeding, the program arguments must be set. In Visual
        Studio 7, this can be performed several ways. For example,
        right-clicking on the project name in the Solution Explorer brings up
        the menu shown in <xref linkend="visual.studio.project-menu.figure" />.
        We are interested in changing the project&#39;s properties, so we
        select the <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem> item from the popup
        menu.</para>

        <figure id="visual.studio.project-menu.figure">
          <title>Project Menu</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
              fileref="figures/MPApp.visual.c++.properties.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Selecting this item opens the <quote>Project Pages</quote>
        dialog, shown in <xref
        linkend="visual.studio.project-settings.dialog.figure" />. In this
        window, choose the <guilabel>Debugging</guilabel> item. There will be
        an empty text entry field under the heading <guilabel>Command
        Arguments</guilabel>. Here, enter the full paths to the VR Juggler
        configuration files that will be used to run the torus application.
        The <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> environment variable cannot be used
        here, unfortunately, so the <emphasis>full path</emphasis> to
        <emphasis>every</emphasis> file must be used. The following shows the
        beginning of the program arguments listing <filename>sim.base.config</filename>
        and <filename>sim.wand.mixin.config</filename>:</para>

        <figure id="visual.studio.project-settings.dialog.figure">
          <title>Project Settings Dialog</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
              fileref="figures/MPApp.visual.c++.args.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Note that in this example, the / directory separator is used
        instead of \ for the program arguments. This is not strictly required
        in this case, but doing it this way maintains consistency with other
        examples.</para>

        <para>Also under the MPApp project settings, the path to the NSPR
        headers and libraries may need to be filled in. All the Visual C++
        project files shipped with VR Juggler refer to the NSPR installation
        via the <envar>NSPR_ROOT</envar> environment variable. If this is not
        set or cannot be used, the paths must be filled in manually.</para>

        <para>Once the program arguments are set up, compile the application.
        Under the <guimenu>Build</guimenu> menu, choose the
        <guimenuitem>Build MPApp</guimenuitem> item as shown in <xref
        linkend="visual.studio.build-menu.figure" />.</para>

        <figure id="visual.studio.build-menu.figure">
          <title>Build <filename>MPApp.exe</filename></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
              fileref="figures/MPApp.visual.c++.build.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Visual C++ will compile the application, and if you have
        everything configured properly on your computer, the compiling will
        complete successfully. Once it is done, execute the MPApp program by
        choosing the <guimenuitem>Start</guimenuitem> item from the
        <guimenu>Debug</guimenu> menu, shown below in <xref
        linkend="visual.studio.debug-menu.exectue.figure" />. For the
        remainder of this book, we will explain how to run applications from
        the command line rather than from the Visual Studio GUI. Readers can
        follow whichever method they prefer.</para>

        <figure id="visual.studio.debug-menu.exectue.figure">
          <title>Execute <filename>MPApp.exe</filename></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
              fileref="figures/MPApp.visual.c++.run.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="running.app.chapter">
    <title>Running a VR Juggler Sample Program</title>

    <para>It is important to note that the same VR Juggler application can be
    run in simulator mode or in a full-scale VR system with no modifications.
    What does change is the configuration files used when starting the
    program. In <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/configFiles</filename>,
    you can find many basic configuration files including those for running in
    simulator using a mouse and keyboard to simulate VR input devices and some
    example files based on those used for the old VRAC C2 system<footnote><para>The
    VRAC C2 has been replaced, and the files in <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/configFiles</filename>
    are maintained primarily as an example of how to configure a multi-wall
    projection system. They do not necessarily work, but they can be used as a
    starting point.</para></footnote>. In the directory, you will see some
    files with names containing <quote>mixin</quote>. These are special files
    that provide a specific capability not necessarily needed by all
    applications. They can be mixed in (hence the name) with other
    configuration files as needed. The configuration files found in the
    <filename>configFiles</filename> directory will be referenced in the
    examples provided, so be sure you know where they are.</para>

    <section>
      <title><anchor id="reading" />Required Reading</title>

      <para>Before reading any further, make sure you have already read the
      instructions on how to install VR Juggler (see <xref
      linkend="install.vrj.chapter" />) and on how to configure your
      environment (see <xref linkend="envvar.chapter" />). That information
      will not be repeated, and it is assumed that you already know what we
      mean by <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> and <envar>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</envar>,
      to name two environment variables. At this point, it is also assumed
      that you already have compiled an application (MPApp in the case of the
      examples provided), so you should be sure to have read about how to
      compile a sample VR Juggler application (in <xref
      linkend="app.compile.chapter" />) before proceeding.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title><anchor id="simulator" />Running an Application in Simulator Mode</title>

      <para>Running in <quote>simulator mode</quote> means that your input is
      simulated and your display windows may have limited functionality. (By
      <quote>simulated input</quote>, we mean that input is provided through
      windows that take keyboard and mouse input and translate that into
      transformations in the virtual world.) Simulator viewports are limited
      primarily in that they cannot display stereo graphics. It is important
      to note that a simulator viewport is a special kind of VR Juggler
      viewport within a display window. Instead of basing its viewpoint on the
      head position of one of the users, the viewpoint is controlled by a
      separate camera that is just another positional device. Within a
      simulator viewport, VR Juggler draws certain objects to help visualize
      the environment. For example, the heads of users are represented as blue
      ellipsoids with gray eyes, and a wand (if present) is drawn as a green
      pointing device. Besides these common simulator objects, display
      surfaces can be drawn. These represent projection screens or HMD viewing
      projections and are drawn as translucent rectangles.</para>

      <para>As mentioned, several simulator configuration files are provided
      with a VR Juggler distribution. These files provide a complete
      simulation of an immersive environment. Please note that this
      documentation reflects the state of the configuration files at the time
      the documentation was written. For more information about the
      configuration files and how to view or modify the configuration, refer
      to the <emphasis>VRJConfig Guide</emphasis>. (Using VRJConfig is the
      best way to find out how a specific configuration file is set up.) The
      configuration files of interest for simulator mode are as follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><filename>sim.base.config</filename> - The basic configuration
          file needed by all applications when run in simulator mode. It
          defines commonly used VR Juggler concepts that are beyond the scope
          of this particular book. It also defines simulated head movement
          using the keyboard. For now, it is sufficient to know that it is
          required to run the sample applications in simulator mode.</para>

          <para>This file also contains the basic simulator display
          configuration file needed by all applications when run in simulator
          mode. It defines the display windows where the rendering magic
          occurs. Two simulator display windows are configured by this file: a
          small one that is active by default and a larger one that is
          inactive initially.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>sim.analog.wandmixin.config</filename> - A
          <quote>mix-in</quote> configuration file that defines simulated
          analog input using the keyboard. This is only required for
          applications where analog input is used and needs to be simulated
          when in simulator mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>sim.analog.mixin.config</filename> - This version of
          the analog simulator opens its own window. See the previous file (<filename>sim.analog.wandmixin.config</filename>)
          for other details.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>sim.c6displays.mixin.config</filename> - A
          <quote>mix-in</quote> configuration file that defines the surface
          displays of VRAC&#39;s C6. This is not required for any application
          but can be used to test opening multiple display windows (each
          containing either a surface or a simulator viewport) before running
          in a multi-screen VR system.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>sim.digital.glove.mixin.config</filename> - A
          <quote>mix-in</quote> configuration file that defines simulated
          digital glove input using the keyboard. This is only required for
          applications where digital glove input is used and needs to be
          simulated when in simulator mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>sim.glove.mixin.config</filename> - A
          <quote>mix-in</quote> configuration file that defines simulated
          gesture-based glove input using the keyboard. This is only required
          for applications where gesture-based glove input is used and needs
          to be simulated when in simulator mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>sim.wand.mixin.config</filename> - A <quote>mix-in</quote>
          configuration file that defines simulated wand input using the
          mouse. This is only required for applications where wand input is
          used and needs to be simulated when in simulator mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>standalone.config</filename> - A configuration file
          that stands on its own and combines the functionality of
          <filename>sim.base.config</filename> and <filename>sim.wand.mixin.config</filename>.
          Note that it uses a single display window for all input.</para>

          <note>
            <para>At the time of this writing, this configuration file only
            works with OpenGL, OpenSG, and Open Scene Graph applications on
            UNIX and Win32. It will not work with OpenGL Performer.</para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For the MPApp application, we need the base configuration file and
      the wand mix-in configuration file.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Starting the Application</title>

        <para>Now it is time to run the application—finally! Make sure that
        all your environment variables are set properly before trying to start
        the application. Once you are ready, specify the name of the
        application and all the configuration files it needs. An example of
        this is:</para>

        <screen>% MPApp sim.base.config sim.wand.mixin.config</screen>

        <para>You will notice that no paths are specified for finding the
        three configuration files. This is intentional to shorten the command
        line given in the example. In general, you always have to give the
        full path to the files<footnote><para>This is being remedied for VR
        Juggler 2.0 and beyond.</para></footnote>. Beginning users will
        typically want to reference the example configuration files in
        <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/configFiles</filename>. As
        you get more comfortable with VR Juggler and its configuration system,
        you may want to make your own modified files and put them in the
        directory <filename>$HOME/.vjconfig</filename>. To simplify running
        applications, you may want to make a shell script (or batch file as
        appropriate) that does all the work of passing configuration files and
        common command-line arguments. For now, though, use the path
        <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/configFiles</filename> for
        each of the configuration files you pass on the command line.</para>

        <para>As the application starts, you will see a plethora of output
        (more or less depending on how you have <envar>$VPR_DEBUG_NFY_LEVEL</envar>,
        <envar>$VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES</envar>, and <envar>$VPR_DEBUG_DISALLOW_CATEGORIES</envar>
        set), and then one moderately sized simulator display window will open
        on the left side of your screen while three blank keyboard input
        windows open on the right side of your screen. The display window will
        be titled <quote>SimWindow1</quote>, and the keyboard input windows
        will be titled <quote>Head Keyboard</quote>, <quote>Sim View Cameras
        Control</quote> and <quote>Wand Keyboard</quote> (in order from the
        top of the display to the bottom). Do not worry that the keyboard
        windows are black—that is normal. The display window will have an
        animated blue mesh, a cyan ellipsoid, and a green pointer. The mesh is
        what you have come to see; the ellipsoid is the user&#39;s head; and
        the pointer is the user&#39;s hand. In <xref
        linkend="MPApp.running.figure" />, we show what this looks on a RedHat
        Linux 7.2 desktop for comparison with what you are seeing. Note that
        the head and wand are only rendered in the simulator windows. They are
        present because head and wand input are being simulated, and it is
        typically quite helpful to see the results of that simulated input. To
        exit the application, press <keysym>ESC</keysym> in the window titled
        <quote>Head Window</quote>.</para>

        <figure id="MPApp.running.figure">
          <title>MPApp running on a Linux desktop with multiple input windows</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
              fileref="figures/MPApp.thumbnail.multi.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>With VR Juggler 1.1/2.0, it is possible to use a single window
        for graphics and for input. To use such a configuration, execute MPApp
        as follows:</para>

        <screen>% MPApp standalone.config</screen>

        <para>This time, only a single window opens, as shown in <xref
        linkend="MPApp.running.single.figure" />. It shows the same graphics
        as before, but now it is configured to take keyboard and mouse input.
        To exit, press <keysym>ESC</keysym> in the graphics window.</para>

        <figure id="MPApp.running.single.figure">
          <title>MPApp running on a Linux desktop with one window</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
              fileref="figures/MPApp.thumbnail.single.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Running an Application on Mac OS X with the X Window System</title>

        <para>Running a VR Juggler application on Mac OS X is slightly
        different if VR Juggler was compiled against <ulink
        url="http://www.apple.com/macosx/x11/">X11 for OS X</ulink>. Before
        starting the VR Juggler application, X11 must be running. This can be
        accomplished by double-clicking on the X11 icon in the Applications
        folder. By default, X11 will open a standard xterm when it starts. In
        this xterm, the <envar>$DISPLAY</envar> environment variable will be
        set correctly, and it is recommended that VR Juggler applications be
        launched from this xterm. From this xterm, set the necessary
        environment variables as described earlier in <xref
        linkend="envvar.chapter" />. Once this is done, the application can be
        executed from the command line just as described in the previous
        section.</para>

        <para>MPApp is shown executing on a Mac OS X desktop in <xref
        linkend="MPApp.OSX.running.single.figure" />. Note that in the dock,
        the X11 icon is activated and that the application menu is for an X11
        application. This truly is an X11 application running on OS X.</para>

        <figure id="MPApp.OSX.running.single.figure">
          <title>MPApp running on Mac OS X using X11 with one window</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
              fileref="figures/MPApp-OSX.thumbnail.single.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Basic Desktop Configuration Controls</title>

        <para>So now you are probably wondering what you can do with this
        fancy application. Both of the preceding configurations use the same
        keyboard/mouse mappings; they vary only in which windows accept the
        keyboard and mouse input. Using the multi-window configuration, head
        movement is done with the keyboard in <quote>Head Keyboard</quote>;
        camera movement is done with the keyboard in <quote>Sim View Cameras
        Control</quote>; and wand movement is done with the keyboard and mouse
        in <quote>Wand Keyboard</quote>. Using the single-window
        configuration, all input is done with the keyboard and mouse in
        <quote>Sim Window</quote>. Note, however, that for the single-window
        configuration, the camera is attached to the user&#39;s head for an
        over-the-shoulder view, and hence, it does not move separately from
        the head. For information on how to verify these settings and to view
        the current configuration, refer to the <emphasis>VRJConfig Guide</emphasis>.
        The following list of tables provides all the keyboard and mouse
        controls for the simulator when using these particular configuration
        files. Note that it is possible to reconfigure the simulator to suit
        your preferences. This is provided mainly for those who just want
        something that works now.</para>

        <table>
          <title>Moving the simulated head</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Transformation</entry>

                <entry>Key Press</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Move head backward</entry>

                <entry align="left">2 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Move head left</entry>

                <entry align="left">4 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Move head right</entry>

                <entry align="left">6 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Move head forward</entry>

                <entry align="left">8 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Move head down</entry>

                <entry align="left">7 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Move head up</entry>

                <entry align="left">9 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Turn head up</entry>

                <entry align="left">CTRL+2 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Turn head left</entry>

                <entry align="left">CTRL+4 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Turn head right</entry>

                <entry align="left">CTRL+6 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Turn head down</entry>

                <entry align="left">CTRL+8 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Rotate head clockwise</entry>

                <entry align="left">1 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Rotate head counter-clockwise</entry>

                <entry align="left">3 on keypad</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
          <title>Moving the simulated wand</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Transformation</entry>

                <entry>Mouse Input/Key Press</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Move wand backward</entry>

                <entry>ALT+move mouse backward</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move wand forward</entry>

                <entry>ALT+move mouse forward</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move wand left</entry>

                <entry>CTRL+move mouse left</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move wand right</entry>

                <entry>CTRL+move mouse right</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move wand up</entry>

                <entry>CTRL+move mouse forward</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move wand down</entry>

                <entry>CTRL+move mouse backward</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Rotate wand left</entry>

                <entry>SHIFT+move mouse left</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Rotate wand right</entry>

                <entry>SHIFT+move mouse right</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Rotate wand up</entry>

                <entry>SHIFT+move mouse backward</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Rotate wand down</entry>

                <entry>SHIFT+move mouse forward</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Rotate wand clockwise</entry>

                <entry>Right arrow</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Rotate wand counter-clockwise</entry>

                <entry>Left arrow</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Wand button #1</entry>

                <entry>Left mouse button</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Wand button #2</entry>

                <entry>Middle mouse button</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Wand button #3</entry>

                <entry>Right mouse button</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Wand button #4</entry>

                <entry>4</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Wand button #5</entry>

                <entry>5</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Wand button #6</entry>

                <entry>6</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
          <title>Moving the camera (multi-window configuration only)</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Transformation</entry>

                <entry>Key Press</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Move camera backward</entry>

                <entry>2 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move camera left</entry>

                <entry>4 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move camera right</entry>

                <entry>6 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move camera forward</entry>

                <entry>8 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move camera down</entry>

                <entry>7 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move camera up</entry>

                <entry>9 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Turn camera up</entry>

                <entry>CTRL+2 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Turn camera left</entry>

                <entry>CTRL+4 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Turn camera right</entry>

                <entry>CTRL+6 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Turn camera down</entry>

                <entry>CTRL+8 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Rotate camera clockwise</entry>

                <entry>1 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Rotate camera counter-clockwise</entry>

                <entry>3 on keypad</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>Before continuing on to running an application in a full-scale
        VR system, we provide two asides: using a simulated glove and using a
        simulated analog device. The examples provided thus far have not
        discussed this because the information was not relevant to the
        particular sample application being used. Knowing how to use these
        simulated devices is important, however, and it is treated separately
        as a reference for your future endeavors in running VR Juggler
        applications.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Using a Simulated Glove</title>

        <para>If you include the <filename>sim.glove.mixin.config</filename>
        file, your application will also have access to a simulated glove,
        with position and gesture inputs. The glove is controlled by a window
        titled <quote>Glove Keyboard</quote>. This window lets you control the
        glove position and selected gesture. Movement control of the glove
        uses the mouse and is the same as that of the wand. The mouse buttons
        are used to select gestures. The mapping of the gesture numbers to
        actual hand positions is controlled by the <quote>training file</quote>
        for the sim glove. The default training file is <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/gesture/simpleSimGestures.dat</filename>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Using a Simulated Analog Device</title>

        <para>If you include the <filename>sim.analog.wandmixin.config</filename>
        file, your application will also have access to a set of four analog
        devices (devices with a value in a range from 0.0 to 1.0). The analog
        devices are also controlled using the <quote>Wand Keyboard</quote>
        window which means that their configuration file requires the wand
        configuration file.</para>

        <note>
          <para>A separate file, <filename>sim.analog.mixin.config</filename>,
          is provided for analog input from a separate simulator window.</para>
        </note>

        <para>The key presses used for controlling the analog devices are
        listed in <xref linkend="sim.analog.keys.table" />.</para>

        <table id="sim.analog.keys.table">
          <title>Analog Device Simulator Keys</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="center">Analog Device Action</entry>

                <entry align="center">Key Press</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">VJAnalog0 increase</entry>

                <entry align="center">Q</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">VJAnalog0 decrease</entry>

                <entry align="center">A</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">VJAnalog1 increase</entry>

                <entry align="center">W</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">VJAnalog1 decrease</entry>

                <entry align="center">S</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">VJAnalog2 increase</entry>

                <entry align="center">E</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">VJAnalog2 decrease</entry>

                <entry align="center">D</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">VJAnalog3 increase</entry>

                <entry align="center">R</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">VJAnalog3 decrease</entry>

                <entry align="center">F</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Running an Application in a VR System</title>

      <para>Running an application full-scale in a VR system is more
      complicated than running in simulator mode. The reason for this is that
      VR systems tend to differ in configuration and in available hardware. VR
      Juggler is flexible enough to handle most any configuration you throw at
      it, but those configurations need to be put together first. Examples of
      configuration files used in VRAC&#39;s C2 system are provided, and they
      are used in this documentation. It should be noted, however, that for
      any particular system, custom configuration files will probably have to
      be written. The idea behind this section is to provide a basic
      understanding of what is needed to get started with running in a VR
      system.</para>

      <para>The example configuration files in the directory
      <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/configFiles</filename>
      modeled after those used for VRAC&#39;s C2 system are as follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><filename>C2.base.config</filename> - The basic configuration
          file needed by all applications when run in the C2. It defines
          commonly used VR Juggler concepts that are beyond the scope of this
          particular book.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>C2.displays.config</filename> - The basic display
          configuration file needed to run with all four walls active and
          rendering stereo graphics. This defines only the four surface
          displays to be opened.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>C2.flock.config</filename> - The Ascension Flock of
          Birds configuration file that defines which bird provides input for
          the head and for the wand.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>C2.ibox_buttons.config</filename> - The IBox
          configuration file that handles the digital wand button inputs.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>C2.mono.displays.config</filename> - The same
          configuration as <filename>C2.displays.config</filename> except that
          the walls are opened to render mono graphics.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Running the application is the same as in simulator mode except
      that the configuration files given on the command line are different.
      For example, to run MPApp in the C2 with stereo graphics, the following
      command would be used:</para>

      <screen>% MPApp C2.base.config C2.displays.config C2.flock.config C2.ibox_buttons.config</screen>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
