<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
   <articleinfo>
      <title>Building and Installing the Juggler Project (Version
      2.1/2.2)</title>

      <authorgroup>
         <author>
            <othername>The Juggler Team</othername>
         </author>
      </authorgroup>

      <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
   </articleinfo>

   <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>You have downloaded the source code for Version 2.1 of the Juggler
      Project. This is the code that will become VR Juggler 2.2, and it is the
      code that is used to create the VR juggler 2.2 pre-releases. Please be
      aware that this code represents a work in progress, and if you acquired
      it directly from Subversion rather than using a pre-packaged source code
      snapshot, the code may have bugs affecting compilation and
      execution.</para>

      <para>This document explains how to build the modules of the Juggler
      Project from the source code. We begin by explaining some issues related
      to specific operating systems. We then explain how to get the source
      code from our Subversion repository. (Those users who downloaded a
      pre-packaged source release can skip ahead to <xref
      linkend="using.configure.pl" />). We conclude with instructions on how
      to build VR Juggler and its individual components.</para>

      <para>Before reading further, we recommend that readers take a look at
      the Wiki page relating to building from source (<ulink
      url="http://www.vrjuggler.org/twiki_public/bin/view/Juggler/BuildingFromSvn">http://www.vrjuggler.org/twiki_public/bin/view/Juggler/BuildingFromSvn</ulink>).
      It is a <emphasis>supplement</emphasis> to this document containing tips
      and reminders for those users building the SVN version of VR Juggler. It
      is not a replacement for this document, nor can it stand on its own as
      build instructions. You are reading the definitive build instructions;
      the Wiki page merely provides informal, extra information.</para>

      <section>
         <title>Important Notes for IRIX Users</title>

         <para>Despite our best efforts, there are some issues related to
         compiling the Juggler Project on IRIX. We introduce them in this
         section and explain how to work around them.</para>

         <section>
            <title>Perl Version</title>

            <para>There are many Perl scripts used as part of getting,
            configuring, and building the Juggler Suite of tools. In
            particular, two scripts required for compiling need Perl 5.005 or
            newer. The version of Perl that ships with IRIX 6.5 is very old
            (circa 1997) and does not work with many Perl scripts we have
            written. SGI provides a much newer version of Perl (5.6.1) with
            their freeware tools (<ulink
            url="http://freeware.sgi.com/">http://freeware.sgi.com/</ulink>).
            It will be necessary to install that version for our scripts to
            work. This version is typically installed as
            <filename>/usr/freeware/bin/perl</filename>.</para>

            <para>Once you have a modern Perl installed, you can run various
            Perl scripts as follows:</para>

            <screen>/usr/freeware/bin/perl &lt;script-name&gt;</screen>

            <para>The above will be required any time a Perl script fails with
            an error similar to the following:</para>

            <screen>Perl 5.005 required--this is only version 5.00404, stopped at ./configure.pl line 35.
BEGIN failed--compilation aborted at ./configure.pl line 35.</screen>

            <para>Furthermore, it is highly recommended that the
            <option>--with-perl</option> argument be passed to
            <command>configure.pl</command>. This argument gives all the
            Autoconf-based configure scripts a hint about where the preferred
            version of Perl lives. If using
            <filename>/usr/freeware/bin/perl</filename> to run
            <command>configure.pl</command>, we recommend that the
            <command>configure.pl</command> command line appear similar to the
            following:</para>

            <screen>/usr/freeware/bin/perl configure.pl --with-perl=/usr/freeware/bin</screen>

            <para>Note that the value given to <option>--with-perl</option> is
            the <emphasis>directory</emphasis> where the
            <command>perl</command> executable can be found. The configure
            scripts will add this directory to the front of the search path
            when trying to find a suitable <command>perl</command> executable.
            Once it is found, all the Perl scripts used for configuration,
            compilation, and installation will use that executable.</para>

            <para>To simplify command execution somewhat, it can help to have
            <filename>/usr/freeware/bin</filename> (or whatever path is
            appropriate) in your path before <filename>/bin</filename> or
            <filename>/usr/bin</filename> or any of the other myriad
            directories where Perl might exist on IRIX. In such a situation,
            none of the above extra steps should be necessary. The correct
            version of Perl will be found simply by virtue of it being early
            in your path.</para>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>MIPSpro Compiler Version</title>

            <para>Reports have been made on the VR Juggler mailing list
            regarding compile failures (including segmentation faults within
            the compiler) occur when using the MIPSpro Compilers Version
            7.3.1.1m. We have found upgrading to Version 7.3.1.3m (or newer)
            fixes the problems.</para>

            <para>A new feature of VR Juggler 1.1 and newer is support for GCC
            on IRIX. Users who do not have MIPSpro or cannot upgrade can
            compile and run VR Juggler (without OpenGL Performer support)
            using the version of GCC distributed by SGI. It can be downloaded
            from <ulink
            url="http://freeware.sgi.com/index-by-alpha.html">http://freeware.sgi.com/index-by-alpha.html</ulink>
            for free. When configuring the source with
            <command>configure.pl</command> (described later), use the option
            <option>--with-gcc</option>.</para>
         </section>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Important Note for Windows Users</title>

         <para>VR Juggler 1.1 and newer use a lot of C++ features not
         supported by Visual Studio 6.0. Microsoft <ulink
         url="http://support.microsoft.com/default.aspx?scid=http://support.microsoft.com:80/support/kb/articles/q243/4/51.asp&amp;NoWebContent=1">acknowledges</ulink>
         the issues concerning noncompliance to the C++ Standard with Visual
         Studio 6.0, and it appears that they have no plans to fix these
         problems. Therefore, we require the use of Visual Studio 7.x (.NET
         2002 or 2003) or newer to compile the source code.</para>
      </section>
   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Build Tools</title>

      <para>When building on non-Windows platforms, the GNU Autotools are
      required. This means that, in addition to a C++ compiler (e.g., GCC),
      the following packages must be installed in order to compile VR
      Juggler:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>GNU Make 3.79 or newer</para>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para>GNU Autoconf 2.53 or newer</para>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para>GNU Automake 1.8 or newer</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Additionally, VR Juggler 2.1 and beyond require the <ulink
      url="https://realityforge.vrsource.org/view/FlagPoll/">Flagpoll</ulink>
      software tool. As of this writing, the minimum required version is
      0.8.1. It is recommended that all of these tools be installed in either
      the <filename>/usr</filename> or the <filename>/usr/local</filename>
      directory trees so that search paths do not have to be extended.</para>
   </section>

   <section id="source.code.section">
      <title>Getting the Source Code and the Dependencies</title>

      <para>In this section, we explain how to get the Juggler Project source
      code and the dependencies required to build Juggler. There are two ways
      to get the source code: from a pre-packaged source release archive or
      from the Subversion repository on RealityForge. If you got the code from
      a pre-packaged source archive, that code is a complete
      <quote>snapshot</quote> of the Subversion repository at the time of
      release. It contains all dependencies that would otherwise have been
      acquired using Subversion. It <emphasis>does not</emphasis> contain
      binary dependencies that must be downloaded separately (such as NSPR,
      the Java Developer Kit, a C++ compiler, etc.).</para>

      <para>The current list of <emphasis>required</emphasis> software
      packages is as follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>CppDOM (<ulink
            url="http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/xml-cppdom/">http://www.sf.net/projects/xml-cppdom/</ulink>):
            A lightweight, easy-to-use XML parser written in C++. CppDOM must
            be compiled and installed for use with VR Juggler.</para>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para>Boost (<ulink
            url="http://www.boost.org/">http://www.boost.org/</ulink>): A C++
            library providing many powerful utility classes and libraries.
            Boost must be compiled and installed for use with VR
            Juggler.</para>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para>GMTL (<ulink
            url="http://ggt.sourceforge.net/">http://ggt.sf.net/</ulink>): A
            generic math library that makes use of C++ templates and STL
            paradigms. GMTL must be installed for use with VR Juggler.</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The following lists <emphasis>semi-optional</emphasis>
      packages:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>NSPR (<ulink
            url="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/nspr/">http://www.mozilla.org/projects/nspr/</ulink>):
            The Netscape Portable Runtime, which can be used by VPR for
            threading and sockets (required on Win32 and Solaris).</para>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para>Java Developer Kit (<ulink
            url="http://java.sun.com/">http://java.sun.com/</ulink>): The J2SE
            SDK (or JDK) is used to compile all the Java code used in the
            Juggler Project. Without it, none of the Java code can be built.
            We require version 1.4 or newer. The Java Standard Edition (J2SE)
            can be downloaded from <ulink
            url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/">http://java.sun.com/j2se/</ulink>.</para>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para>omniORB (<ulink
            url="http://www.jdom.org/">http://omniorb.sourceforge.net/</ulink>):
            A C++ implementation of CORBA 2.3, required for the Tweek C++
            API.</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The following are fully optional packages that are primarily of
      interest only to people doing development on the Juggler Suite
      itself:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>JUnit (<ulink
            url="http://www.junit.org/">http://www.junit.org/</ulink>): A unit
            testing framework for Java.</para>
         </listitem>

         <listitem>
            <para>CppUnit (<ulink
            url="http://cppunit.sourceforge.net/">http://cppunit.sourceforge.net/</ulink>):
            A unit testing framework for C++. The Juggler C++ test suties make
            use of extensions to CppUnit. An extended version of the CppUnit
            source that includes these extensions can be acquired from the
            Juggler Subversion repository in the module
            <literal>cppunit</literal>. Refer to <xref
            linkend="section.cvs.access" /> for instructions about accessing
            the Juggler Subversion repository.</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The third-party dependencies must be downloaded from the sites
      listed above and installed manually. You may also have to compile one or
      more of the packages if binary distributions are not available. Which
      packages you download depends on what you already have installed. Note
      carefully which packages are needed based on the software you have
      installed and what versions of tools (such as the JDK) that you
      download.</para>

      <section id="section.cvs.access">
         <title>How to Get the Juggler Suite from Subversion</title>

         <para>You can optionally get the Juggler Project as a source code
         tarball from the website (<ulink
         url="http://www.vrjuggler.org/">http://www.vrjuggler.org/</ulink>) or
         you can execute the following command from a shell to get the code
         from our Subversion repository:</para>

         <screen>svn co https://realityforge.vrsource.org/svn/vrjuggler/juggler/trunk juggler
</screen>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Downloading Third-Party Dependencies</title>

         <para>In addition to source the dependencies acquired through
         Subversion, there are some third-party dependencies that must be
         installed separately. Remember that no Java code in VR Juggler can be
         used without the JDK and a working Java version of CORBA.</para>

         <section>
            <title>Boost</title>

            <para>The minimum required version of Boost, as of this writing,
            is 1.31.0. The Boost source can be downloaded from <ulink
            url="http://www.sf.net/projects/boost/">http://www.sf.net/projects/boost/</ulink>.
            To compile and install Boost, refer to its installation
            documentation (<ulink
            url="http://www.boost.org/more/getting_started.html#Build_Install">http://www.boost.org/more/getting_started.html#Build_Install</ulink>).
            Note that you need the command <command>bjam</command> (referred
            to as <quote>boost-jam</quote> on the Boost download page) to
            build Boost.</para>

            <important>
               <para>Mac OS X users should compile the Boost libraries using
               the <quote>darwin</quote> toolset.</para>
            </important>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>CppDOM</title>

            <para>For XML processing, we use CppDOM 0.6.5 or newer. The source
            and binary distributions for some platforms can be downloaded from
            <ulink
            url="http://www.sf.net/projects/xml-cppdom/">http://www.sf.net/projects/xml-cppdom/</ulink>.
            If a binary version is not available for your operating system you
            must compile and install CppDOM yourself. Note that you need SCons
            (<ulink
            url="http://scons.sourceforge.net/">http://scons.sourceforge.net/</ulink>)
            to build and install CppDOM.</para>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>GMTL</title>

            <para>For high-level mathematical operations, we use GMTL 0.4.12
            or newer. The source distribution can be downloaded from <ulink
            url="http://www.sf.net/projects/ggt/">http://www.sf.net/projects/ggt/</ulink>.
            Note that you need SCons (<ulink
            url="http://scons.sourceforge.net/">http://scons.sourceforge.net/</ulink>)
            to build and install GMTL.</para>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Netscape Portable Runtime (NSPR)</title>

            <para>Our operating system abstraction, VPR, can make use of NSPR
            for operating system primitives. On some platforms (IRIX, FreeBSD,
            Linux, Mac OS X), the use of NSPR is strictly optional. On others
            (Win32, HP-UX, and Solaris), it is required. Based on your local
            system, you should decide whether you need NSPR. Binary versions
            of NSPR can be downloaded from <ulink
            url="ftp://ftp.mozilla.org/pub/mozilla.org/nspr/releases">ftp://ftp.mozilla.org/pub/mozilla.org/nspr/releases</ulink>.
            At this time, we recommend the use of version 4.2 or newer.</para>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Java Developer Kit (also called the J2SE SDK)</title>

            <para>We make use of the Java programming language in addition to
            C++. Java is used exclusively for GUIs such as Tweek and VRJConfig
            (which is a JavaBean that is loaded into Tweek). To compile the
            Java code, a JDK is necessary. We currently require version 1.4 or
            newer. The Java Standard Edition can be downloaded from <ulink
            url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/">http://java.sun.com/j2se/</ulink>.
            More information can be found at <ulink
            url="http://java.sun.com/">http://java.sun.com/</ulink>.</para>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>omniORB</title>

            <para>omniORB is a C++ implementation of CORBA 2.3. It is required
            in order to compile the Tweek C++ API. At this time, the Tweek C++
            API is not required for VR Juggler, but this situation will change
            in the near future. At this time, we primarily use omniORB 4.0.x;
            omniORB 3.0 is not supported. omniORB can be downloaded from
            <ulink
            url="http://omniorb.sourceforge.net/">http://omniorb.sourceforge.net/</ulink>.</para>
         </section>
      </section>
   </section>

   <section id="compile.section">
      <title>Compiling</title>

      <para>In this section, we describe how to compile the Juggler Project.
      We focus on VR Juggler as a whole, but information about some of the
      individual components is provided later.</para>

      <section>
         <title>Important Note Regarding Compiling</title>

         <para>You have downloaded <emphasis>developmental</emphasis> code. It
         may not be stable, and it may not even compile. Compiling VR Juggler
         itself can be a little complicated for anyone who does not have some
         background in using Subversion, Autoconf, C++, and
         <command>make</command> or Visual Studio.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
         <title>Compiling the Juggler Suite of Tools</title>

         <para>This section explains how to get, configure, and compile all of
         the tools that make up VR Juggler. Each tool compiles to its own
         library and can be installed individually. (Refer to the
         <filename>README</filename> file in this directory for more
         information about the specific modules.)</para>

         <para>To build VR Juggler on Windows, you must use the Visual Studio
         solution. After getting the dependencies needed to compile VR Juggler
         (see the next section), refer to the <ulink
         url="README-WINDOWS.html">README-WINDOWS.html</ulink> file located in
         this directory. Do not bother to the rest of this document.</para>

         <section>
            <title>Per-Module Dependencies</title>

            <para>Here, we provide per-module dependency information. Given
            that the dependencies for any single module are met, the modules
            may be reused effectively outside the scope of immersive VR
            application development. Below, we list the
            <emphasis>minimum</emphasis> required version for each dependency,
            and where appropriate, we note which dependencies are
            optional.</para>

            <section>
               <title>VPR</title>

               <para>VPR provides a cross-platform, object-oriented operating
               system abstraction. It is the foundation for all other Juggler
               modules.</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>CppDOM 0.6.5</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>Boost headers and Boost.Filesystem 1.31.0</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>NSPR (Windows, Solaris, and HP-UX only) 4.4</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Tweek C++ API</title>

               <para>Tweek implements a distributed model/view/controller
               system on top of CORBA. The Tweek C++ API provides the C++
               component of that system. Code written on top of the Tweek C++
               API normally acts as the model piece of the distributed
               model/view/controller system.</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>VPR</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>omniORB 4.0</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Tweek Java API</title>

               <para>Tweek implements a distributed model/view/controller
               system on top of CORBA. The Tweek Java API provides the Java
               component of that system. The main part of the Tweek Java API
               is the Tweek JavaBean Loader, a GUI application that loads
               Tweek Beans that normally function as the view and controller
               pieces of the distributed module/view/controller system.</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>J2SE SDK 1.4</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>JDOM (included with Juggler source)</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>Ant (included with Juggler source)</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>JacORB IDL-to-Java compiler (included with Juggler
                     source)</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Tweek Python API</title>

               <para>Tweek implements a distributed model/view/controller
               system on top of CORBA. The Tweek Python API provides the
               Python component of that system. The main part of the Tweek
               Java API is the <emphasis>unfinished</emphasis> TweekQt GUI, an
               application that loads Python modules that normally function as
               the view and controller pieces of the distributed
               module/view/controller system.</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>Python 2.3</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>omniORBpy 2.0</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>JCCL C++ API</title>

               <para>The JCCL C++ API provides an interface for loading
               XML-based configurations. It includes the run-time
               reconfiguration feature of Juggler.</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>VPR</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>JCCL Java API</title>

               <para>The JCCL Java API provides a programming interface for
               editing Juggler configuration files and config definition files
               as well as JavaBeans for editing these files using a graphical
               interface.</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>Tweek Java API</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>TableLayout package (included with Juggler
                     source)</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>JCCL Remote Run-Time Reconfiguration Plug-in
               (C++)</title>

               <para>The C++ JCCL Remote Run-Time Reconfiguration Plug-in is
               an optional extension to the JCCL Config Manager for allowing
               remote manipulation of a Juggler configuration at run time
               based on Tweek.</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>Tweek C++ API</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>JCCL Remote Run-Time Reconfiguration Plug-in
               (Java)</title>

               <para>The Java JCCL Remote Run-Time Reconfiguration Plug-in is
               an optional extension that provides the features needed for a
               Java-based editor to communicate with the C++ Remote Run-Time
               Reconfiguration Plug-in to edit Juggler configurations
               live.</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>Tweek Java API</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Sonix</title>

               <para>Sonix is an abstraction layer for positional sound
               software. Sonix itself cannot play audio, but it includes
               plug-ins based on popular interfaces for playing audio. Each
               plug-in depends on a specific audio software library.</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>VPR</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>GMTL 0.4.12</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>

               <section>
                  <title>Sonix OpenAL Plug-in</title>

                  <itemizedlist>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>Sonix</para>
                     </listitem>

                     <listitem>
                        <para>OpenAL</para>
                     </listitem>

                     <listitem>
                        <para>Free ALUT</para>
                     </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
               </section>

               <section>
                  <title>Sonix Audiere Plug-in</title>

                  <itemizedlist>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>Sonix</para>
                     </listitem>

                     <listitem>
                        <para>Audiere</para>
                     </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
               </section>

               <section>
                  <title>Sonix AudioWorks Plug-in</title>

                  <itemizedlist>
                     <listitem>
                        <para>Sonix</para>
                     </listitem>

                     <listitem>
                        <para>AudioWorks</para>
                     </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
               </section>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Gadgeteer</title>

               <para>Gadgeteer handles all input devices that can be used by
               VR Juggler applications.</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>VPR</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>JCCL</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>GMTL 0.4.12</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>X Window System (non-Windows platforms)</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Gadgeteer Device Driver Plug-ins</title>

               <para>The device driver plug-ins for Gadgeteer are independent
               components that are discovered and used at run time based on
               the application configuration. Drivers with dependencies are
               optional.</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>Gadgeteer</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>VRPN 07.03 for the VRPN driver plug-in</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>TrackD API 4 for the TrackD API driver
                     plug-in</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>Microsoft Speech API for the MS Speech API driver
                     plug-in</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Gadgeteer Cluster Plug-ins</title>

               <para>The cluster plug-ins extend the functionality of the
               clustering infrastructure built into Gadgeteer.</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>Gadgeteer</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>VR Juggler</title>

               <para>The VR Juggler module is the unifying piece that pulls
               all the other Juggler modules together. It provides a virtual
               platform for VR application development. Real-time rendering is
               controlled by Draw Managers. The OpenGL Performer Draw Manager
               is optional.</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>Gadgeteer</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>Sonix</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>OpenGL</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>OpenGL Performer for the
                     <emphasis>optional</emphasis> OpenGL Performer Draw
                     Manager</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>VR Juggler Run-Time Performance Monitoring Plug-in
               (C++)</title>

               <para>The C++ VR Juggler Run-Time Performance Monitoring
               Plug-in provides an optional extension to VR Juggler for remote
               visualization of performance metrics that are captured while
               running a VR Juggler application. Communication is performed
               using the Tweek C++ API on top of CORBA.</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>Tweek C++ API</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>VR Juggler</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>VR Juggler Run-Time Performance Monitoring Plug-in
               (Java)</title>

               <para>The Java VR Juggler Run-Time Performance Monitoring
               Plug-in is an optional extension that provides the features
               needed for Java-based visualization of performance data
               collected while a VR Juggler application is running. This is
               another JavaBean handled by the Tweek JavaBean Loader, and it
               uses CORBA to communicate with the C++ VR Juggler Run-Time
               Performance Monitoring Plug-in.</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>JCCL Java API</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>JFreeChart (included with Juggler source)</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>VRJConfig</title>

               <para>VRJConfig is the graphical editor for Juggler
               configurations. It is a JavaBean loaded by the Tweek JavaBean
               Loader, and it makes use of the editor Beans provided by the
               JCCL Java API.</para>

               <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>JCCL Java API</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>JGraph (included with Juggler source)</para>
                  </listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
            </section>
         </section>

         <section>
            <title>Preparing Flagpoll</title>

            <para>The Flagpoll software has a default search path where it
            looks for <filename>.pc</filename> and <filename>.fpc</filename>
            package metadata files. It searchs
            <filename>/usr/lib/pkgconfig</filename>,
            <filename>/usr/lib/flagpoll</filename>,
            <filename>/usr/lib64/pkgconfig</filename>,
            <filename>/usr/lib64/flagpoll</filename>,
            <filename>/usr/share/pkgconfig</filename>, and
            <filename>/usr/share/flagpoll</filename>. If
            <envar>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</envar> (or
            <envar>DYLD_LIBRARY_PATH</envar> on Mac OS X) is set, Flagpoll
            will search each of the directories in that environment variable
            for subdirectories named <filename>pkgconfig</filename> and
            <filename>flagpoll</filename>. Users can extend this search path
            further by setting the environment variables
            <envar>PKG_CONFIG_PATH</envar> and/or <envar>FLAGPOLL_PATH</envar>
            to list more directories for Flagpoll to search. (All of the
            environment variables mentioned here have as their value a
            colon-separated list of directories.)</para>

            <para>The Juggler build relies upon Flagpoll for getting compiler
            and linker flags for the following packages:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>CppDOM</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para>GMTL</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para>omniORB</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <para>Therefore, it is critical that Flagpoll be able to find the
            package metadata file for each. For CppDOM, the
            <filename>.fpc</filename> file is under the CppDOM
            <filename>lib</filename> (or <filename>lib64</filename>) directory
            in the <filename>flagpoll</filename> subdirectory. For omniORB,
            the <filename>.pc</filename> files (there are several) are under
            the omniORB <filename>lib</filename> (or
            <filename>lib64</filename>) directory in the
            <filename>pkgconfig</filename> subdirectory. Finally, for GMTL,
            the <filename>.pc</filename> file is under the GMTL
            <filename>share</filename> directory in the
            <filename>pkgconfig</filename> subdirectory. If these packages are
            installed in <filename>/usr</filename>, then Flagpoll will be able
            to find the information it needs with no extra work on the part of
            the user.</para>

            <important>
               <para>If Flagpoll is not installed in a place where the
               <command>aclocal</command> tool searches for
               <filename>.m4</filename> files by default, then it is necessary
               to extend <command>aclocal</command>'s search path. This is
               done by setting the environment variable
               <envar>ACLOCAL_FLAGS</envar> to <quote><literal>-I
               .../share/alocal</literal></quote> where
               <quote><literal>...</literal></quote> is the path to the
               directory tree where Flagpoll is installed.</para>
            </important>
         </section>

         <section id="config.vrjuggler.section">
            <title>Configuring the Juggler Build</title>

            <para>We now explain the process by which the Juggler build is
            configured. The Juggler Suite makes use of the well-known, widely
            used GNU tools Autoconf and GNU Make. We provide a wrapper script
            written in Perl called <command>configure.pl</command> that gets
            the process started.</para>

            <para>The Juggler build is highly automated. The trickiest part is
            telling the build where to find the third-party dependencies. This
            part can be simplified, however, by installing the third-party
            dependencies in the default location where the search will be
            performed. In most cases, this is <filename>/usr/local</filename>,
            but in others it is <filename>/usr</filename>. The default search
            location is determined by whether the dependency is considered to
            be a fundamental part of the operating system installation (such
            as OpenGL) or if it is an <quote>add-on</quote> package (such as
            Boost, GMTL, CppDOM, or omniORB).</para>

            <sidebar>
               <para>The distinction between <filename>/usr/local</filename>
               and <filename>/usr</filename> is complicated by the fact that
               most Linux distributions have <emphasis>everything</emphasis>
               installed in <filename>/usr</filename>. While Linux may be
               popular, it should not (yet) be considered a model example of
               how to do things. In traditional UN*X distributions (BSD and
               System V), <filename>/usr</filename> is only used for the
               fundamental operating system pieces;
               <filename>/usr/local</filename> is used for extra bits. The
               Juggler build is based on these assumptions. Furthermore, most
               open source software packages (e.g., Boost, omniORB, Perl,
               Python) default to installing themselves in
               <filename>/usr/local</filename>, which suggests that the
               authors of those tools generally expect their software to be in
               <filename>/usr/local</filename>.</para>
            </sidebar>

            <section id="using.configure.pl">
               <title>Using <command>configure.pl</command></title>

               <para>In the base <filename>juggler</filename> source
               directory, we have a <quote>global</quote> configure script
               written in Perl called <command>configure.pl</command>. To get
               the command-line options for this script, use one of the
               following (the second being much more detailed):</para>

               <screen>./configure.pl --help
./configure.pl --manual</screen>

               <para>To configure your system, you will need to see what
               options all the Autoconf-based configure scripts in VR Juggler
               need. To get this text, enter:</para>

               <screen>./configure.pl --all-help</screen>

               <para><important>
                     <para>In order for this to work, the configure script for
                     each of the Juggler modules must be generated. This can
                     be done manually by running <command>autogen.sh</command>
                     in the top-level <filename>juggler</filename> directory.
                     It use is simple:</para>

                     <screen>./autogen.sh</screen>

                     <para>This <command>autogen.sh</command> script must be
                     run from the directory where it exists. Do not try to run
                     it from a build directory or any other place in the
                     Juggler source tree. The same holds for the individual
                     <command>autogen.sh</command> scripts in the various
                     modules, should you need to run one individually.</para>
                  </important><command>configure.pl</command> can run in a
               unique <quote>build</quote> directory or in the directory where
               it resides. Here is how we (the Juggler Team) have been using
               it:</para>

               <orderedlist>
                  <listitem>
                     <para>Make a directory for compiling. There are many good
                     reasons to do this away from the main source tree (though
                     they will not be listed here).</para>

                     <screen>mkdir build.linux.posix</screen>

                     <para>This example using an ad hoc naming convention
                     based on operating system and threading subsystem. Other
                     examples could be <filename>build.irix.sproc</filename>,
                     <filename>build.solaris.nspr</filename>, etc.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>Enter the new build directory.</para>

                     <screen>cd build.linux.posix</screen>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                     <para>Configure all the modules making up VR Juggler.
                     This is when you must tell the module configure scripts
                     where all the package dependencies are found.</para>

                     <screen>../configure.pl --prefix=$HOME/vrjuggler-2.2 --with-java-orb=JDK</screen>

                     <important>
                        <para>You will probably have to specify the path to
                        your local Boost installation using the option
                        <option>--with-boost</option> unless it is installed
                        in the default location
                        (<filename>/usr/local</filename>). By default, Boost
                        1.31 and newer install the Boost header files in a
                        subdirectory of <filename>include</filename> called
                        <filename>boost-VERSION</filename> (where
                        <filename>VERSION</filename> is the Boost version
                        number with underscores instead of periods). That is,
                        if Boost 1.34 is installed in
                        <filename>/home/user1/pkgs/boost</filename>, the
                        header files will be in
                        <filename>/home/user1/pkgs/boost/include/boost-1_34</filename>.
                        In this case, you must also specify the option
                        <option>--with-boost-includes=/home/user1/pkgs/boost/include/boost-1_34</option>
                        when running <command>configure.pl</command>.</para>
                     </important>
                  </listitem>
               </orderedlist>

               <para>By default, the configuration process will configure VR
               Juggler and all of its dependencies. This includes Sonix, which
               is an interesting special case. Sonix can make use of Audiere,
               OpenAL, or AudioWorks to add sound to VR Juggler applications.
               If none of those packages is found, Sonix will <quote>stub
               out</quote> its sound APIs. This means that Sonix and the VR
               Juggler Sound Manager can still be used in applications, but no
               audio will be heard at run time. See <xref
               linkend="sonix.compile.section" /> for more information about
               how to configure Sonix to use Audiere, OpenAL, or
               AudioWorks.</para>

               <para>For example uses of <command>configure.pl</command>, take
               a look at the Wiki page relating to building from source
               (<ulink
               url="http://www.vrjuggler.org/twiki_public/bin/view/Juggler/BuildingFromSvn">http://www.vrjuggler.org/twiki_public/bin/view/Juggler/BuildingFromSvn</ulink>).
               It is not a replacement for this document, but it shows how
               some members of the Juggler team configure VR Juggler. It also
               has information on more advanced uses of
               <command>configure.pl</command> that are beyond the scope of
               this document.</para>
            </section>

            <section>
               <title>Using Locally Installed Software</title>

               <para>As noted in <xref linkend="source.code.section" />, VR
               Juggler depends on several external software packages. As an
               example, consider the case where the Boost libraries are
               installed in <filename>/home/user1/pkgs/boost</filename> with
               the headers in
               <filename>/home/user1/pkgs/boost/include</filename>. To use
               this installation, run <command>configure.pl</command> as
               follows:</para>

               <screen>../configure.pl --with-boost=/home/user1/pkgs/boost</screen>
            </section>
         </section>

         <section id="compile.vrjuggler.section">
            <title>Compiling VR Juggler</title>

            <para>Once the configuration process is complete, the code can be
            compiled. Remember that we require the use of GNU make 3.78 or
            newer.</para>

            <orderedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Compile the source tree using GNU make.</para>

                  <screen>gmake build</screen>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para>Once this completes, you will have a full build of VR
                  Juggler. For those who are not interested in developing VR
                  Juggler or its component modules, it is recommended that you
                  install the software and use the installed version for
                  application development. Do this as follows:</para>

                  <screen>gmake install</screen>
               </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
         </section>
      </section>

      <section id="compile.individual.section">
         <title>Tips for Compiling Individual Tools in the Juggler
         Suite</title>

         <para>In this section, we provide tips for ensuring that individual
         tools in the Juggler Suite are compiled correctly. For the most part,
         this duplicates information that can be found on the Wiki page
         relating to building from source (<ulink
         url="http://www.vrjuggler.org/twiki_public/bin/view/Juggler/BuildingFromSvn">http://www.vrjuggler.org/twiki_public/bin/view/Juggler/BuildingFromSvn</ulink>).</para>

         <section id="sonix.compile.section">
            <title>Sonix</title>

            <para>Sonix wraps other audio subsystems such as OpenAL (<ulink
            url="http://www.openal.org/">www.openal.org</ulink>), Audiere
            (<ulink url="http://audiere.sf.net/">audiere.sf.net</ulink>), or
            AudioWorks (<ulink
            url="http://www.multigen.com/">multigen.com</ulink>). At least one
            of these packages must be installed for use by Sonix in order to
            hear sounds in VR Juggler applications. Once you have all the
            necessary source code and third-party package installations, add
            one or more of the following options to your
            <command>configure.pl</command> command line to enable the
            appropriate audio subsystem:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
               <listitem>
                  <para><option>--enable-openal
                  --with-openal=&lt;OPENAL_PATH&gt;</option>: Enable the use
                  of OpenAL and tell the build where OpenAL is installed. The
                  default search path is
                  <filename>/usr/local</filename>.</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para><option>--enable-audiere
                  --with-audiere=&lt;AUDIERE_PATH&gt;</option>: Enable the use
                  of Audiere and tell the build where Audiere is installed.
                  The default search path is
                  <filename>/usr/local</filename>.</para>
               </listitem>

               <listitem>
                  <para><option>--enable-audioworks
                  --with-audioworks=&lt;AUDIOWORKS_PATH&gt;</option>: Enable
                  the use of AudioWorks and tell the build where AudioWorks is
                  installed. The default search path is
                  <filename>/usr</filename>.</para>
               </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>

            <note>
               <para>AudioWorks and OpenAL cannot be compiled together. They
               depend on mutually exclusive VPR threading subsystems. Warnings
               will be printed by the Sonix configure script indicating this
               fact. OpenAL and Audiere can be compiled together,
               however.</para>
            </note>
         </section>

         <section id="tweek.build.section">
            <title>Tweek</title>

            <para>Tweek needs JDK 1.4 or newer and a C++ CORBA implementation.
            Currently, we primarily use omniORB 4.0. Visit the <ulink
            url="http://omniorb.sourceforge.net/">omniORB website</ulink> to
            download omniORB.</para>

            <note>
               <para>IRIX users must configure Tweek (and its VPR dependency)
               to use the POSIX subsystem or the NSPR subsystem. omniORB
               <emphasis>will not work</emphasis> with SPROC threads. To
               configure VPR to use either POSIX threads or NSPR threads, pass
               either <option>--enable-subsystem=POSIX</option> or
               <option>--enable-subsystem=NSPR</option> respectively to
               <command>configure.pl</command>.</para>
            </note>

            <para>For the following steps, assume that you have omniORB
            installed in <filename>&lt;OMNIORB_PATH&gt;</filename>. Assuming
            you have the external packages installed, do the following from
            the top-level <filename>juggler</filename> directory:</para>

            <screen>mkdir build
cd build
../configure.pl --with-cxx-orb=omniORB4 --with-cxx-orb-root=&lt;OMNIORB_PATH&gt; --with-java-orb=JDK --module=Tweek
gmake build install</screen>
         </section>
      </section>
   </section>
</article>