<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>VR Juggler 1.0</title>

    <subtitle>Technical Overview</subtitle>

    <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>

    <!--        
<releaseinfo>$Header$</releaseinfo>
        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
                <date>Feb 27, 2002</date>
                <revremark>Initial revision of the document.</revremark>
            </revision>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>1.3</revnumber>
                <date>Feb 28, 2002</date>
                <revremark>Added content from some other sources.</revremark>
            </revision>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>1.4</revnumber>
                <date>Feb 28, 2002</date>
                <revremark>Fixed up figures and cleaned up all the errors in the xml structure.</revremark>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>
-->
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>This document is the technical for VR Juggler (VRJ). It describes
    the design choices and implementation details of VR Juggler. We describe
    what the major components of the system are, why the components are there,
    and how the components are implemented and used with the rest of VR
    Juggler.</para>

    <para>This guide is designed to be used by developers who want to extend
    VR Juggler and people who are just interest in the low-level details of
    the system. As such, it is expected that readers are already comfortable
    with the basics of VR Juggler such as writing an application and
    configuring the system. This guide will not describe these basic details
    of VR Juggler but will instead focus on the behind the scenes details of
    the underlying system.</para>

    <para>Before we get start describing the system in detail, we are going to
    take a moment and explain what VR Juggler is and describe some of the
    fundamental concepts and metaphors of the system. Hopefully this will make
    the design more clear and provide some insight into our design
    philosophy.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Fundamentals</title>

    <section>
      <title>What is VR Juggler?</title>

      <para>VR Juggler is an object-oriented development environment to
      support the efficient development of time-critical, interactive
      immersive applications independently of the underlying technologies. We
      discuss the VP concept in the context of prototyping, debugging, and
      running immersive applications and focus on the approach taken to
      specify, design, and implement VR Juggler.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Virtual Platform: A virtual platform for virtual reality
      application development</title>

      <para>The fundamental metaphor of VR Juggler is that VR Juggler is a
      virtual platform for VR application development.</para>

      <para>A virtual platform (VP) provides a development and execution
      environment that is independent from hardware architecture, operating
      system (OS), and available VR hardware configurations. It provides a
      unified operating environment in which developers can write and test
      applications using the available resources while guaranteeing the
      portability of the application to other resources.</para>

      <para>The VR Juggler virtual platform (JVP) addresses the following key
      technical challenges (See <xref linkend="NeedsOfVRSystem.appendix" />
      for more information about these needs)</para>

      <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="normal">
        <listitem>
          <para>Abstract the complexities of the current VR system</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Allow the use of any graphics API</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Provide for scalability of VR systems and resources in terms
          of the number of display surfaces, computer systems, human/computer
          interface equipment, networks, and software tools.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Provide flexibility to adapt and cope with a wide variety of
          hardware configurations</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Allow for run-time changes in the hardware and software
          configuration of the environment</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Provide the ability of running multiple applications
          simultaneously</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Provide tools for evaluating and tuning the performance of the
          VR Juggler system and the applications that use it.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <remark>[Describe why we need a virtual platform. What use cases does it
      satisfy: write once-run anywhere, ]</remark>

      <para>The purpose of the VR Juggler virtual platform (JVP) is to
      separate the hardware-dependent and hardware-independent software
      components of the VR software system. The virtual platform provides a
      simple operating environment for virtual reality application
      development. By using the JVP, a developer can write an application once
      on a local VR system and run it on any other VR system.</para>

      <para>The JVP design has the following characteristics.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Virtual platform API</title>

        <figure float="1" id="Intro-VirtualPlatformAppInterface.figure">
          <title>Application/VP Interface</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/VP_APP_sepLine.png" format="PNG"
                         scalefit="1" width="3in" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>The basic JVP system () is composed of an application object, a
        draw manager, and the VR Juggler kernel. The interface between the
        application object and the JVP consists of the kernel interface that
        provides the hardware abstraction for the virtual platform, and the
        draw manager that provides the abstraction for the graphics AP (<xref
        linkend="Intro-VirtualPlatformAppInterface.figure" />).</para>

        <remark>[Pt: Summary of Kernel interface]</remark>

        <para>The JVP kernel interface provides all application accessible
        functionality except for graphics API specific features. The kernel
        itself is responsible for controlling all components in the VR Juggler
        system. Because the kernel controls all the other VR Juggler
        components, its interface provides the virtual platform API for the
        hardware-specific details of the environment. Because the kernel
        interface is the only way the application accesses the hardware, it is
        possible to change the implementation details of any component of VR
        Juggler as long as the kernel interface remains the same.</para>

        <remark>[Pt: Draw manager interface summary]</remark>

        <para>The kernel does not depend upon any graphics API specific
        details, instead it captures all of these in the draw manager, which
        is an external manager of the VR Juggler kernel. Applications use the
        draw manager portion of the virtual platform interface to access any
        API specific details that are needed.</para>

        <remark>[Pt: Don’t have to change code when the system
        changes]</remark>

        <para>The virtual platform interface means that application code does
        not have to change when new system features are added or even when
        running on a different VR system. The virtual platform in VR Juggler
        separates the application developer from the system details that can
        change. Since the virtual platform consists of the kernel and the draw
        manager, we have the freedom to change any details of the VR Juggler
        system as long as the interfaces to the draw manager and the kernel
        remain the same. As long as the interface looks and behaves the same,
        the application can never see or rely upon any details hidden by the
        virtual platform. This provides VR Juggler applications system
        independence. Once a VR Juggler application is written for one system,
        it can run with VR Juggler on any other system.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Benefits of virtual platform</title>

        <para>The following are the major benefits of the of the virtual
        platform design in VR Juggler.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Architecture and OS independence</para>

            <remark>[Pt: The JVP handles cross-platform issues]</remark>

            <para>The JVP allows development of applications that are free
            from architecture and OS dependence leading to truly
            cross-platform applications. This allows applications written with
            the virtual platform to run on architecture that the JVP has been
            ported to. It also allows the virtual platform to be tuned for
            each local platform in order to run VR Juggler applications with
            high-performance.</para>

            <remark>[Pt: The JVP scales]</remark>

            <para>Freedom from architecture and OS allow application
            development on any available hardware. It is possible to develop
            applications on low-end PC systems without sacrificing any
            functionality. The application will still run on high-end systems,
            but access to the high-end system and VR hardware is not required
            during development. Developing on low-end systems cuts costs and
            allows for easier application development.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Device abstraction</para>

            <remark>[Pt: VP provides Standard abstractions of input
            devices]</remark>

            <para>The JVP provides standard abstractions for many classes of
            VR devices such as: positional, digital, and glove. By using these
            common abstractions for device classes, the virtual software
            system hides the details of the actual devices in use. The
            application can make use of these device abstractions to get data
            from the devices.</para>

            <remark>[Pt: Separation from hardware]</remark>

            <para>The JVP eliminates the need for direct ties between the
            application and the hardware by separating the application and the
            device in use. Applications written using the virtual platform
            only need to use a device handle to an input device. A device
            handle has an associated device class and returns data of that
            class type. The input data can come from any available device that
            is of the needed class type or can simulate that class
            type.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Allows for use of multiple graphics APIs</para>

            <remark>[Must have support to multiple APIs]</remark>

            <para>In addition to freeing the application from hardware
            dependencies, a virtual platform must allow developers to use any
            graphics API they choose. This satisfies the requirements of not
            tying the environment to a single graphics API and also allowing
            the developer to use whatever tools are best suited for the
            job.</para>

            <remark>[Pt: Intro to VJ draw manager]</remark>

            <para>The JVP supports multiple graphics APIs by encapsulating all
            graphics API specific behavior in draw managers. Because the
            kernel represents only the part of the virtual platform that hides
            system details, we must add an additional interface to the virtual
            platform that is specific for each supported graphics API. Each
            draw manager controls the details of writing an application for
            its specific graphics API. The draw manager's interface represents
            an entirely different virtual platform interface that presents the
            application with an API-specific abstraction.</para>

            <remark>[Pt: Use kernel and draw manager in parallel]</remark>

            <para>The kernel and the draw managers are used in parallel to
            create applications that are both independent of hardware and that
            make use of features of the graphics API used by the application.
            When we refer to the virtual platform in the rest of this writing,
            we will be referring to this combination of the kernel virtual
            platform interface and the draw manager virtual platform interface
            unless specifically noted.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Operating environment</para>

            <para>The JVP provides a simple operating environment for VR
            applications. This operating environment allows for multiple
            running applications and components. Each running application is
            an object under the control of the JVP that shares resources and
            processing time with other applications currently
            executing.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Discussion</title>

        <para>The concept of a virtual platform facilitates and simplifies the
        effort of application development in complex VR systems. It provides a
        unified working environment that supports development and execution of
        applications, independently of the underlying technology. A virtual
        platform guarantees the longevity of applications, and allows
        application developers to keep up with the technology advances without
        having to invest time and resources in modifying applications to
        support the new technologies.</para>

        <para>Although there is a popular, and all-to-often well-founded,
        belief that object-oriented abstraction introduces severe penalties in
        program performance, we believe that object-oriented design approach
        for VR Juggler as a virtual platform provides the best avenue to
        achieve its goals. We have placed a great deal of effort on
        optimization of our abstraction levels to minimize the performance
        impact. Currently, performance evaluations of the different components
        are under way; early results are showing that the overall VR Juggler
        performance is within acceptable response times.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Configuration information</title>

    <figure float="1" id="ConfigChunk-WindowChunk.figure">
      <title>Figure 20: Window Configuration Element</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/Thesis18.png" format="PNG" scalefit="1"
                     width="2in" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <remark revisionflag="added">Need much more information about the
    configuration system here. Add information from run-time config paper
    about parameterization.</remark>

    <para>All configuration information is contained within small units called
    config "elements", and these elements are divided into properties that
    hold values. Each property value has a default type associated with it.
    Although the properties have these default types, they are implemented as
    a variant data type which allows them to return data in whatever data type
    is needed.</para>

    <para>An element contains all the configuration information for a
    particular aspect of the VR system or application. For example, the
    element given in <xref linkend="ConfigChunk-WindowChunk.figure" /> defines
    configuration information for a window. It has three properties: name,
    size, and origin. The size property has two values of type int.</para>

    <para>VR Juggler uses config elements to set configuration options for all
    the components of the system. There are elements for specifying
    configuration information for all types of information needed to set up a
    VR environment: display elements, tracker elements, C2 elements, HMD
    elements, and so on.</para>

    <para>Configuration information is edited with a Java based GUI called
    vjControl. It used to edit configuration information and interface to the
    running VR Juggler kernel. It allows users to create and edit config
    files, change the configuration at run-time, start and stop devices, and
    view performance data.</para>

    <para>Applications can also use the configuration system, adding their own
    elements of data that can be loaded with the same interface and edited
    with the same graphical tools. This allows applications to use the same
    simple, graphical configuration tools as the VR Juggler environment
    itself.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>VR Juggler Microkernel</title>

    <figure float="1" id="MicroKernel-MainArch.figure">
      <title>Microkernel architecture</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/MicrokernelClassDiagram.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <remark>[ Why use a microkernel. ]</remark>

    <para>Based upon the requirements that the system must be extensible and
    flexible, the first problem the VR Juggler team set about to solve was how
    to design the core of a system that could support the needs of such a
    dynamic system. The system would need to allow evolve as it grew and
    needed to support the ability to add new functionality and make changes to
    existing services without affecting the entire system. The design also
    needed to have ingrained support for its own modification and
    extension.</para>

    <para>It was concluded that a specialization of the microkernel
    architecture [#system of patterns] would be the best solution to this
    problem.</para>

    <remark revisionflag="added">[Pt: Short summary of microkernel
    architecture]</remark>

    <para>The microkernel controls the entire run-time system and manages all
    communication within the system. The VR Juggler microkernel architecture
    (<xref linkend="MicroKernel-MainArch.figure" />) has a core kernel object
    that implements the central services needed for VR application
    development: input devices, display settings, and configuration
    information.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Internal Managers</para>

        <para>Internal managers implement core functionality that the kernel
        cannot easily handle. If a core service would unduly increase the size
        or complexity of the kernel, the kernel uses an internal manager to
        provide the service. Internal managers can also be used to group logic
        functionality together in a single sub-unit. By grouping common
        functionality together, it allows the kernel to manage the features as
        a single group. There are internal managers to handle input devices,
        display settings, configuration information, and to communicate with
        the external applications.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>External Managers</para>

        <para>External managers provide an interface to the system that is
        specific to the application type. Client applications communicate with
        the VR Juggler system through the interfaces of the external managers
        and of the kernel. Currently the only external managers are the
        graphics API specific draw managers. These draw managers give
        applications a view specific to a graphics API. The system can be
        easily extended to add other types of external managers such as sound
        systems. The Juggler external managers are primarily used to provide
        an interface to external software tools that applications need to
        share</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Modularity</title>

      <remark>[Pt: Juggler has a highly modular kernel]</remark>

      <para>The VR Juggler kernel is a modular architecture that allows
      managers to be added, removed, and reconfigured at run-time. The kernel
      only loads the modules that running applications currently require. This
      modularization of the kernel helps to prevent the system from becoming
      monolithic. It also give the kernel a high degree of robustness because
      the kernel can execute with any combination of modules.</para>

      <para>The kernel has references to each active manager in the system. By
      changing the references at run-time, the kernel can alter the behavior
      of the system. When the references are null, then the kernel simply
      ignores that functionality. Although the kernel can execute without any
      other managers, it must be connected to managers in order to render a
      virtual environment.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Mediator</title>

      <remark>[Pt: The managers are active objects under kernel
      control]</remark>

      <para>Many of the managers in VR Juggler are active objects [#active
      object] that are kept synchronized by the kernel. The kernel maintains
      control of the system because all the managers require the kernel to
      signal them during the stages of their processing. Because of this, the
      main kernel thread can control the timing of all the other active
      objects in the system. The managers and application only get processing
      time when the kernel allocates it either by calling a method of the
      class or by signaling the active object's thread to continue
      processing.</para>

      <remark>[Pt: Kernel acts as mediator and captures interaction]</remark>

      <para>In this way, the VR Juggler kernel acts as a mediator [#Design
      patterns] by encapsulating the control of how all the other components
      in the system interact. It can do this because only the kernel knows
      about the managers; there are no direct dependencies between the
      managers themselves. The kernel can change the way the system frame
      executes by simply changing the timing of calls it makes to the
      managers. It can do this without disrupting their normal
      behavior.</para>

      <remark>[Pt: Loose coupling and flexibility]</remark>

      <para>Capturing the interaction between the managers decreases coupling
      since the managers only know about the kernel. This means that the
      kernel can change the way the managers interact with each other without
      requiring changes in the implementation of the managers. It also means
      that the managers can change independently of the interactions. This
      independence is an aid to development because of the flexibility it
      gives to the design. If new capabilities are needed, it is only
      necessary to add a new internal or external manager. Changes to one part
      of the system, such as the addition of a draw manager for a new graphics
      API, have no effect on the rest of kernel.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Kernel portability</title>

      <para>The VR Juggler kernel is layered on top of a set of low-level
      primitives that ease porting and allow for performance tuning on each
      hardware platform. The primitives control process management,
      synchronization, and other hardware-dependent issues (<xref
      linkend="MicroKernel-MainArch.figure" />). Because these primitive
      classes account for the majority of hardware-specific implementation
      differences, they can greatly ease the porting of VR Juggler to other
      architectures. During the porting process, each low-level primitive is
      extended and optimized in order to achieve high performance on each
      system.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Consequences</title>

      <para>A microkernel design has several important consequences to the
      design as discussed in [#system of patterns]</para>

      <section>
        <title>Benefits</title>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Portability:</emphasis> Porting the
        microkernel to a new platform only requires modifying the hardware
        depended components. In a microkernel design, the dependencies are
        captured in a small subset of the system.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Flexibility and Extensibility:</emphasis>
        "One of the biggest strengths of the Microkernel system is its
        flexibility and extensibility." To add new features to the kernel, a
        new internal manager is added. To add a new system interface or
        support a new external API, a new external manager is added to the
        system.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Costs</title>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">Complexity of design and
        implementation:</emphasis> Developing a microkernel-based system is a
        non-trivial task.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Internal Managers</title>

    <para>As stated in the section about the microkernel, internal managers
    are responsible for system tasks that are beyond the scope of the kernel.
    The internal managers capture the commonality of tasks such as managing
    the current input devices or tracking the current state of the
    configuration system. The remainder of this section describes the major
    internal managers.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Input manager</title>

      <figure float="1" id="InputManager-DeviceTypeHierarchy.figure">
        <title>Input device hierarchy</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/InputDeviceTypeHierarchy.png"
                       format="PNG" scalefit="" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <remark>[What is the input manager?]</remark>

      <para>The Input Manager controls all manner of input devices for the
      kernel. The input devices are divided into distinct categories,
      including position devices (such as trackers), digital devices (such as
      a wand or mouse button), analog devices (such as a steering wheel or
      joystick), and glove devices (such as a CyberGlove™). VR Juggler defines
      a class hierarchy for the all of these types of input devices (see <xref
      linkend="InputManager-DeviceTypeHierarchy.figure" />). There is base
      class for all input devices that specifies the methods that must be
      implemented to start, stop, and update the device (see
      <classname>vjInput</classname> <xref
      linkend="InputManager-DeviceTypeHierarchy.figure" />). There is also a
      base class defined for each distinct category that specifies the generic
      interface that any device of that category must support. For example all
      positional devices must derive from <classname>vjPosition</classname>
      support a <methodname>getPosData() </methodname>member function that
      returns a position matrix.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Adding a device</title>

        <para>To add support for new devices, developers create a new class
        for the specific device. The new class must be derived from the base
        classes of the input types that the new device can return (<xref
        linkend="InputManager-DeviceTypeHierarchy.figure" />). For example, a
        device that can return analog and positional data is derived from
        <classname>vjAnalog</classname> and <classname>vjPosition</classname>.
        The new class has to implement the member functions of the base input
        device interface as well as the methods for returning the input type
        of each of the parent classes.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Device proxies</title>

        <remark>[Pt: Applications access devices through proxies]]</remark>

        <para>The application uses device proxies [#Design patterns] to
        interface with all devices. Before an application gets data from a
        device, it must first get a proxy to the device. The application
        requests the device using the name given to it in the current
        configuration. The input manager looks up the requested device name,
        and returns a proxy to the corresponding physical device.</para>

        <remark>[Pt: Device proxies allow for decoupling ◊
        reconfiguration]</remark>

        <para>The main advantage of device proxies is that they allow the
        application to be decoupled from the physical device being used. The
        device referred to by a proxy can change at run-time. For example, a
        proxy may initially be linked to a hardware tracker in the system. If
        the user wants to change tracking systems, then the user points the
        proxy to a different tracker. The next frame, the application still
        uses the same proxy but the data returned is now coming from a
        different device. The proxy abstraction allows the configuration of
        the virtual platform to change during execution without disturbing the
        application.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Device store</title>

        <remark>[What is it]</remark>

        <figure float="1" id="InputManager-DeviceStore.figure">
          <title>Device store</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/DeviceFactory.png" format="PNG"
                         scalefit="" width="4in" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>VR Juggler uses a device store [#Object store] to allow the
        system to keep all device drivers separate from the main library and
        to dynamically load device drivers at run-time (see vjDeviceFactory in
        <xref linkend="InputManager-DeviceStore.figure" />). The device store
        is a factory object [#GOF] that keeps track of device drivers and
        associated device constructors that have registered with the system. A
        device constructor is a proxy that hides the exact type of a device
        driver and the method used to create new instances of the device.
        There is no coupling between the library and the device drivers, so
        the set of device drivers can vary independently.</para>

        <remark>[How does it work]</remark>

        <para>When the input manager receives a configuration request to add a
        new device, it asks the store if it has a constructor that knows about
        the device name given. The store queries all the registered device
        constructors and if one of them knows how to instantiate a driver for
        the named device, then an instance of the new class is created and the
        configuration information is passed to it. A handle to the new device
        is then added to the input manager’s list of active devices.</para>

        <remark>[Dynamic loading]</remark>

        <para>The device store supports the addition of new devices at
        run-time or at link time by registering a new device constructor
        object with the device store. This allows a developer to add new
        device drivers without having to recompile an application. The
        application only has to be compiled with the associated device library
        or load the device library at run-time to have access to the new
        devices.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Environment manager</title>

      <para>The environment manager allows vjControl to connect to a running
      VR Juggler application. VjControl, communicates with the environment
      manager via a network connection. The environment manager supplies data
      to the GUI and passes on instructions from the GUI to the kernel. From
      the vjControl user interface, it is possible to view and dynamically
      control every aspect the running virtual platform.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Display manager</title>

      <figure float="1" id="DisplayManager-DisplayMgrClasses.figure">
        <title>Display Manager</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/DisplayManagerClasses.png"
                       format="PNG" scalefit="1" width="3.5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The display manager (see <xref
      linkend="DisplayManager-DisplayMgrClasses.figure" />) encapsulates all
      the information about the display windows' settings. This includes
      information such as size, location, graphics pipeline, and the viewing
      parameters being used. In addition to holding the display parameters,
      the display manager is also responsible for performing all viewing
      calculations for the windows it controls. This is done as part of the
      main kernel control loop.</para>

      <para>The display manager is also used for communicating configuration
      requests to the draw managers in the system. When a new window is
      created in the system, the display manager handles the configuration
      request by adding the window to its internal state information. Then it
      triggers an update notification that notifies the draw manager of the
      new display window.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>External managers</title>

    <section>
      <title>Draw manager</title>

      <remark>[Pt: What is it and what services does it provide]</remark>

      <para>The draw manager provides support for client applications that
      need access to graphics API-specific functionality. A draw manager
      defines a base class application interface that is customized for a
      specific graphics API. Since the draw manager is specific to an API, it
      allows for use of API specific features. For example, a scene graph API
      has a custom interface that queries the application for the scene graph
      to render. A direct mode rendering API, such as OpenGL, has an interface
      that defines a draw method to send all graphics rendering commands.
      Customizing the draw managers for specific APIs allows for maximum
      application performance because the application can make use of any
      advanced API features the developer desires.</para>

      <remark>[How does it work]</remark>

      <para>Draw managers manage all the details specific to each API. They
      handle the details of configuring the settings of the API, setting up
      viewing parameters for each frame, and rendering the views. The draw
      manager also manages API-specific windowing and graphic context
      creation. Because all the graphics API specific details are captured in
      the draw managers, VR Juggler maintains portability to many graphics
      APIs.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Other external managers</title>

      <para>Currently VR Juggler has no other external managers, but we expect
      that this will be a major area for future extension.</para>

      <para>New external managers would function much like the draw manager by
      providing applications with interfaces that are specific to the type of
      service offered to the application. As long as the applications make use
      of the encapsulated features using the interface provided, VR Juggler
      will take care of the details of keeping the manager synchronized with
      the rest of the system.</para>

      <para>An example of an external manager that is currently under
      development is a sound manager. The sound manager will provide a unified
      interface for loading and play sound samples. The actual implementation
      will adapt to the local system configuration and use whatever method is
      available to handle the sound. Since user applications will only access
      the sound system through this interface, their applications will move
      transparently from one sound system backend to another.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Application objects</title>

    <figure float="1" id="AppObjectInterfaceAndCodePullout.figure">
      <title>Application object</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/AppPulloutCode.png" format="PNG"
                     scalefit="1" width="4in" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>In VR Juggler, user applications are objects (see <xref
    linkend="AppObjectInterfaceAndCodePullout.figure" />). The VR Juggler
    system uses the application object to create the VR environment in which
    the user interacts. The application object inherits from based application
    objects that define an interface that must be implemented by the
    application object. The kernel maintains control over the environment and
    calls the methods defined in the application interface. When the kernel
    calls the application's methods, it gives up control to the application
    object so the application can execute the code needed to create the
    virtual environment.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Base application interfaces</title>

      <remark>[communicate through pre-defined class interfaces]</remark>

      <figure float="1" id="VJAPP-HIER-App-GlApp-PfApp.figure">
        <title>Application class hierarchy</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/AppHierarchy.png" format="PNG"
                       scalefit="1" width="4in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure float="1" id="AppObject-AppBaseClasses.figure">
        <title>User app base classes</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/userOglApp_hierarchy.png" format="PNG"
                       scalefit="1" width="4in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <remark>[Pt: Must derive from base classes]</remark>

      <para>The first step in writing an application object is to derive from
      the base classes that define the kernel and draw manager interfaces the
      application needs to implement. There is a base class for the interface
      that the kernel expects and a base class for interfaces needed by each
      of the available draw managers. For example in the
      <methodname>userOglApp</methodname> class in <xref
      linkend="AppObject-AppBaseClasses.figure" /> the interface needed for
      the Kernel is <methodname>vjApp</methodname> and the interface needed by
      the draw manager is <methodname>vjGlApp</methodname>. Since all
      applications must interact with the kernel, all applications are
      required to implement the <methodname>vjApp</methodname> interface. Only
      OpenGL application objects need to implement the
      <methodname>vjGlApp</methodname> interface.</para>

      <para>The kernel interface (<methodname>vjApp</methodname>) specifies
      methods for initialization, shutdown, and to give the application
      processing time.</para>

      <para>The kernel calls each of the member functions of the interface
      based on a strictly scheduled frame of execution. During the frame of
      execution, the kernel calls the application methods and performs
      internal updates (see <methodname>updateDevices()</methodname> in <xref
      linkend="AppObject-KERNEL-FRAME.figure" />). Because the kernel has
      complete control over the frame, it can make changes at predefined
      "safe" times when the application is not doing any processing (see
      checkForReconfig() in <xref linkend="AppObject-KERNEL-FRAME.figure" />).
      During these "safe" times, the kernel can change the virtual platform
      configuration as long as the interface remains the same.</para>

      <para>The frame of execution also serves as a framework for the
      application. The application can expect that when
      <methodname>preFrame()</methodname> is called, the devices have just
      been updated for this frame. Applications can rely upon the system being
      in well-defined stages of the frame when the kernel executes its
      methods.</para>

      <para>The draw manager interface for this application
      (<methodname>vjGlApp</methodname>) specifies the functions that are
      necessary to render and OpenGL application. The interface has functions
      for drawing the scene and for initializing context-specific
      information.</para>

      <figure float="1" id="AppObject-KERNEL-FRAME.figure">
        <title>Kernel frame</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/Kernel_Loop_Call_Sequence.png"
                       format="PNG" scalefit="1" width="5in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>No main() -- Don't call me, I'll call you.</title>

      <remark>[No Main]</remark>

      <para>There is no main() function. Since VR Juggler applications are
      objects, developers do not write a main() function. Instead, developers
      create an application object that implement a set of pre-defined
      interfaces.</para>

      <remark>[How is juggler kernel actually performing same thing]</remark>

      <para>In common programs, the main function signals the point where the
      thread of control enters the application. After the main function is
      called, the application starts performing any application processing
      necessary. When the OS starts the program, it gives the main function
      some processing time. Then after the process's quantum expires, the
      operating system switches to another process.</para>

      <para>In VR Juggler, we accomplish the same functionality. The kernel is
      the scheduler, and it allocates processing time to an application by
      invoking the methods of the application object. The difference is that
      the kernel is stricter about when the application gets processing time
      because it has extra knowledge about how the application works.</para>

      <para>Application objects can exist either linked in with the kernel
      startup code or alone as a dynamically loadable object. In this paper we
      will only talk about compiling application objects with the startup code
      to produce a standalone executable. However, it is possible to do some
      exciting things with dynamically loadable application objects which are
      beyond the scope of this paper.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Benefits of application objects</title>

      <para>Application objects provide many unique benefits that are not
      possible in traditional procedural systems. Many of these benefits can
      be traced back the the flexibility allows by the microkernel
      architecture and application object design.</para>

      <para>Because the kernel always knows the current state of the system,
      it can make changes at run-time. If the application was not an object,
      but was instead a program that was in control of the kernel, then the
      kernel would not have so much flexibility. The kernel would not be able
      to know what the application was doing and as a result, it would be
      possible for the application to rely on something in a way the kernel
      did not expect.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run-time changes</para>

          <para>Since the kernel controls each execution frame, it is simpler
          for the system to change at run-time because the kernel knows when
          it is safe to make changes to the virtual platform. The VR Juggler
          system allows nearly every parameter to change at run time. It is
          possible to change applications, start new devices, reconfigure
          devices, and send reconfiguration information to the application
          object. The ability to modify the system's behavior at run-time is
          one of the major strengths of VR Juggler, and it is enabled because
          the application is an object with a standard public
          interface.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Low coupling and increased robustness</para>

          <para>Application objects lead to a robust architecture as a result
          of low coupling and well defined inter-object dependencies. The
          application interface defines the only communication path between
          the application and the virtual platform. By restricting
          interactions to the interfaces of the kernel, draw manager, and
          application, the system restricts object inter-dependencies to those
          few interfaces. This decreased coupling allows changes in the system
          to stay local. Changes to one object will not affect another unless
          the change involves a change of the interface of one of the objects.
          This leads to more robust and extensible code.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Dynamic loading</para>

          <para>Because the application is simply an object, it is possible to
          dynamically load and unload applications at run-time. When the
          virtual platform starts up, it waits for an application to be passed
          to it. When the application is given to the VR Juggler kernel at
          run-time, the kernel performs a few initialization steps, and then
          executes the application.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Allow implementation changes</para>

          <para>Since applications use a distinct interface to communicate
          with the virtual platform, changes to the implementation of the
          virtual platform do not affect the application. This makes it simple
          to make significant changes to the implementation of the virtual
          platform without affecting any applications that currently run on
          the platform. These changes could include bug fixes, performance
          tuning, new device support, or any number of other changes.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>VR Juggler Clustering Architecture Design</title>

    <para>In this section, we present the design of the clustering support in
    VR Juggler. This feature architecture allows an application to
    transparently run on a cluster of comodity PCs. The main goals of the VR
    Juggler clustering support are to allow the cluster software to adapt to
    the particular hardware configuration of the virtual reality system, to
    provide application portability and scalability from high-end to commodity
    by hiding the clustering from developers, and to allow users to customize
    the clustering methods being used.</para>

    <para>Based on our past experiences, we have created an infrastructure
    that combines best practices of graphics clustering into a modular and
    extensible design. Its key aspects are the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A layered clustering architecture that separates the clustering
        components into several major subsystems. This allows for a high
        degree of modularity.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A component system that allows extension to the clustering
        infrastructure through dynamically loaded plug-ins. Plug-ins extend
        the core clustering system with specialized functionality.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>As shown in <xref linkend="figure.cluster.layers" />, the VR Juggler
    clustering infrastructure is comprised of a set of components arranged
    into several layers. This technique was chosen to make the infrastructure
    highly modular. Each layer uses only the functionality provided to it by
    the layers below.</para>

    <figure id="figure.cluster.layers">
      <title>VR Juggler Cluster Infrastructure Layers</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/ClusterLayers.png"
                     format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Each of the layers is described in more detail below.</para>

    <section id="section.cluster.manager">
      <title>Cluster Manager</title>

      <indexterm zone="section.cluster.manager">
        <primary>cluster</primary>

        <secondary>architecture layers</secondary>

        <tertiary>Cluster Manager</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The Cluster Manager layer is responsible for the configuration of
      all layers in the cluster infrastructure and managing the active plugins
      (see <xref linkend="figure.cluster.classes" />). This includes
      maintaining a list of all current plug-ins and synchronizing the calls
      to each plug-in so that they may perform their specialized tasks.
      Plug-ins register themselves with the Cluster Manager upon being
      loaded.</para>

      <figure id="figure.cluster.classes">
        <title>Cluster Classes</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/ClusterClasses.png"
                       scale="" width="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The Cluster Manager is one of only two static components of the
      clustering infrastructure. It acts as a facade for the entire clustering
      sub-system. It is responsible for maintaining a list of all current
      plug-ins, configuring all sub layers, calling the plugins to perform
      their specific tasks, and syncronizing the kernel loop between
      machines.</para>

      <para>When a plug-in is dynamically loading, it automatically registers
      itself with the Cluster Manger where it is thrown into a list of
      plug-ins for later use. This list is the only way that the clustering
      infrastrucdture knows about the plug-ins. This means that that there is
      absolutely no way to access these plug-ins unless you go through the
      Cluster Manager's API and this list.</para>

      <para>VR Juggler's architeture has the amazing ability to reconfigure
      itself while it is running. This is a complex task of <indexterm>
          <primary>Run Time Reconfiguration</primary>
        </indexterm>run-time reconfiguration is difficult when running on one
      machine, let alone across a cluster. The Cluster Manager is resoponsible
      for making this all happen behind the sceens.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Run-time configuration is the process of changing the state of
        the application while it is running. For example it would be possible
        for the user to connect to the cluster using a PDA and reconfigure the
        display system being used. This is a complex task when running on one
        machine let alone across a cluster.</para>
      </note>

      <figure id="figure.class.ClusterManager">
        <title>Class Diagram:
        <classname>cluster::ClusterManager</classname></title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/ClusterManager.gif"
                       width="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <note>
        <para>VR Juggler is continually running through a loop of method calls
        that receive information from external devices, calculates application
        data, and draws the users perspective called the kernel loop.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Within the VR Juggler kernel loop (see <xref
      linkend="figure.kernel.control.loop" />) there are many different
      locations that we might need to send information across the network in
      order to fully synchronize the cluster. For example, application data
      needs to be shared directly before the draw function because this data
      needs to be identical across the cluster right before we draw the scene.
      But, on the other hand input data needs to be shared at the beginning of
      the loop so that <methodname>preFrame()</methodname> can use this data
      to calculate the state of the scene such as the navigation matrix. In
      order to accommodate all possible needs of a plug in, there are calls
      into the Cluster Manager at numerous locations during the kernel loop.
      The Cluster Manager is then responsible for calling any plugin that
      needs to use the network to transfer data.</para>

      <figure id="figure.kernel.control.loop">
        <title>VR Juggler <indexterm>
            <primary>Kernel</primary>

            <secondary>ConrolLoop</secondary>
          </indexterm>Kernel Loop</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figures/Kernel_Loop_Call_Sequence.png"
                       format="PNG" width="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>In order to guarantee that one node does not progress further
      through the kernel loop than the other nodes the Cluster Manager must
      provide a level of synchronization on every method call from the kernel
      loop. This is accomplished by requiring the Cluster Manager to receive
      all data packets. Each plug-in is only responsible for sending packets
      to other cluster nodes. Once all plugins have sent their data, the
      Cluster Manager sends an <literal>END_BLOCK</literal> packet telling the
      remote nodes that it is done sending information and then reads data
      from the network until it receives an <literal>END_BLOCK</literal> from
      all other nodes. The syncronization occurs because each node must
      indicate to all other nodes that it has completed the current frame (see
      <xref linkend="figure.frame.sync" />).</para>

      <figure id="figure.frame.sync">
        <title>Frame Syncronization</title>

        <mediaobject id="y">
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/EndBlock.png"
                       format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="section.cluster.network">
      <title>Cluster Network</title>

      <indexterm zone="section.cluster.network">
        <primary>cluster</primary>

        <secondary>architecture layers</secondary>

        <tertiary>Cluster Network</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The Cluster Network layer maintains an abstract representation of
      the system of interconnected nodes that comprise the cluster (see <xref
      linkend="figure.cluster.classes" />). This abstraction provides the rest
      of the clustering infrastructre, including all plug-ins, with a
      messaging interface for communicating with the entire cluster.
      Internally, it maintains a list of each node in the cluster along with
      the network connection used to communicate with it. Because the
      networking layer is an abstraction, developers can provide different
      implementations that make use of alternative low-level networking
      methods. The networking implementation can then be configured by the
      user.</para>

      <para>The packets are structured in a way to allow the Cluster Network
      to take a given packet, serialize it to a string of characters and send
      the string to a remote node. When received this string is de-serialized
      into a packet object again. This is accomplished by having a packet
      header, as seen in <xref linkend="figure.cluster.network.packet" />,
      that begins all packets. This header contains integers representing the
      packet type and the packet length. In order to allow the objects to be
      serialized and de-serialized into different formats we took advantage of
      the <interfacename>vpr::ObjectReader</interfacename> and
      <interfacename>vpr::ObjectWriter</interfacename> abstractions within
      VPR, VR Juggler's system abstraction module. This enables us to
      serialize the packets into many different formats such as a string of
      characters or even an XML tree.</para>

      <figure id="figure.cluster.network.packet">
        <title>Packet Structure</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/Packet.png" width="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The process of reading the header, determining the packet type,
      creating the packet structure, and de-serializing the data can be a very
      tedious task. Because of this, we have created a packet factory, seen in
      <xref linkend="figure.class.PacketFactory" />, that automates this
      process. This simplifies code and eliminates one location of possible
      errors.</para>

      <figure id="figure.class.PacketFactory">
        <title>Class Diagram:
        <classname>cluster::PacketFactory</classname></title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/PacketFactory.png"
                       format="PNG" scale="0.25" width="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>As can be seen in <xref linkend="figure.class.ClusterNetwork" />,
      the Cluster Network has been designed to have a very intuitive API
      without any reference to any other parts of the VR Juggler clustering
      infrastructure. The Cluster Network provides everything that a
      programmer needs to send messages between nodes in a cluster. It is also
      because of this robust design that it is possible to develop a
      replacement for the Cluster Network that might use a different low-level
      networking technique.</para>

      <figure id="figure.class.ClusterNetwork">
        <title>Class Diagram:
        <classname>cluster::ClusterNetwork</classname></title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/ClusterNetwork.gif"
                       format="GIF" width="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section id="section.cluster.plugins">
      <title>Cluster Plug-ins</title>

      <indexterm zone="section.cluster.plugins">
        <primary>cluster</primary>

        <secondary>architecture layers</secondary>

        <tertiary>Cluster Plug-ins</tertiary>
      </indexterm>

      <para>The VR Juggler clustering infrastructure makes use of plug-ins to
      extend the basic functionality with specialized features. Cluster
      Plug-ins are loaded on demand at run time. This allows developers to add
      new plug-ins to support additional cluster-based functionality without
      modifying the core clustering infrastructure. All Cluster Plug-ins are
      derived from a common base interface named
      <interfacename>cluster::ClusterPlugin</interfacename>. To create a new
      plug-in, a developer must implement a few of the base interface methods.
      In return, they get a support for network communication,
      synchronization, and run-time reconfiguration.</para>

      <para>VR Juggler ships with several commonly used plug-ins that provide
      the basic features required for clustering of VR Juggler applications.
      The base set of plug-ins can also be used as examples for other
      developers to extend the system.</para>

      <para>These base plugins are the RIMPlugin, ApplicationDataManager, and
      SwapLockManager. The RemoteInputManager plugin is responsible for
      distributing synchronized device data across the cluster. The
      ApplicationDataManager provides developers with a method for sharing
      application data within a clustered application. The SwapLockManager
      implements several methods for synchronizing display updates within a
      cluster. We plan to add additional plugins in the future to support
      extended clustering functionality.</para>

      <para>In order to create a modular system, we wanted to allow the user
      to add any number of additional components to the clustering
      infrastructure in a simple way. We have provided a Cluster Network layer
      to handle all low-level communication and the Cluster Manager to take
      care of all synchronization details. This allows the user to concentrate
      on their specific clustering needs without worrying about the difficult
      low-level issues. In order to create a plug-in, a programmer must only
      implement a few methods. In return they get run-time reconfiguration,
      synchronization, and a cluster network abstraction to handle all
      communication.</para>

      <note>
        <para>As new configuration information is added to the system it is
        delivered to the correct layer or plug-in by the Cluster Manager. In
        order to accomplish this we require that all cluster plug-ins and the
        Cluster Network implement the
        <classname>jccl::ConfigElementHandler</classname> abstract base
        class.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Plug-ins have a very simple interface, shown in <xref
      linkend="figure.interface.ClusterPlugin" />, that allows the user a high
      level of specialization. Plug-in programmers only need to implement
      <methodname>preDraw()</methodname>,
      <methodname>postPostFrame()</methodname>
      <methodname>configCanHandle()</methodname>,
      <methodname>configAdd()</methodname>, and
      <methodname>configRemove()</methodname>. Since these plug-ins are simply
      additions to the Cluster Manager, they are loaded dynamically at run
      time. This allows the sharing of plug-in libraries which do not require
      the developer to recompile VR Juggler.</para>

      <figure id="figure.interface.ClusterPlugin">
        <title>Interface
        <interfacename>cluster::ClusterPlugin</interfacename></title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/ClusterPlugin.png"
                       format="PNG" width="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <section>
        <title>Remote Input Manager</title>

        <para>The Remote Input Manager was created to share device input
        across a cluster. Having the ability to share input data allows us to
        support two different possible application needs. The first being that
        a machine can act as a device server and allow remote applications to
        request device data from a locally attached device such as a tracker.
        The second is the case when we are clustering multiple machines and we
        want to have the exact same input data on each machine every frame so
        that all nodes will be using the same data for computation. The idea
        being that if each node has the same input it will create the same
        scene. We can then configure each node to draw a different section of
        the scene to be displayed.</para>

        <para>Our goal is to design a distributed shared memory system for VR
        application I/O (input/output) data. As a result of distributed I/O,
        application development and execution can transparently move between
        shared memory VR systems and PC cluster VR systems. This means the
        same VR applications will run on both systems, without any changes
        needed to the application.</para>

        <para>VR Juggler already has an input manager that handles local input
        data on a single computer. The clustering infrastructure extends VR
        Juggler by using the Remote Input Manager plug-in as an extension to
        the existing Input Manager. The Remote Input Manager provides a few
        key functions: device location transparency, heterogeneous clusters,
        support for platform-specific device drivers, and an unlimited number
        of devices.</para>

        <para>Not only does the remote input manager have useful
        functionality, but it also intends to avoid forcing the application
        programmer to worry about the location of devices. Once a cluster is
        set up, the programmer and application can act as if each input device
        is connected to every cluster node(<xref
        linkend="figure.virtual.devices" />). The remote input manager avoids
        putting extra burden on application developers and hides the
        complications of the cluster from them.</para>

        <figure id="figure.virtual.devices">
          <title>Virtual Devices</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/VirtualDevices.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Also by distributing the input to cluster nodes across the
        network, we can remove the typical cluster computing constraint of
        having identical computers at each node. We are able to accomplish
        this very easily since our Cluster Network layer works across multiple
        platforms. This allows us to construct a cluster from any combination
        of the platforms supported by VR Juggler (see <xref
        linkend="figure.heterogeneous.cluster" />).</para>

        <figure id="figure.heterogeneous.cluster">
          <title>Heterogeneous Cluster</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
                         fileref="figures/HeterogeneousCluster.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Although VR Juggler supports many platforms, new devices require
        their own drivers for each platform. This can restrict the use of new
        devices on VR systems because writing device drivers is time
        consuming. With the help of the Remote Input Manager, devices whose
        drivers have been integrated into VR Juggler on one platform can be
        utilized on other platforms as well. By connecting to another computer
        through the Remote Input Manager, other platforms can retrieve device
        data across the network until drivers for the specific platforms are
        finally integrated.</para>

        <para>Also, if a large number of input devices are to be used, our
        design allows the devices to be spread across the cluster nodes. This
        prevents problems such as multiple input devices creating a large
        workload on a single computer, or all input hardware not being able to
        attach to a single PC.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Application Data Manager</title>

        <para>The Application Data Manager was created to allow VR application
        developers to easily exchange any type of data they want across a
        cluster of machines. We can accomplish this by letting the developer
        derive from an interface that we have defined. This will allow us to
        grab the data structure, serialize it, send it across the cluster,
        serialize it, and allow all other nodes to access the identical
        data.</para>

        <para>The Application Data Manager allows the application developer to
        share any arbitrary type of data. For example we might have a GUI
        running on a hand held device that interacts with the application to
        provide data to control the application. Since we can not expect this
        GUI to connect to all nodes in the cluster, the application data
        manager allows the hand held device to connect to a single machine
        which will synchronize this data across the cluster.</para>

        <para>As can be seen in <xref linkend="figure.class.UserData" />, you
        can create your own data structure and use two templated mixin classes
        in order to gain the needed interface to allow the Application Data
        Manager to handle you data.</para>

        <figure id="figure.class.UserData">
          <title>User Data</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/UserData.png"
                         format="PNG" width="" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Swap Lock Plug-ins</title>

        <para>Synchronizing multiple displays is one of the biggest challenges
        in creating immersive VR on PCs. This is because a single PC does not
        have enough processing power to generate the graphics for multiple
        displays in VR systems such as a CAVE. Now that graphics hardware is
        becoming available to synchronize multiple active stereo PCs or show
        passive stereo, the design of the VR Juggler clustering infrastructure
        must provide a way for a running applications that distribute across
        multiple PCs and graphic hardware. Because we are using different
        machines that may even have different graphics cards, generating the
        graphics is going to take a different length of time on each machine.
        While generating the image the graphics hardware places the data into
        a buffer that is not being displayed. Once the hardware has generated
        the image it swaps the buffer containing the new data with the buffer
        that is being displayed. We encounter a synchronization issue when the
        cluster nodes swap these buffers at different times. This creates a
        ripping effect that causes the display to appear out of sync. We can
        combat this issue by sending a signal between all machines when they
        should swap their buffers. This communication needs to have a very low
        level of latency, usually on the order of 10-80 μs.</para>

        <para>The swap lock plug-ins give the application developer a set of
        methods which they can choose from while configuring the application.
        The options are shown below:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>TCP/IP: Uses a socket connection to synchronize the cluster.
            [Latency:100 μs]</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>TCP/IP Serial Hybrid: Uses a socket connection for the
            slave-to-master communication and a serial connection for the
            master-to-slave communication. [Latency:80 μs]</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Wired Parallel Port: Uses a Linux kernel module to directly
            communicate through the parallel port. You are required to have an
            external device that acts as a simple AND gate. [Latency:10
            μs]</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Run-time (re)configuration</title>

    <figure id="ConfigChunkHandlerHierarchy.figure">
      <title>jccl::ConfigElementHandler interface</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/ConfigChunkHandlerHierarchy.png"
                     format="PNG" scalefit="1" width="5.5in" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>All VR Juggler managers support run-time reconfigurability. Input
    devices can be reconfigured at runtime without affecting the current
    application. A reconfiguration request can be sent to the input manager
    requesting that a specific proxy be pointed at a different device.
    Displays can also be added and removed at run-time. This feature is
    particularly useful for multi-screen VR systems, because screens can be
    activated and deactivated as the application runs. Applications can also
    receive configuration information. This allows applications to respond to
    changes at run-time in the same way that the rest of the VP does.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Config element handler interface</title>

      <para>VR Juggler provides a common framework for processing
      configuration and reconfiguration requests (see<xref
      linkend="ConfigChunkHandlerHierarchy.figure" />). The framework defines
      an interface (<classname>jccl::ConfigElementHandler</classname>) that
      specifies the methods a "handler" component must implement to support
      run-time reconfiguration. All reconfigurable objects must conform to
      this interface. New objects can add support for run-time reconfiguration
      by simply inheriting from the jccl::ConfigElementHandler class and
      providing implementations for the methods defined by the
      interface.</para>

      <para>The methods in the handler interface are:</para>

      <para><methodname>bool configCanHandle(jccl::ConfigElementPtr
      element):</methodname></para>

      <para>This function is used to determine whether the handler object
      knows how to handle the configuration element given. If the object wants
      to handle the element, then this method should return true. If not, then
      it returns false.</para>

      <para><methodname>bool configAdd(jccl::ConfigElementPtr element):
      </methodname></para>

      <para>The system is requesting that the handler reconfigures the system
      to add the configuration specified by the given element. It returns true
      if the change is successful, and false otherwise.</para>

      <para><methodname>bool configRemove(jccl::ConfigElementPtr
      element):</methodname></para>

      <para>The system is requesting that the handler reconfigures the system
      to remove the configuration specified by the given element. It returns
      true if the change is successful, and false it the change is
      unsuccessful or cannot be completed.</para>

      <para>The class interface creates a simple interface for allowing
      objects to become configurable. Since all configurable components
      support a common interface, the system can simply keep a list of
      reconfigurable components. It is not necessary to know the actual type
      of the components that are being configured.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Pending configuration queue</title>

      <figure float="1" id="ConfigManager-PendingList-Structure.figure">
        <title>Configuration manager structure</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/ConfigManagerStructure.png"
                       format="PNG" scalefit="1" width="4in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Reconfiguration is implemented using a pending config queue that
      is contained in the config manager (see
      <classname>vjConfigManager</classname> in <xref
      linkend="ConfigManager-PendingList-Structure.figure" />). The queue
      contains a list of all currently pending reconfiguration requests. As
      with all other managers, the kernel controls the configuration manager.
      The kernel is in charge of synchronizing the system and sending
      reconfiguration requests.</para>

      <para>The system initially starts with only the kernel and several
      system managers instantiated. When the kernel receives a new
      configuration request, it passes it to the config manager which adds the
      config element to a pending reconfiguration queue. The request remains
      there until the kernel attempts to reconfigure the system with the
      pending requests. When a request is successfully processed, it is
      removed from the queue. If a request is not able to be successfully
      satisfied, then it remains in the queue until the system is able to
      satisfy the request.</para>

      <figure float="1" id="RuntimeConfigurationSequence.figure">
        <title>Interaction of run-time configuration components</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/RuntimeConfigurationSequence.png"
                       format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <address></address>
      </figure>

      <para>Each frame, the kernel checks for new configuration requests (see
      <methodname>checkForReconfig</methodname> in <xref
      linkend="RuntimeConfigurationSequence.figure" />). If there are any new
      entries, then the kernel attempts to process the request. The kernel
      steps through all known managers (that implement the
      <classname>jccl::ConfigElementHandler</classname> interface). The kernel
      asks each one in turn whether they can handle the configuration request.
      If they can, then the kernel passes the request on to the manager. The
      manager then processes the request using whatever methods it requires.
      For example, the input manager maintains an internal list of
      configurable devices. It looks for the device that corresponds to the
      given element, and configures it.</para>

      <para>When the manager returns from processing the request, the kernel
      continues on to the next manager and attempts to process the same
      request. The kernel does not stop processing with the first manager that
      can handle the request, because multiple managers may need to respond to
      the same configuration requests.</para>

      <para>After the kernel has iterated through all the known managers, it
      checks to see if any of the managers successfully processed the
      configuration request. If a manager successfully processed the request,
      then the kernel removes it from the pending queue. The configuration
      request is also stored in an active configuration data structure so the
      system may use the information again in the future. If no manager was
      able to complete the request, then the request remains in the queue
      where the kernel will try to process it again in a future frame.</para>

      <para>This method of processing the configuration information is based
      on the chain of responsibility pattern [#design patterns GOF]. It
      differs only in that the handlers in VR Juggler do not have a strict
      successor chain. Instead, the kernel keeps a list of several base
      handlers. The kernel then traverses this list to find a valid handler
      for a given reconfiguration config element. These handlers may then in
      turn process the request in any way they wish. VR Juggler does not
      impose any specific behavior on the reconfigurable components.</para>

      <para>It is also possible for a system component to directly query the
      config manager if an object would rather not have the kernel manage its
      reconfiguration.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Dependency management</title>

      <figure float="1" id="DependencyCheckingClasses.figure">
        <title>Dependency checking classes</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/DependencyCheckingClasses.png"
                       format="PNG" scalefit="1" width="6in" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>It is not difficult to image situations where the configuration of
      one component relies upon the successful loading and configuration of
      another component. For example, in VR Juggler users access all devices
      through proxies. The device proxy serves as a handle to a device that
      allows the system to access the device indirectly. Users configure
      proxies by specifying the device that the proxy should reference. If the
      system attempts to configure a proxy before the device being referenced
      has been loaded, the proxy’s configuration will fail. Any system that
      implements configuration or reconfiguration of the system must have a
      system in place to handle these inter-dependency issues.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Dependency checking</title>

        <para>To handle dependency resolution, VR Juggler performs dependency
        checking between system components. Dependency checking refers to the
        process the system goes through when it runs a check to see if all the
        system resources required by a new configuration request are available
        before it allows that request to be processed.</para>

        <para>Dependency checking is supervised by the
        <classname>vjDependencyManager</classname>. The dependency manager
        allows the system to send it a query about any configuration element.
        The dependency manager will check to make sure that any dependencies
        that need to be satisfied for the given element have been satisfied,
        and will return approval to the caller.</para>

        <para>The dependency manager checks dependencies by maintaining a list
        of dependency checkers objects that it uses to check for dependency
        fulfillment. All dependency checker objects implement a common
        interface specified by the <classname>vjDepChecker</classname> class
        (see <xref linkend="DependencyCheckingClasses.figure" />).</para>

        <para>This interface defines two methods that are used for dependency
        checking:</para>

        <para><methodname>bool canHandle(jccl::ConfigElementPtr
        element)</methodname></para>

        <para>This function is used to determine whether the checker object
        knows how to evaluated dependencies for the configuration element
        given. It returns true if the object knows how to evaluate the
        dependencies, and false if not.</para>

        <para><methodname>bool depSatisfied(jccl::ConfigElementPtr
        element)</methodname></para>

        <para>This function actually performs the dependency evaluation. If
        the dependencies are satisfied, then it returns true. If dependencies
        are not satisfied, then it returns false.</para>

        <para>System components that require advanced dependency checking are
        responsible for registering their dependency checkers with the
        dependency manager. The VR Juggler manager that most directly deals
        with the components often handles this registration. For example,
        whenever a new device registers with the input manager, the device
        also registers any dependency checkers with the dependency
        manager.</para>

        <para>The manager processes dependency requests by querying each
        dependency checker object to find out what types of configuration
        elements it can evaluate.</para>

        <para>When the manager receives a dependency query, it attempts to
        find a dependency checker that can handle the given configuration
        element (see <xref linkend="RuntimeConfigurationSequence.figure" />).
        If it finds a dependency checker, then it sends a request with the
        element to the checker. The checker then checks for whatever system
        state is required and returns an answer, which the manager returns to
        the originator of the query. If the dependency manager does not find a
        checker, then it uses the default dependency checker to check for many
        of the most common dependency issues.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Automatic unloading</title>

        <para>One issue that we have not touched upon yet is what to do if a
        user removes a component from the system through reconfiguration, but
        another component relies upon the removed item. As an example,
        consider again the case of a proxy that is configured to reference a
        given input device. After the system is fully configured, the device
        is removed via reconfiguration. How does the system keep the proxy in
        a valid state? How does it re-connect the proxy if the original
        component is later re-added to the software system?</para>

        <para>VR Juggler handles these issues through "smart unloading" of
        system components. When a component’s dependencies are reconfigured or
        removed, smart unloading allows the dependent component to reconfigure
        itself dynamically in an attempt to satisfy its dependencies by
        modifying its behavior. If the dependencies cannot be satisfied by
        dynamic modification, then the component is unloaded and placed back
        into the pending queue. This effectively backs-out the original
        configuration requests until all the dependencies are once again
        satisfied.</para>

        <para>Because this process could lead to a cascade of unsatisfied
        dependencies, it continues iteratively until all components of the
        system are once again in a stable state.</para>

        <para>This area of the system is a current area of active research. We
        are investigating better ways for components to dynamically change the
        way that they work in an attempt to deal with unsatisfied dependencies
        via graceful degradation. We are also working to better techniques to
        deal with some of the more highly complex dependencies.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Run-time reconfiguration discussion</title>

      <para>Results of the initial implementation have been very positive. We
      have been able to create a flexible architecture that allows for the
      majority of system components to be reconfigured at run-time. We are
      still refactoring the design to increase flexibility and add more
      reconfiguration abilities to the system.</para>

      <para>The reconfiguration system has been used to create application
      "switchers" at VRAC. When we give tours of the VR systems at VRAC, we
      are faced with the problem of needing to rapidly switch between
      applications and VR system settings. Before we had run-time
      reconfiguration, we would have to shutdown the application and the VR
      system every time we wanted to switch applications. This led to
      unacceptable downtime and increased risk of potential problems when
      restarting the application.</para>

      <para>Using run-time reconfiguration, we have been able to solve this
      problem by creating switcher applications. Our switcher applications
      provide a single unified virtual environment that contains and manages
      any number of stand-alone user applications. Once the switcher
      application has been started, users of the VR system can quickly swap
      between the stand-alone applications without having to leave the
      switcher virtual environment or change system settings. This allows
      people giving tours to just start a single application that allows them
      to run any number of other applications within the same
      environment.</para>

      <para>We have also benefited immensely from the increased robustness
      that the reconfiguration system affords while debugging new hardware
      systems and drivers. Because of the reconfiguration system, the
      applications keep running even when the hardware fails and has to be
      reconfigured or entirely restarted.</para>

      <para>Run-time reconfiguration has also allowed us to do run-time
      performance tuning using the abilities provided by VR Juggler. VR
      Juggler provides a performance monitoring system that allows users to
      interactively evaluate the performance of their applications [#Juggler
      performance Just IPT 2000]. Using this tool, developers can pinpoint
      performance bottlenecks. Then using run-time configuration they can make
      changes in an attempt to increase performance.</para>

      <para>The implementation of run-time reconfiguration has not been
      without its problems though. There have been several obstacles we have
      had overcome and work around during the implementing the system.</para>

      <para>One area of difficulty that we have found is that some of the
      popular application programming interfaces (APIs) used in a VR
      application do not lend themselves well to reconfiguration. Some
      graphics APIs (such as Iris Performer) expect the be in complete control
      of system resources and as such do not provide a way to release the
      API’s resources when VR Juggler does not need them any more. We are
      actively pursuing ways to alleviate these problems by communicating with
      API developers and by investigating systems that are more
      flexible.</para>

      <para>An unexpected result was that average VR users did not jump into
      using run-time reconfigurability immediately. Dynamic systems are still
      a new concept and it will take some time for users to become comfortable
      with and begin actively taking advantage of the new abilities afforded
      by such a system. As we are training out users and show them the
      benefits of reconfigurability, the are becoming increasingly excited and
      have started to use reconfigurability in their applications.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Multi-threading</title>

    <para>On technique used extensively in the VR Juggler implementation is
    multi-threading. This section describes how multi-threading helps to
    increase the performance of VR Juggler and also to simplify the design of
    the system.</para>

    <para>VR systems can make use of multiple threads to increase performance.
    In many instances, this is actually the only way to achieve high
    performance. VR applications have to deal with numerous input and output
    devices in addition to whatever simulation and processing is executed by
    the application. If each of these tasks is executed sequentially, then the
    system performance will suffer because the performance will be limited by
    the completion time of the slowest operation[#Bryson successful
    design].</para>

    <para>To avoid this problem, several current VR development environments
    decouple each of the tasks so that each operation can execute individually
    without incurring delay by waiting for other operations[#Shaw decoupled
    1993][#CAVE Cruz thesis]. Each task can be viewed as separate component
    that executes relatively independently of the other components. The system
    core is responsible for making sure that the components are synchronized
    when needed. This allows the application to run as fast as possible
    because, the display may be able to run at 60hz while the tracking system
    runs at 50hz and a haptic controller runs at 500hz. If the devices were
    not in separate threads, they would have to run at least as slow as the
    slowest device, and would actually run slower because they would have to
    wait for all devices.</para>

    <para>It is worth noting that multi-threading the VR software system
    increases performance even if there are not multiple processors available.
    In the case where there is a single CPU, multi-threading still increases
    performance because when one thread is blocked waiting for a system
    resource, another thread can execute the operations that it needs
    to.</para>

    <para>The multi-threaded architecture also simplifies the architecture
    greatly. In a multi-threaded architecture is possible to have many small
    modules executing small amounts of specific code with a well defined
    function instead of having a small number of monolithic code segments that
    try to handle everything.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How does everything get started?</title>

    <para>The VR Juggler system is started separately from the actually
    application. To load the system, a boot loader process instantiates the
    kernel and gives it a new thread to start running. The kernel then
    initializes the system and waits for an application to be handed to it or
    for configuration data is passed to it.</para>

    <example id="KernelStartupCode.example">
      <title>Kernel Startup</title>

      <programlisting>...
// Start the kernel
vjKernel* kernel = vjKernel::instance();
kernel-&gt;start();
.
.
.
// Instantiate application. Set application
wandApp* application = new wandApp(kernel);
kernel-&gt;setApplication(application);
...</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>An application is given to the kernel at a later time through the
    kernel interface. Once the kernel has an application, it begins executing
    application methods within the kernel execution frame. The application can
    be given to the kernel as a dynamic object or as an object allocate in the
    kernel boot loader code. In the case that object is allocate in the
    loader, a common main() function (see <xref
    linkend="KernelStartupCode.example" />) can hold both the kernel start
    code and the code to give the kernel the application.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>System interaction</title>

    <para>In order to better explain interaction within the VR Juggler
    architecture, we will now describe how the system starts up and loads a
    single OpenGL application (see <xref
    linkend="KernelStartupAndExecutionSequence.figure" />). In order to
    simplify the diagrams we will not go into the details of configuration, we
    also leave out some method invocations, and we do not deal with multiple
    application objects.</para>

    <para>The first step in starting the system is to initialize the kernel.
    This starts by giving the kernel a thread of control. This is done in a
    startup routines that instantiates the kernel object, and then activates
    it by executing the kernel method start() which creates a thread for the
    kernel. Once the kernel has been activated, the kernel then initializes
    each internal manager.</para>

    <para>The next step in startup is to create and initialize an application.
    First, an application object must be instantiated. Then the application
    object is given to the kernel to start executing. The first thing the
    kernel does with an application is to create the draw manager that the
    application needs. Once this is done, the kernel then executes the
    applications initialization methods and signals the draw manager to do the
    same.</para>

    <para>The final phase of a clean startup is to start the execution frame
    loop. When the kernel does not have an application object, it does not
    execute any parts of the execution frame that deal with application
    objects.</para>

    <para>The first step in the execution frame is to call the preFrame()
    method of the application to tell it that a frame is starting. Next the
    kernel triggers the draw manager to render. While the draw manager is
    rendering, the kernel calls the application intraFrame() method to allow
    for parallel processing of rendering and application processing. Next, the
    kernel synchronizes with the draw manager by invoking the blocking sync()
    method which will not return until rendering has been completed. The
    kernel then calls the application postSync() method to notify the
    application that the frame is done. Next, the kernel check for any
    reconfiguration requests. If there are requests, then the kernel
    reconfigures the virtual platform before continuing. The final step in the
    execution frame is to update all device data and compute the drawing
    projections for the next frame.</para>

    <figure float="1" id="KernelStartupAndExecutionSequence.figure">
      <title>Kernel startup and execution</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/FullKernelControlLoop.png" format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How well does VR Juggler meet the design goals?</title>

    <remark revisionflag="added">May move all this stuff to benefits section
    or something of the individual topics.</remark>

    <section>
      <title>Hardware abstraction</title>

      <para>Displays are abstracted to allow support for any VR device. The
      display manager uses a generic surface description that allows for any
      projection surface. Currently, we use VR Juggler with projection-based
      system such as the C2 or CAVE. It also has support for HMDs. By using a
      generic display description, we can configure an application to run on
      nearly any VR display device.</para>

      <para>For some types of display devices, it is necessary to change the
      way the application behaves. Currently we are investigating ways to
      allow application to change behavior depending on the type of the device
      the display is set for.</para>

      <para>Input is abstracted through proxies. The proxies provide the
      application with a uniform interface to all devices. The application
      developer never directly interacts with the physical devices, or the
      specific input classes that control them. New devices can quickly be
      added by deriving a new class to manage the new device. Once this class
      exists, applications can immediately begin to take advantage of
      it.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Run-time flexibility</title>

      <para>The proxy system gives VR Juggler much of its run-time
      flexibility. The physical device classes can be moved around, removed,
      restarted, or replaced without affecting the application. The proxies
      themselves remain the same, even when the underlying devices are
      changed.</para>

      <para>VjControl offers an easy-to-use interface for reconfiguring,
      restarting, and replacing devices and displays at run-time. This allows
      users to interactively reconfigure a VR system while an application is
      running. The ability to reconfigure at run-time increases the robustness
      of applications because it allows devices to fail without taking down
      the entire application.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Performance tuning</title>

      <remark>[Discuss current performance, get from Chris]</remark>

      <para>VR Juggler includes built-in performance monitoring capabilities.
      These include the ability to accumulate data about time spent by various
      processes, performance data for the underlying graphics hardware (as
      available), and measure tracker latency (the time between generation of
      tracker data and the display of data generated from the tracker data).
      VjControl can display the performance data at run-time or the
      performance data can be captured and analyzed later.</para>

      <para>The environment manager allows users to dynamically reconfigure
      the system at run-time in an attempt to optimize performance. When the
      user changes the VR system configuration, the performance effects will
      be immediately visible with the performance monitor.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Cross-platform</title>

      <para>VR Juggler is portable to all major platforms use for VR
      development. To maintain portability, all system specific needs (such as
      threads, shared memory, and synchronization) are encapsulated by
      abstract classes. The library only uses the abstract, uniform interface.
      This allows easy porting of the library to other platforms by replacing
      the system-specific classes derived from the abstract bases. Currently
      the library has support for SGI, Linux, and Windows NT.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Extensible</title>

      <para>The library allows extension without impacting the rest of the
      system or applications that have been previously written. Adding new
      devices of an already supported general type (such as new position
      inputs, or new displays) is simple and transparent to applications. This
      is because the library uses generic base class interfaces to interface
      with all objects in the system.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <appendix id="NeedsOfVRSystem.appendix">
    <title>Appendix: Needs of VR system</title>

    <para>A VR development environment must address several specific needs in
    order to successfully create VR applications. This section divides these
    requirements into five broad categories: performance, extensibility,
    flexibility, simplicity, and robustness. This chapter first gives an
    overview of each of these general categories then proceeds to enumerate
    and describe many specific requirements in each category.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Primary needs</title>

      <section>
        <title>Performance</title>

        <remark>[Pt: Performance is key because bad performance can cause
        disengagement from the application and cybersickness]</remark>

        <para>Performance is the key requirement of any VR system. VR
        applications are "user centered", therefore the physical comfort and
        experience of the user is of vital importance. As covered in the
        previous chapter, the experience of the user relies upon presenting an
        interactive and engaging environment. If the performance of the system
        is too low, the interactivity of the system becomes erratic and can
        lead to disengagement from the application that significantly degrades
        the experience of the user. Poor performance is not merely an
        inconvenience for the end user; performance problems can cause serious
        physical side effects including disorientation and motion sickness
        [#Kalawsky].</para>

        <remark>[Pt: Software system must strive for utmost
        performance]</remark>

        <para>Because of these potential problems, VR software requires the
        utmost in performance [#Zyda networked virtual environments].
        Effective immersive environments must maintain a high visual frame
        rate (15hz or better) and maximize the responsiveness of the system to
        user inputs [#Rory]. To achieve the best performance, VR systems
        should take advantage of all available resources on a system, such as
        processors and special graphics hardware. In addition, the development
        system itself should have as little application overhead as
        possible.</para>

        <remark>[Pt: Although current systems have good performance, they
        sacrifice other SE fundamentals]</remark>

        <para>Current VR software systems have been successful at achieving
        good performance. Unfortunately, many of these systems do so while
        neglecting several fundamental needs of a software system such as:
        reusability, extensibility, flexibility, portability, and robustness.
        In some cases, system developers sacrifice these needs in an attempt
        to increase performance by tying the software system as closely to the
        hardware as possible. Another reason that current systems may not
        implement these features is that it is much more difficult to design a
        system that supports these features. Since the primary focus of VR
        research to date has been hardware systems and not software systems,
        these types of features have not received the attention that they
        deserve in a VR software system. We believe that a high-performance VR
        software system does not need to sacrifice any of these features in
        order to maintain high performance. In addition, we believe that these
        features are vitally important for creating a long lasting standard VR
        software system.</para>

        <para>The next sections discuss some of the software architectural
        needs that are commonly overlooked.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Extensibility</title>

        <remark>[Pt: Extensibility is important to allow for application
        survivability]</remark>

        <para>Extensibility in a VR development environment allows user
        applications to survive technological changes of the future.
        Extensibility refers to the ability to add new features and extensions
        to a current software system. Extensibility is required because the
        hardware and software tools used for VR development change rapidly.
        Researchers are constantly creating new VR hardware devices that must
        be supported by development environments. The development environment
        should not require a programmer to re-write their application every
        time support for a new VR hardware device is added.</para>

        <para>If a development environment does not allow easy extension, then
        it becomes difficult for users to write applications that can survive
        into the future. To avoid rewriting applications for new hardware,
        application developers need the ability to write an application once
        and rely upon the VR development environment to support future
        hardware advances. Although it would be adequate to simply require
        users to re-compile to get support for new hardware, it is better if
        the users are not required to even re-compile. In order to avoid the
        need for re-compilation, a development environment must support
        dynamic extension.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Flexibility</title>

        <para>Extensibility of the software architecture is not enough. The
        software architecture must also be flexible enough to adapt to new
        requirements. Flexibility here refers to the ability of the system to
        adapt to the shifting configurations and changing requirements of a VR
        system. For example, the development environment must support multiple
        operating systems in addition to supporting many types of graphics
        software and hardware.</para>

        <para>Development environments should not require developers to
        rewrite an application for every type of VR system. Instead, the
        software should adjust itself to the local VR system and facilitate
        the execution of the user’s application. If the environment cannot
        adapt to new configurations, applications will be limited in the scope
        of their usefulness.</para>

        <para>In addition, the design of the system itself should not lock
        developers into writing only one given type of application. For
        example, the development environment must make it just as easy to
        write a passive architectural walk-through application as it is to
        create an interactive scientific visualization application. This
        requires a development environment that is not only flexible about
        what hardware it is running on, but is also flexible about what type
        of applications and toolkits are running within the software
        system.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Simplicity</title>

        <para>Although a VR system is inherently complex, a VR development
        system does not have to be. The complexity of VR systems has
        unnecessarily led to the expectation and acceptance of corresponding
        complexity in development environments. This software complexity
        limits the ability of on-technical users to develop VR
        applications.</para>

        <para>As more people begin using VR, system designers need to simplify
        development environments to allow for widespread application
        development by non-technical users. VR allows users from many fields
        to gain insight into their problems, but these users are not
        necessarily expert software developers. Because users may not have
        software expertise, a VR development environment should be as simple
        and easy to use as possible. They should not have to worry about the
        complexities of VR systems, but should instead be able to spend time
        creating innovative applications.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Robustness</title>

        <para>Before VR applications can completely escape the domain of
        research, applications will be required to run reliably. Many current
        VR development environments were developed in research labs that have
        contributed many innovations and continue to do so. The problem is
        that in a research lab a "good" program may only be required to be
        partially stable; crashing one out of five times is commonly
        considered acceptable. It is research after all, so if the application
        crashes occasionally, that is to be expected. Outside the research
        lab, users are not so forgiving.</para>

        <para>VR is beginning to enter the mainstream of corporate users.
        These users will make use of VR applications in their production
        environments, and will not settle for down time or sporadic behavior
        in an application. VR development environments need to consider this
        in order satisfy the rigid demands of corporate users.</para>

        <para>The next pages will look at each of these broad requirements of
        VR development environments in more detail.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Performance</title>

      <section>
        <title>Low latency</title>

        <para>Latency is defined as the total delay time between a user action
        and the system response [#Rory]. Latency can come from the data rate
        of input devices; the time spent processing input, running
        applications simulation, and rendering output; the time required for
        multiprocessor synchronization; the refresh rate of display devices;
        and cumulative transmission times [#Rory]. Delays in the system
        introduce the lag that causes latency in a VR environment.</para>

        <remark>[Insert diagram about system latency]</remark>

        <para>High system latency adversely affects engagement and presence in
        applications because it causes cur conflicts for the user. System lag
        causes cue conflicts because although the user may have made a change
        to the system state, the system may not have updated to that change
        yet. A commonly observed cue conflict occurs when the user moves their
        head but the tracker data has latency such that the image generator
        does not update the user’s view to the new position fast enough to
        fool the visual senses of the user. This effect can be very
        disorienting for the user and at best causes them to disengage from
        the application.</para>

        <para>Latency can also cause users to experience an uncomfortable side
        effect called cybersickness. Cybersickness consists of
        motion-sickness-like symptoms during the use of a virtual environment
        and residual effect afterwards [#Rory]. According to Rory, the effects
        may include nausea, disorientation, stomach awareness, fatigue, and
        headache. Motion sickness can also have after effects including
        postural instability, weakness, fatigue, and visual problems.</para>

        <para>Several theories exist about the cause(s) of cybersickness. The
        most commonly accepted theory attributes the phenomenon to cue
        conflicts such as visual cues without vestibular cues. Cue conflicts
        can be caused by purposely creating an environment that behaves in a
        way that is contrary to real-world behavior, or more commonly, the cue
        conflicts are caused by lags within the VR system being used.</para>

        <para>A development environment must reduce system latency in order
        for the system to be usable.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>High frame rate</title>

        <remark>[Talk in reference to frame of update: What is frame rate,
        what does it influence, what influences it?]</remark>

        <remark>[Use diagram to describe]</remark>

        <remark>[Key: update of application depends on response time]</remark>

        <remark>[Frame rates: global, user-loop, simulation]</remark>

        <remark>[Pt: If frame rate is low, then user loses interactive
        realling]</remark>

        <para>There are many potential areas in a VR software system where
        latency can be introduces. In order to reduce latency, the sources of
        the latency must be thoroughly understood. <xref
        linkend="FrameRateLatencyChart.figure" />shows a diagram that outlines
        the sources of latency is the system. The diagram shows the path of a
        single set of sampled input data. The effects of the data are traced
        through the system</para>

        <para>The diagram shows the number update "frames" of several system
        components. The input devices are running asynchronously to the rest
        of the system which is coordinating through the use of synchronization
        points during processing. The chart highlights the tracker data that
        is valid at the first synchronization point (at the end of display
        frame 1). The system then uses this input data to start the rendering
        and computation of the next interval. When this interval completes,
        the user can see a rendered display (display frame 3) that is has used
        the original tracker readings, but the display does not have any
        updates that are dependent upon computing a new application state from
        the input. Display updates of this type are not available until
        display frame 4.</para>

        <figure float="1" id="FrameRateLatencyChart.figure">
          <title>System frame rates</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/Thesis06.png" format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>There are several ways to measure the update rate of the
        application. Three of the most commonly used methods are shown at the
        top of the chart. The first of these is the visual frame rate. This is
        simply a measure of how long it takes for the application to render
        the graphics of a single frame. The second measurement is the input
        latency. This measures the time from an input device update until the
        environment outputs new sensory information to the user based upon
        this input. The third measurement outlined is the latency when there
        is a computation that has to be performed upon the input data. Each of
        these measurements must be taken into account when measuring the
        performance of a VR application.</para>

        <para>The amount of interactivity and engagement in an application
        depends on the response time of the application. If the application
        responds quickly to user input, then the user has a feeling that they
        are directly influencing the application. If the application responds
        slowly to the user’s input, then the user loses the feeling of
        interactivity and instead they start using non-interactive interaction
        methods. Within a VR software system, these response times are
        measured in terms of frame rates and latencies.</para>

        <remark>[Pt: What is frame rate?]</remark>

        <remark>[Pt: What does diagram mean?]</remark>

        <para>Because interactivity is so important to system success,
        developers constantly strive to reduce system lag thus increasing
        perceived interactivity. The simplest way to detect lag in a system is
        to observe low rendering frame rate. Because of this, applications
        developers spend much time trying to increase the visual frame rate.
        Visual frame rate is not the only factor to decreasing lag though.
        There are many other factors that influence the user-loop frame rate.
        A development environment should help the developer to tune the system
        for a high frame rate.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Support for hardware</title>

        <remark>[Pt: System performance can increase by making use of custom
        hardware]</remark>

        <para>Modern hardware systems have many special features that a VR
        application can use to dramatically increase performance. However,
        explicitly making use of custom hardware can make applications
        hardware specific. If possible, a VR development environment needs to
        transparently take advantage of any special abilities of the hardware.
        If it is not possible to transparently use the features, the
        development environment should still allow the developer to use a
        direct interface on their own even if it will make the application
        platform specific.</para>

        <remark>[Pt: VR dev envs can be high-level or low-level]</remark>

        <para>VR development environments differ widely in the interfaces
        provided for creating an application. Some provide a very high-level
        view, where users create applications with custom scripting languages
        and graphical tools, and the system itself takes on most of the
        responsibility of simulation, geometry, and interaction. Other
        interfaces float just above the hardware level, using well-known
        graphics APIs and programming languages to ensure the greatest
        performance. Often, the higher-level tools will enable faster
        development with a shallower learning curve. The other side of the
        argument is, "If you want something done right, do it yourself." The
        more one of these systems is willing to do by itself, the more likely
        it is that it will do something unwanted, or do it in a way that is
        not optimal for a particular application. The key to balancing this
        trade off is to make application development as easy as possible, but
        all the developer enough flexibility to use whatever optimizations
        they need.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Performance monitoring</title>

        <para>Because performance is so critical to the success of a VR
        application, development environments need to provide a way to collect
        performance analysis information. In a VR application, there are many
        potential areas for performance problems; the tracking system may be
        running to slowly, the device updates may be taking to much processing
        overhead, the graphics may be taking longer than normal to render, the
        simulation code may be using too much processing time. Performance
        monitoring allows developers and end users at production sites to
        quickly zero in on the source of performance problems.</para>

        <para>Developers can use the collected performance information to find
        bottlenecks in their application code. According to Barry Boehm,
        applications spend 80% of their time in 20% of the code [#code
        complete]. This may actually be an understatement; Donald Knuth has
        found that less than 4% of a program accounts for 50% of run-time, and
        others have found that 90% of code accounts for 10% or run-time. This
        author has found the 90/10 rule to be an accurate estimate. In any
        case, the key to good application performance is finding the 10% that
        is performing badly and optimizing it. In a multi-threaded system, it
        becomes even more important to have support from the development
        environment for performance monitoring because many times a
        performance problem can be related to synchronization issues in a
        system. For example, the user may be executing simulation code while
        the rest of the system is waiting for the user thread. This
        application may be able to increase performance by moving the code to
        a parallel section of the application. Standard profiling techniques
        have difficulty showing this type of performance problem because the
        tools do not have the knowledge of the software system that the
        development environment does.</para>

        <para>The performance information can also be used to find and
        alleviate performance problems with a specific VR system’s
        configuration. Often small changes in configuration options can have a
        dramatic impact on the performance of applications in a given VR
        system. For example, it may be possible to tweak the configuration of
        graphics windows in a way that achieves a higher visual frame rate.
        This type of configuration tuning can increase the performance of all
        applications that run in the local VR system.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Extensibility</title>

      <section>
        <title>Hardware abstraction</title>

        <remark>[Pt: Development environments should provide abstractions for
        devices. ]</remark>

        <para>In order to be usable, the VR development environment must
        provide support for the physical hardware devices in the local VR
        system, but almost as vital is how well the toolkit abstracts away the
        details of the low-level hardware interfaces. Do devices of the same
        type share the same interface, or are there specific APIs for each
        one? This comes into play when replacing hardware. For example: If an
        application has been using tracking system A, but a newer, better
        tracking system B becomes available, will the application have to be
        modified to take advantage of it? Preferably, the environment will
        support this with a change in a script or configuration file, without
        requiring any application re-coding.</para>

        <para>A well-designed hardware abstraction is very important. While a
        less generic interface might be better able to take advantage of a
        device’s unusual features, the generic interface makes the application
        more portable and easier to upgrade, maintain, and understand. While
        major changes, such as replacing a joystick with a glove, might
        require rethinking the user interface, smaller changes, like switching
        one tracking system for another or changing between models of HMDs,
        should not require changes to the VR application itself.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Simple extension</title>

        <remark>[Pt: Must support easy, simple extension]</remark>

        <para>The development environment should allow developers to easily
        extend the VR software system using simple programming interfaces.
        Users need to be able to extend the system when an application
        requires the use of customized interaction devices. For example, when
        creating a vehicle simulation application, it may be necessary to
        support a customized device that mimics the interaction methods of the
        vehicle being simulated. These devices commonly have non-standard
        hardware, which means the application developer needs to add a custom
        device driver to the VR system.</para>

        <para>In addition to being easy to extend, developer should be able to
        add support for the custom devices without possessing expertise about
        the internals of the rest of the VR software system. Instead, they
        should only need to know about a small subset of the system that they
        can use to add device support in a straightforward manner. By allowing
        developers to easily extend the system, the development environment is
        able to change and adapt quickly to new advances in VR systems.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Do not require application changes</title>

        <remark>[Pt: Extension should not require application to
        change.]</remark>

        <para>Extending the development environment’s functionality should not
        require any changes or rebuilding of current applications; extensions
        should be transparent to current applications. Current applications
        should be able to take advantage of the new extensions simply by
        changing the configuration parameters of the system. The configuration
        system parameterizes the settings of the VR system that is being used.
        This also means that an application compiled for use at one location’s
        VR system can be distributed to another location and run on the second
        VR system without requiring any changes to the application. Instead,
        the users only need to provide the configuration parameters for the
        new system.</para>

        <para>An extendable parameterized VR system leads to applications that
        have longer lifetimes. I have personally experienced applications that
        have been running perfectly fine for years, but then the VR system
        changes and requires an update to the development system. This in turn
        requires all applications to be re-compiled. This is fine as long as
        the source code is available, someone knows how to compile it, and
        someone has the time, knowledge, and tools to do so. In any other
        case, this task can range from difficult to impossible. In a
        production setting, this problem is worsened by the fact that any
        downtime is costing the company. This problem can be avoided entirely
        by designing the VR development environment to allow extensions to be
        transparent to the applications.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Flexibility</title>

      <section>
        <title>Scalability</title>

        <remark>[Different levels of equipment (processor, graphics)]</remark>

        <remark>[Different VR systems low⇓◊high: fishtank,◊full C6, bench (1
        screen) ◊ multi-screen]</remark>

        <remark>[Pt: The environment should run efficiently on any VR
        system]</remark>

        <para>Scalability refers to the ability of a development environment
        to be able to run on a wide variety of VR systems. A VR development
        environment should provide the scalability to run applications
        efficiently on any type of VR system, be it a simulator on a desktop
        PC or a high-end VR system like a CAVE. Scalable systems have the
        benefit of allowing developers to write an application once and run it
        in any environment.</para>

        <remark>[Pt: When systems are limited, scalability helps because it
        allows simulation]</remark>

        <para>A scalable system also eases application development when VR
        system resources are scarce. Most sites only have one large scale VR
        system that all developers share. A scalable development environment
        allows applications to be development on a desktop PCs or small VR
        systems. This means that applications developers can write and debug
        their applications without requiring access to the high-end target VR
        system. This idea is explored further below when discussion rapid
        prototyping using a simulator.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Cross-platform</title>

        <remark>[Pt: A good toolkit must provide for cross-platform
        development]</remark>

        <para>What happens if an application has twenty potential customers,
        but ten of them use Windows NT workstations the rest use Linux
        workstations, and the high-end VR system is running on Irix? Today’s
        VR systems make use of a wide variety of system architectures. To be
        widely accepted, a successful VR development environment must offer
        support for not one, but many platforms.</para>

        <para>A well-designed VR development should provide support from
        cross-platform development. It should hide platform-specific details
        well enough that porting an application between different platforms
        requires little or no change in the application. For toolkits that use
        their own data formats and scripting languages, it is often the case
        that no changes are necessary. On the other hand, toolkits where the
        developer writes his or her own code in a language like C++ are
        subject to all the usual headaches of porting source code.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Run-time changes</title>

        <remark>[Pt: VR development environments can benefit from run-time
        changes, and therefore should support it]</remark>

        <para>Most current virtual reality (VR) systems do not allow users to
        make run-time changes to modify initial settings. A user configures
        the system before running an application, and the configuration
        remains static for the duration of the application. For example, the
        initial settings specify how many projection surfaces to display and
        what type of tracking system to use. Each facet of the system is
        specific a priori. There is no way to modify these settings once the
        software system has started.</para>

        <para>This is because, most VR control software relies upon having all
        configuration information when the application starts. If the user
        needs to change a system setting, they have to shutdown the running
        application, change the configuration parameters, and then restart the
        application with the new parameters. They may have to repeat these
        steps many times to get the system into the correct
        configuration.</para>

        <para>Requiring static configurations limit the ability of a VR system
        to adapt and change to new requirements. A flexible reconfiguration
        system can provide benefits in many areas that make the system more
        flexible and robust. A brief overview of a few of these areas
        follows.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Setup</title>

          <remark>[pt: Runtime reconfig helps in configuring a new
          system]</remark>

          <para>Run-time reconfiguration can prove invaluable when setting up
          and configuring a new system. Reconfiguration allows users to change
          device configuration parameters while an application is running. For
          example, users can use this ability to interactively tweak tracker
          settings at run-time. A person setting up a system can run a
          calibration program that draws a coordinate axes at the position of
          a tracker. By using this visual feedback, a user can interactively
          test whether the offset and rotation parameters for the current
          tracking system have been configured correctly. This type of
          interactive testing is helpful in determining correct system
          settings.</para>

          <remark>[pt: Reconfiguration also allow for interactive
          configuration of displays]</remark>

          <para>Reconfiguration also permits display setting to change at
          run-time. This allows users to configure new projection surfaces
          while running test applications. For example, it is possible to
          interactively change the display settings of a projection
          environment at run-time.</para>

          <para>First, the user specifies an initial system configuration that
          may include information such as the tracking system used and any
          other information that they believe to be correct. This initial
          configuration also includes speculated settings for the display
          surfaces in the environment. The user then starts a test application
          in order to try the settings. Once the application is running, the
          user can then interactively change the settings of the active
          display surfaces, and even add new displays or remove current ones.
          They can change parameters such as the size, location, and a variety
          of other projection parameters, all while observing the result of
          the changes.</para>

          <remark>[pt: Allow use of physically changing devices]</remark>

          <para>Reconfigurable VR software systems also enable the use of
          advanced projection systems where the physical settings of the
          projection surface itself are changing at run-time. Examples of this
          type of system include desk-based systems with a movable projection
          surface and large scale CAVE-like devices that allow users to move
          the walls. Run-time reconfiguration allows users to reconfigure the
          desk projection surface while an application is running; or if a
          driver is available, the running system can actively monitor the
          desk’s current settings and automatically update the projection
          parameters to reflect any changes.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Software and hardware testing</title>

          <para>A reconfiguration VR system can also be very helpful when
          testing new software and hardware.</para>

          <remark>[Pt: Reconfig allows moving between many configurations
          rapidly]</remark>

          <para>Reconfiguration reduces the turn around time for testing
          multiple configurations while developing applications. Many times VR
          applications take a lengthy amount of time to load due either to
          loading large models or the time required to start input devices.
          When debugging an application, there is no reason to bring the
          application up in a full VR environment every time the program
          starts. Instead, a developer can start the application in a
          simulated environment to quickly test the program. If the
          application is working in the simulated environment, then instead of
          restarting it with new configuration information, run-time
          reconfiguration allows a user to simply change the configuration so
          that it is running in the full VR system.</para>

          <remark>[pt: Developers can test in many different configurations
          without stopping the application]</remark>

          <para>Developers can make use of this flexibility to test an
          application using many different VR system configurations. For
          example, it may be helpful to start the application first in a
          simulator, reconfigure it so that it is running with an HMD, and
          then reconfigure it again so that it is using a CAVE or some other
          large-scale projection environment. Applications can be tested in
          all of these environments without ever halting execution.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Performance tuning</title>

          <para>As touched upon above, performance tuning is very important in
          a VR software system. Run-time changes can be used to tune
          performance of VR applications. By analyzing the performance of a
          running application, and adjusting the current system configuration
          based upon these measurements, users can change a VR system
          configuration to achieve better performance. For example, device
          drivers could be moved to lightly loaded systems or have parameters
          changed in such a way that the driver requires less system
          resources. As another example, consider advance graphics
          architectures where it is possible to change the parameters of the
          graphics hardware. Users of run-time reconfiguration can exploit
          these abilities in order to find more optimal settings for the VR
          system’s graphics hardware.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Application adaptations</title>

          <para>Reconfiguration is not limited to only the VR system. VR
          applications can also take advantage of the abilities afforded by
          such a system. Since the VR system provides the infrastructure, it
          becomes much easier to write applications that are reconfigurable as
          well. Applications can allow for their parameters to be configured
          using the reconfiguration system.</para>

          <para>Runtime reconfiguration be used to change application specific
          parameters such as models loaded or interaction methods used. For
          example, an application can be written where the user can remotely
          change the model that is being viewed in the VR environment and the
          navigation method that is being used. Because the run-time
          reconfiguration system is being used to make these application
          changes, they can come from any entity be it a remote controlling
          interface, another application that is running, or the local
          application it self.</para>

          <para>In a VR system that allows for multiple simultaneous users in
          a single environment, run-time reconfiguration allows user to
          exchange control. An example would be an application that was not
          written with multiple users in mind. As such, the application would
          only expect to be controlled by one input device. Using run-time
          reconfiguration, the two users can exchange which user’s interaction
          device is active in the system.</para>

          <para>This same idea can be used to enable multiple tracked users to
          use an environment that only has support for a single tracked user
          at one time. In such an environment, the run-time reconfiguration
          system can be used to choose which tracked user is "active" and thus
          controlling the environment at any given time.[look for
          references]</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Support use of other application toolkits</title>

        <remark>[Pt: Allow developers to use best tools for the job]</remark>

        <para>A VR development environment should assist the user in creating
        the best VR application possible. As such, the development environment
        should allow the user to create the application using whatever tools
        are best suited for the problem domain of the application. If the user
        wants to create a scientific visualization application, then the
        development environment should allow them to use VTK or OpenDX [#VTK
        homepage][#OpenDX homepage]. If the developer wants to create a visual
        simulation application, the environment should allow the user to make
        use of the advanced features of Iris Performer. The environment should
        not restrict the developer by requiring the use of only one tool for
        all jobs because there will always be limits to what a single tool can
        do.</para>

        <remark>[Pt: Integrated tools are good to a point, then they become a
        hindrance]</remark>

        <para>Several current VR development environments include support for
        graphics and/or simulation in the core of the software system. For
        example, a system may include a scene graph that is specific to the
        development environment. This works well when the user’s application
        is suited for using the type of tools included in the development
        environment. The user can write the application using the integrated
        libraries and be assured that it will work on all platforms and with
        all hardware supported by the development environment. This can
        greatly eases the software development burden on the developer.
        However, when a user wants to create an application that is not
        supported well by the integrated tools, the development environment
        becomes restrictive.</para>

        <remark>[Pt: VR tool should not tie to an environment. This does not
        lose anything though]</remark>

        <para>What is needed is a VR development environment that easily
        supports a wide variety of other toolkits. The application developer
        can then choose which tool works best for the job and use it. The
        power and ease of use that comes from integrated tools does not need
        to be lost. It is still possible to create modules that have strong
        ties with many common toolkits in such a way that they work as well as
        a completely integrated tool would. However, by decoupling the
        development environment from a specific tool, it can be used in a
        wider variety of applications.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Do not be overly restrictive</title>

        <remark>[Pt. Don’t restrict the developers]</remark>

        <para>A VR development environment should have no restrictions that
        prevent a skilled user from implementing an advanced solution.
        Developers should never hit a wall where the development environment
        restricts them from creating an application that works the way they
        have envisioned it. For example, many development environments that
        allow the use of OpenGL, do so by using draw callbacks that are called
        once per OpenGL context by the software system. In order to keep the
        applications simple and to prevent new users from writing non-portable
        code, many of these systems do not explicitly get the user access to
        the current context id. An advanced user may need to use this context
        id to interact with OpenGL directly. The software system should not
        prevent the application from getting to this information. If it did,
        then it would be impossible for the user to interact directly with
        OpenGL.</para>

        <para>While simplicity is valuable, the software should not be so
        restrictive as to prevent the implementation of advanced techniques.
        The environment should not require the use of an overly-restrictive
        program structure, nor should it place an impenetrable barrier between
        the developer and the computer system – there should be a way to go
        outside of the environment, and access the operating system or
        hardware directly, when that is required.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Simplicity</title>

      <section>
        <title>Short learning curve</title>

        <remark>[Pt: Don’t require developers to know everything in order to
        write simple applications]</remark>

        <para>A VR development environment makes use of many complex software
        concepts including: multi-processor programming, components, run-time
        loading, and run-time reconfiguration. A new developer should not have
        to know how to use these concepts to write simple applications that
        solve their problems. VR systems are complex, but application
        development does not need to be.</para>

        <remark>[Pt: Small simple interface for most users]</remark>

        <para>A VR development environment should provide a small and simple
        interface that makes basic functionality available. By using a simple
        interface, the environment does not require users to understand the
        entire. Instead, the developer only needs to understand the basics of
        a small portion of the system. To further ease learning, the
        development environment can provide sample applications and re-usable
        application components that developers can use to rapidly create new
        applications.</para>

        <para>By simplifying the development environment, VR application
        development becomes more accessible to a wide number of users.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Rapid prototyping using simulation</title>

        <remark>[Pt: Provide an accurate simulation of a VR system that can be
        used on desktop machines to develop applications. Because... high-end
        VR systems are limited and take to long to use.]</remark>

        <para>Since most development groups only have access to a few VR
        systems, it is important to be able to run an application and interact
        with it without requiring access to the entire VR system. If
        developers have to wait for VR hardware, they will waste time waiting
        for their turn to use the equipment. Additionally, while debugging
        applications it is overly burdensome to use a full VR system. Many
        times, it is much faster and easier to debug applications on desktop
        machines. On a desktop machine, there is no worry about devices
        loading, projectors synchronizing, or other people needing to use the
        system. Instead, a developer can focus on writing the application and
        fixing any bugs that pop up.</para>

        <para>To allow developers to quickly prototype an application, a
        development environment should include a simulator environment that
        accurately imitates a full VR system. This generally involves drawing
        the display in a window on a monitor and using the keyboard and mouse
        to simulate head tracking and any other input devices. A correct
        simulator also must replicate the underlying system behavior of a full
        VR system. This includes accurately reproducing the program conditions
        that will occur in the full environment such as: multi-processing,
        shared memory, etc. The simulator must also model restrictions that
        the user will encounter in the real world VR system such as:
        restrictions on device ranges, collision with projection screens and
        walls, etc. The more accurate the simulator, the less time the
        developer has to spend making the application work in the physical VR
        system.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Robustness</title>

      <section>
        <title>Failure protection</title>

        <remark>[Main Pt: If one part fails, the entire system does not have
        to fail]</remark>

        <remark>[Pt: Failure happens]</remark>

        <para>Application developers need a robust platform to run VR
        applications. When running on a modern operating systems, a single
        process failing does not bring down the entire system. A VR system
        should behave in much the same way. A single component failure should
        not result in the entire VR system crashing. With a system as large
        and complex as a VR system, components are bound to fail or break. A
        tracker may be unstable, a cable may be loose, or the driver software
        may just be buggy. However, just because a single component has
        problems does not mean that it should affect the entire system.</para>

        <remark>[Pt: Separate the system to protect it from failure]</remark>

        <para>The key to protecting the system from a single component failure
        is to keep the components of a system separated so that the interface
        between components can shield the components from failures. The
        interfaces can then provide a layer of protection between all the
        components. For example, the system may give a "smart" handle to an
        input device. The application uses this handle to reference a device
        instead of using a direct reference. In this way, the system can
        protect the resource by placing failure detection logic in the handle
        such that the handle will never return a reference to an invalid
        device. The application itself can protect itself in this way by using
        an application harness to separate the application from the VR
        software system.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Maintainability and correctness</title>

        <remark>[Add references]</remark>

        <para>VR systems are complex and as such, VR development environments
        are large and complex software systems. As with any large software
        system maintenance and correctness become important issues. How can we
        design a VR development environment so that is maintainable into the
        future? How do developers test for correctness in a large VR
        development environment?</para>

        <remark>[Pt: A modular system is easier to maintain]</remark>

        <para>Maintenance presents a problem in a large system because of
        inter dependencies within the software system. In a complex system, it
        is very difficult to completely understand every part of the system.
        If system components are highly intertwined, changes in one component
        could affect the correctness of another component. These dependencies
        are often very difficult to predict and take into account.</para>

        <para>Maintenance is simplified by breaking the system up into many
        separate self-contained code modules. Each of these modules presents a
        single interface that can be accessed by other modules in the system.
        By breaking the system up into small elements, it is possible for
        system designers to make changes within a module without affecting
        code outside the module.</para>

        <remark>[Pt: A modular system is easier to test for
        correctness]</remark>

        <para>Testing correctness in a large system is important because you
        need some level of confidence that the system will work. A common way
        to manage this is to separate the major system components into
        separate entities that can be individually tested and verified. The
        idea is that if a system is made up of many components and each of
        these components individual works correctly then, the combined system
        will work correctly (assuming the linking code works correctly). To
        test such a system, the components should be tested at many levels of
        granularity. For example in an object-oriented system you may want to
        test at object, module, and sub-system levels.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </appendix>
</article>