<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>VR Juggler</title>

    <subtitle>Getting Started Guide</subtitle>

    <copyright>
      <year>2001–2005</year>

      <holder>Iowa State University</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      the Invariant Sections being <xref linkend="appendix.gfdl" />, with no
      Front-Cover Texts, and with no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license
      is included in <xref linkend="appendix.gfdl" />.</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <releaseinfo>Version 2.0</releaseinfo>

    <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
  </bookinfo>

  <preface>
    <title>Preface</title>

    <para>This book is for people who are just getting started with VR
    Juggler. It guides new users through getting and installing VR Juggler,
    configuring users' environment to use it, and compiling and running a
    sample application.</para>

    <para>The prerequisites for reading this book are minimal. They
    are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Some experience with a command-line interface (i.e., a shell
        such as tcsh or the DOS shell)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Creating and browsing directories</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Those users who want to get more involved with VR Juggler to do more
    than just run applications should be aware right away of the following
    prerequisites:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Knowledge of C++ and object-oriented design</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Knowledge of one of VR Juggler's currently supported graphics
        APIs (<ulink url="http://www.opengl.org/">OpenGL</ulink>, <ulink
        url="http://www.sgi.com/software/performer/">OpenGL Performer</ulink>,
        <ulink url="http://www.opensg.org/">OpenSG</ulink>, or <ulink
        url="http://www.openscenegraph.org/">Open Scene Graph</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </preface>

  <chapter id="chapter.vrj.install">
    <title>Installing VR Juggler</title>

    <para>As with most Open Source projects, VR Juggler is distributed as
    compressed archive files using popular formats. Installing a distribution
    requires very little effort, but you do need to know how to use archiving
    utilities to extract the installation tree. Automation of the installation
    is a goal of the VR Juggler team, but we are still finalizing the details
    of cross-platform installation management. Before reading further, you
    should know where you want to install VR Juggler, and you should make sure
    that you have access to write to that directory.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Installing from a Compressed TAR File</title>

      <para>The TAR (Tape ARchive) format has been around for a long, long
      time in the UNIX world. It is simply a collection of files in a
      directory tree that are lumped into a single file suitable for writing
      to a tape or for downloading. The format is a standard, and the
      <command>tar</command>(1) utility is available on every UNIX-based
      platform and on Win32. A free version can be downloaded from <ulink
      url="http://www.gnu.org/">the GNU Project</ulink>. A compressed TAR file
      is made for each VR Juggler distribution, and some distributions come in
      other formats as well. You can always count on the availability of a TAR
      file, though. The TAR files are compressed using either GZIP or BZIP2,
      both of which are standard compression formats. The
      <command>gzip</command>(1) utility is freely available from the GNU
      Project, and the <command>bzip2</command>(1) utility can be downloaded
      for free from <ulink url="http://sources.redhat.com/bzip2/">RedHat,
      Inc.</ulink>. The GNU version of TAR has the GZIP and BZIP2 algorithms
      built in. The compression algorithm used can be determined by the file
      extension. Files compressed with GZIP end in <filename>.gz</filename>;
      files compressed with BZIP2 end in <filename>.bz2</filename>.</para>

      <para>Once you have downloaded a VR Juggler TAR distribution, you can
      unpack it one of two ways depending on what your platform's version of
      TAR supports. Before extracting the installation tree, make sure that
      your current directory is the one where you want to install VR Juggler.
      If your version of TAR does not have GZIP built in (it does not support
      the <option>-z</option> option), the following command will do the
      decompression and extraction:</para>

      <screen>% gzip -cd vrjuggler-distribution.tar.gz | tar -xvf -</screen>

      <para>For versions of TAR without built-in BZIP2 support (there is no
      <option>-j</option> option) the command is similar:</para>

      <screen>% bzip2 -cd vrjuggler-distribution.tar.bz2 | tar -xvf -</screen>

      <para>Here, you should fill in
      <filename>vrjuggler-distribution.tar.gz</filename> (or
      <filename>vrjuggler-distribution.tar.bz2</filename>) with the name of
      the VR Juggler distribution file you downloaded. The above commands will
      work with any shell that supports redirection of standard output to a
      pipe. If that looks too scary, you can separate the decompression and
      extraction into two commands (for GZIP):</para>

      <screen>% gunzip vrjuggler-distribution.tar.gz
% tar -xvf vrjuggler-distribution.tar</screen>

      <para>or for BZIP2:</para>

      <screen>% bunzip2 vrjuggler-distribution.tar.bz2
% tar -xvf vrjuggler-distribution.tar</screen>

      <para>Note that the distribution file in the second command does not
      have the <filename>.gz</filename> extension after
      <command>gzip</command>(1) is run. These steps also work if your version
      of <command>tar</command>(1) supports the <option>-z</option> option
      (<option>-j</option> for BZIP2), but you can simplify your work if that
      option is supported. The following illustrates how to decompress and
      extract a TAR file compressed with GZIP all in one step:</para>

      <screen>% tar -xzvf vrjuggler-distribution.tar.gz</screen>

      <para>The following would be used for a TAR file compressed with
      BZIP2:</para>

      <screen>% tar -xjvf vrjuggler-distribution.tar.bz2</screen>

      <para>In either case, while the command runs, you will see the name of
      each file as it is written to disk. This is because of the
      <option>-v</option> option to <command>tar</command>(1) that tells it to
      be verbose in its efforts. <command>tar</command>(1) takes care of
      creating all the directories in the installation tree, so you only need
      to have the base directory (for example,
      <filename>/usr/local</filename>) when you start. For more information
      about these utilities, please refer to the <command>tar</command>(1) and
      <command>gzip</command>(1) manual pages.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installing from a ZIP File (Win32 only)</title>

      <para>On the Win32 family of platforms, the ZIP format rules. In the old
      days, you would use the PKZIP utility to uncompress and extract a ZIP
      file. Nowadays, most people use <ulink
      url="http://www.winzip.com/">WinZip</ulink> or some other comparable
      graphical interface. This documentation covers only the use of WinZip
      when extracting a ZIP file.</para>

      <para>Once you have downloaded the VR Juggler ZIP file, the easiest way
      to extract it is to double-click on its icon in the open folder window
      as shown in <xref linkend="figure.windows.temp.folder.view" />.</para>

      <figure id="figure.windows.temp.folder.view">
        <title>Windows Folder View of ZIP File</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/Window.Download.png"
                       format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Double-clicking opens the main WinZip window, as shown in <xref
      linkend="figure.winzip.main" />.</para>

      <figure id="figure.winzip.main">
        <title>Open WinZip Window</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/Window.WinZip.png"
                       format="PNG" scalefit="1" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Note that in this screen shot, the <guibutton>Extract</guibutton>
      button is highlighted. Click this button to open the following window.
      Note that in this screen shot, the <guibutton>Extract</guibutton> button
      is highlighted. Click this button to open the dialog box shown in <xref
      linkend="figure.winzip.extract" />.</para>

      <figure id="figure.winzip.extract">
        <title>WinZip Extract Dialog</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="figures/Window.WinZip.Extract.png"
                       format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>In this window, choose the directory where VR Juggler will be
      installed and click <guibutton>Extract</guibutton>. WinZip will then
      proceed to extract the ZIP file into the directory you named. That is
      all there is to it.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installing from a Disk Image (Mac OS X only)</title>

      <para>The preferred Internet distribution format for Mac OS X is the
      disk image (file extension <filename>.dmg</filename>). Double-clicking
      on the <filename>.dmg</filename> file mounts the disk image which can
      then be opened. Pre-compiled versions of VR Juggler for Mac OS X are
      distributed in this manner. Within the mounted disk image, there is an
      installer program for the VR Juggler release (file extension
      <filename>.pkg</filename>)<footnote>
          <para>Unfortunately, the complexity of VR Juggler prevents it from
          being installed using the preferred drag-and-drop method.</para>
        </footnote>.</para>

      <important>
        <para>Before installing, read any HTML files included with the VR
        Juggler distribution. These will contain relevant information about
        updating an existing VR Juggler installation or how to use the VR
        Juggler installer that is not covered here.</para>
      </important>

      <para>Double-clicking on the VR Juggler installer will install VR
      Juggler. The VR Juggler libraries will be installed to
      <filename>/usr/local</filename>, and the dependencies will be installed
      to <filename>/usr/local/vrjuggler-deps</filename>. The application
      bundles for the Tweek Java GUI and <application>VRJConfig</application>
      will be installed to <filename>/Applications</filename>. Finally, the
      file <filename>~/.MacOSX/environment.plist</filename> will be updated to
      set the VR Juggler-related environment variables (see <xref
      linkend="chapter.envvar" />).</para>

      <note>
        <para>The application bundles for the Tweek Java GUI and
        <application>VRJConfig</application> are still in the early stages of
        development. For convenience, the command line versions of these
        applications are also installed. Running <command>tweek</command> or
        <command>vrjconfig</command> from a terminal window will start those
        applications just as would be done on other operating systems. At some
        point, the command line verrsions of these applications will probably
        be removed on Mac OS X in favor of exclusive use of the application
        bundles.</para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="chapter.envvar">
    <title>Environment Variables</title>

    <para>There are several <firstterm>environment variables</firstterm> that
    affect the way VR Juggler works. Some of these are required to compile and
    run applications while others are optional. This chapter lists all such
    variables and explains their meanings and uses.</para>

    <section>
      <title>How to Set Environment Variables</title>

      <para>The syntax for setting or changing an environment variable varies
      with operating systems and shell interpreters. Instead of choosing one
      style of syntax that is specific to a particular shell type, we define
      our own syntax which you must then translate to your shell's specific
      syntax. Before defining this syntax, we present the method used to set
      environment variables in the three most common types of shells. We also
      provide a quick overview of how to set environment variables using
      Win32-based GUIs.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Common Conventions and Background</title>

        <para>A convention used throughout this book is to name the variables
        using all capital letters. In almost all cases, regardless of the
        shell, this is the naming convention used for environment
        variables.</para>

        <para>Setting a path with an environment variable can require special
        syntax. Because of this, the method for doing so may vary from shell
        to shell. Paths are important with VR Juggler when looking up the path
        to a shared library (dynamically linked library). For each shell, the
        syntax for setting a path is given.</para>

        <para>Referring to environment variables can also vary from shell to
        shell. An example of how to print the value of an environment variable
        will be given for each shell. An example of how to refer to an
        environment variable is also provided as these two operations may vary
        even within one kind of shell!</para>

        <para>In all shells, an environment variable is only available within
        that single shell instance. That is, setting an environment variable
        at a command prompt only affects that specific shell and will not be
        available from other concurrent or future shells. To make a setting
        <quote>permanent</quote>, it should be done in file read by all shell
        instances when they are started. This is addressed briefly as
        appropriate for each shell type.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="section.envvar.csh">
        <title>C-Style Shells (csh, tcsh)</title>

        <para>In a C-style shell (i.e., one whose interface is based on the C
        programming language), setting environment variables is done using the
        built-in command <command>setenv</command>. It is used as
        follows:</para>

        <screen>% setenv &lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt; &lt;value&gt;</screen>

        <para>where the string <literal>&lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;</literal>
        represents the name of the variable you are going to set and
        <literal>&lt;value&gt;</literal> represents the value assigned to that
        variable. Both are required. If the named variable did not exist
        before, it will pop into existence. Otherwise, you overwrite the old
        setting with the new one.</para>

        <para>To print the value of an environment variable, use the following
        command:</para>

        <screen>% printenv &lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;</screen>

        <para>Referring to a variable, however, is done using the following
        syntax:</para>

        <screen>% cd $VARIABLE_NAME/bin</screen>

        <para>Paths are specified as a colon-separated list. An example of
        this is:</para>

        <screen>% printenv PATH
/bin:/sbin:/usr/bin:/usr/sbin</screen>

        <para>For these types of shells, a <quote>permanent</quote> setting
        for a given variable should usually be done in your .cshrc file or in
        your <filename>.login</filename> file, both of which should be in your
        home directory. In most cases, it is better to use
        <filename>.cshrc</filename> because it is evaluated for every shell
        instance.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="section.envvar.sh">
        <title>sh-Derived Shells (sh, ksh, bash, zsh, etc.)</title>

        <para>In a shell based on sh, setting environment variables is done
        using the built-in command <command>export</command>. It is used as
        follows:</para>

        <screen>% export &lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;=&lt;value&gt;</screen>

        <para>or</para>

        <screen>% &lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;=&lt;value&gt;
% export &lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;</screen>

        <para>Here, the string <literal>&lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;</literal>
        represents the name of the variable you are going to set and
        <literal>&lt;value&gt;</literal> represents the value assigned to that
        variable. Both are required. Note that there is no space between the
        variable name and its value. If the named variable did not exist
        before, it will pop into existence. Otherwise, you overwrite the old
        setting with the new one. If the variable was already among your
        current shell's environment variables, the export command is not
        necessary.</para>

        <para>To print the value of an environment variable, use the following
        command:</para>

        <screen>% echo $VARIABLE_NAME</screen>

        <para>Getting the value of a variable works the same way.</para>

        <para>Paths are specified as a colon-separated list. An example of
        this is:</para>

        <screen>% echo $PATH
/bin:/sbin:/usr/bin:/usr/sbin</screen>

        <para>For these types of shells, a <quote>permanent</quote> setting
        for a given variable should usually be done in the
        <filename>.profile</filename> file in your home directory or in your
        shell's <quote>rc</quote> file. Different shells have different names
        for this file. Examples are <filename>.bashrc</filename> for BASH and
        <filename>.zshrc</filename> for Zsh. Please refer to your shell's
        documentation for more information. In any case, the file will be in
        your home directory.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="section.envvar.dos">
        <title>DOS Shell</title>

        <para>The typical syntax for setting an environment variable from the
        command line (in a DOS shell window) under Win32 is:</para>

        <screen>C:\&gt; set &lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;=&lt;value&gt;</screen>

        <para>Here, <literal>&lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;</literal> is the name of
        the environment variable to be set, and
        <literal>&lt;value&gt;</literal> is the value being assigned to that
        variable. If the named variable did not exist before, it will pop into
        existence. Otherwise, you overwrite the old setting with the new
        one.</para>

        <para>To print the value of an environment variable, use the following
        command:</para>

        <screen>C:\&gt; set &lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt;</screen>

        <para>Referring to a variable, however, is done using the following
        syntax:</para>

        <screen>C:\&gt; cd %VARIABLE_NAME%\bin</screen>

        <para>Paths are specified as a semicolon-separated list. An example of
        this is:</para>

        <screen>C:\&gt; set PATH
C:\WINDOWS;C:\bin;C:\</screen>

        <para>For some versions of Windows, a <quote>permanent</quote> setting
        for a given variable should usually be done in
        <filename>C:\AUTOEXEC.BAT</filename>. In newer versions (Windows ME in
        particular) and in the Windows NT line of operating systems, the
        setting is done using the Control Panel. Please refer to the next
        section for more information on that method.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Win 32 GUI</title>

        <para>Before reading this section, please be sure to have read <xref
        linkend="section.envvar.dos" />. This is necessary because the Win32
        GUI for setting environment variables is simply a front-end to that
        older method and thus uses the same conventions and syntax. The
        versions of Windows to which this subsection applies are indicated
        individually since each is a little different. For more detailed
        information, please refer to the Windows online help system and search
        for <quote>environment variables</quote>.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Windows 2000 and Windows XP</title>

          <para>In the Control Panel, open the <guiicon>System</guiicon> icon.
          Under the <guilabel>Advanced</guilabel> tab, there is a button
          labeled <guibutton>Environment Variables</guibutton>, shown in <xref
          linkend="figure.win2k.sysprops" /> (the Windows XP version is shown
          in <xref linkend="figure.winxp.sysprops" />). Clicking this button
          opens the dialog box shown in <xref
          linkend="figure.win2k.envvars" />. Here, you can set variables for
          yourself and, if you have the access privileges, for all
          users.</para>

          <figure id="figure.win2k.sysprops">
            <title>Windows 2000 System Properties Dialog</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center"
                           fileref="figures/Window.SystemProperties.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <figure id="figure.winxp.sysprops">
            <title>Windows XP System Properties Dialog</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center"
                           fileref="figures/Window.SystemProperties.winxp.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <figure id="figure.win2k.envvars">
            <title>Windows Environment Variable Editor Dialog</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center"
                           fileref="figures/Window.EnvironmentVariables.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>To set up VR Juggler, the environment variable
          <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> needs to be set, probably for all users,
          though it depends very much on local system requirements. For this
          example, let us say that the Win32 version of VR Juggler is
          installed in the <filename>D:\</filename> directory. As such, we
          will set <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> as shown in <xref
          linkend="figure.win2k.envvar.set" />. <envar>VJ_DEPS_DIR</envar> is
          set similarly.</para>

          <figure id="figure.win2k.envvar.set">
            <title>Setting <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> on Windows</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center"
                           fileref="figures/Window.EnvironmentVariables.VJ_BASE_DIR.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Windows NT 4.0</title>

          <para>In the Control Panel, open the <guiicon>System</guiicon> icon.
          The window that is opened has a tab labeled <guilabel>Environment
          Variables</guilabel>. Here, you can set variables for yourself and,
          if you have the access privileges, for all users. The GUI is similar
          to that shown above for Windows 2000.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Mac OS X</title>

        <para>On Mac OS X, environment variables can be set in two different
        ways, just as on Windows. They can be set as <quote>global</quote>
        environment variables available to all applications launched from the
        Finder, or they can be set within a Terminal window for use within
        that shell and by all applications launched from that shell. Refer to
        Apple's Technical Q&amp;A <ulink
        url="http://developer.apple.com/qa/qa2001/qa1067.html">QA1067</ulink>
        document for details on how to set global environment variables for
        use by the Mac OS X desktop interface. To set an environment variable
        within a Terminal window, refer to either <xref
        linkend="section.envvar.csh" /> or <xref
        linkend="section.envvar.sh" /> depending on the user's chosen shell
        (the default is tcsh).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Syntax Used in this Document</title>

        <para>To avoid tying this documentation to a single style of
        environment variable creation, assignment and reference, the following
        syntax will be used exclusively from this point onward. Please read
        this carefully before proceeding.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Naming Environment Variables</title>

          <para>When naming an environment variable in the plain text of this
          document, the variable will be referred to by its name only. For
          example, to talk about the environment variable containing your
          path, we will talk about it as <envar>PATH</envar>.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Creating/Setting Environment Variables</title>

          <para>The syntax to set an environment variable is:</para>

          <screen>% &lt;VARIABLE_NAME&gt; = &lt;value&gt;</screen>

          <para>Setting an environment variable also creates it if it is not
          already present in the current shell's environment.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Printing an the Value of an Environment Variable</title>

          <para>Printing an environment variable's value to standard output
          (stdout) is done as follows:</para>

          <screen>% echo $VARIABLE_NAME
value</screen>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Referring to the Value of an Environment Variable</title>

          <para>To get the value of an environment variable when it needs to
          be expanded, the following syntax will be used:</para>

          <screen>% cd $VARIABLE_NAME/bin</screen>

          <para>Here, the reference to the value is
          <envar>$VARIABLE_NAME</envar>.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="section.envvars.required">
      <title>Required Environment Variables</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>VJ_BASE_DIR</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The environment variable <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> tells a
            VR Juggler application where to find important data files. It is
            required to compile and run any Juggler application. It should be
            set to the base directory of the installed VR Juggler library. For
            example, if you downloaded a UNIX version of VR Juggler 2.0 and
            extracted it to the directory <filename>/home/software</filename>,
            you would set <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> with this command:</para>

            <screen>% VJ_BASE_DIR = /home/software/vrjuggler-2.0</screen>

            <para>The last component of the path depends on the particular
            version of Juggler you have downloaded.</para>

            <para>If you downloaded and built VR Juggler from the source code,
            the compilation creates a directory called
            <filename>instlinks</filename> which can be used as a VR Juggler
            base:</para>

            <screen>% VJ_BASE_DIR = $HOME/juggler/my_build_dir/instlinks</screen>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>VJ_DEPS_DIR</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This variable provides the path to the complete set of
            bundled VR Juggler dependencies (Boost, CppDOM, OpenAL, etc.). It
            is used by scripts such as <command>vrjuggler-config</command> and
            by the Visual C++ project files that come with the sample
            applications. If you downloaded the dependencies as a separate
            package, set this environment variable to the path where that
            package was installed. If the dependencies are bundled in the same
            tree as VR Juggler, then this environment variable does not have
            to be set.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>PATH</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>To compile any of the sample applications, the
            <envar>$VJ_BASE_DIR/bin</envar> directory must be added to your
            <envar>PATH</envar> as follows:</para>

            <screen>% PATH = $PATH:$VJ_BASE_DIR/bin</screen>

            <para>Depending on your shell, you may need to run the
            <command>rehash</command> command after executing the
            above.</para>

            <para>Windows users must also include the directories
            <filename>$VJ_DEPS_DIR/bin</filename>,
            <filename>$VJ_DEPS_DIR/lib</filename>, and
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/lib</filename> in their <envar>PATH</envar>
            setting. This is so that the DLLs for VR Juggler and its
            dependencies will be found when an application is executed.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>JDK_HOME</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The <envar>JDK_HOME</envar> environment variable is required
            by the script that starts VRJConfig, the VR Juggler configuration
            program. If Java is installed on your system,
            <envar>JDK_HOME</envar> may already be set. If not, it needs to be
            set to the base of the Java installation.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>LD_LIBRARY_PATH (UNIX/Linux only)</term>

          <term>DYLD_LIBRARY_PATH (Darwin/Mac OS X only)</term>

          <term>LD_LIBRARYN32_PATH (IRIX only)</term>

          <term>LD_LIBRARY64_PATH (IRIX only)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>UNIX/Linux systems use these environment variables to find
            dynamically loaded libraries, such as
            <filename>libvrj.so</filename>. Unless you are building everything
            with static libraries, you will need to set these to include the
            VR Juggler library directory (under <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar>).
            IRIX supports several Application Binary Interfaces (ABIs). VR
            Juggler supports only the N32 and 64 formats, and there are
            different library path variables for each. The N32 ABI uses the
            <envar>LD_LIBRARYN32_PATH</envar> variable, and the 64 ABI uses
            <envar>LD_LIBRARY64_PATH</envar>. An example of setting the
            library path is as follows:</para>

            <screen>% LD_LIBRARY_PATH = $VJ_BASE_DIR/lib</screen>

            <para>If you have <envar>VJ_DEPS_DIR</envar> set and it is not the
            same as <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar>, then
            <envar>$VJ_DEPS_DIR/lib</envar> also needs to be in
            <envar>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</envar>.</para>

            <note>
              <para>On some SGI systems running IRIX, users of the MIPSpro
              Compilers (version 7.3) may need to add another directory as
              follows:</para>

              <screen>% LD_LIBRARY_PATH = $LD_LIBRARY_PATH:/usr/lib32/cmplrs:$VJ_BASE_DIR/lib32</screen>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section id="section.envvars.optional">
      <title>Optional Related Environment Variables</title>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>VJ_CFG_PATH</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This variable provides a search path for looking up
            configuration files. It lists one or more directories where VR
            Juggler configuration files may be found. At run time, this path
            will be used to find configuration files that are not named using
            absolute paths. This variable is set using a platform-specific
            format. On Windows, DOS paths should be used, and they must be
            separated by the semi-colon (;) character. On UNIX variants and
            Mac OS X, the paths should be separated by the colon (:)
            character. This is exactly the way that the <envar>$PATH</envar>
            environment variable would be set on all of these platforms. If
            not set, the default search path for configuration files is
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/configFiles</filename>.</para>

            <note>
              <para>The configuration files are loaded by the module JCCL, and
              it will recognize the environment variable
              <envar>JCCL_CFG_PATH</envar>. If <envar>JCCL_CFG_PATH</envar> is
              set, it takes precedence over <envar>VJ_CFG_PATH</envar>.</para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>JCCL_DEFINITION_PATH</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This variable <emphasis>augments</emphasis> the search path
            for JCCL definition files (those files with the extension
            <filename>.jdef</filename>). It is set using a platform-specific
            format. On Windows, DOS paths should be used, and they must be
            separated by the semi-colon (;) character. On UNIX variants and
            Mac OS X, the paths should be separated by the colon (:)
            character. This is exactly the way that the <envar>PATH</envar>
            environment variable would be set on these platforms.</para>

            <para>The default search path for configuration files is always
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/definitions</filename>.
            Setting the environment variable
            <envar>JCCL_DEFINITION_PATH</envar> appends directories to the
            default search path. It is not possible to change the default
            search path without changing the value of
            <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar>.</para>

            <sidebar>
              <para>Python programmers will find this sort of behavior
              familiar. This functionality is based on the way that the Python
              environment variables <envar>PYTHONHOME</envar> and
              <envar>PYTHONPATH</envar> behave. In this case,
              <envar>PYTHONHOME</envar> corresponds to
              <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar>, and <envar>PYTHONPATH</envar>
              corresponds with <envar>JCCL_DEFINITION_PATH</envar>. Indeed,
              the behavior of <envar>JCCL_DEFINITION_PATH</envar> was inspired
              by the handling of <envar>PYTHONPATH</envar> by the Python
              interpreter.</para>
            </sidebar>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>SNX_BASE_DIR</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>The environment variable that defines the root directory of
            a Sonix installation. At run time, Sonix uses this variable to
            search for plug-ins. If it is not set, Sonix plug-in loading may
            fail. In genereal, it will be set to the same value as
            <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>VPR_DEBUG_NFY_LEVEL</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This variable can be used to control the amount of
            diagnostic information a VR Juggler application outputs. Its value
            is a number between 0 (only very important messages are printed)
            and 7 (vast amounts of data) inclusive. Non-hackers are advised to
            use levels 0 through 3, as higher debug levels become increasingly
            cryptic and <emphasis>can severely impact application
            performance</emphasis>. The default is level 1—only errors and
            critical information are output. An example of setting a value for
            this variable is:</para>

            <screen>% VPR_DEBUG_NFY_LEVEL = 3</screen>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This variable can be used to control which components of VR
            Juggler are allowed to output diagnostic data. If for some reason
            you set <envar>VPR_DEBUG_NFY_LEVEL</envar> to 5 or higher, this
            variable can be used to filter the output. The value of
            <envar>VPR_DEBUG_CATEGORIES</envar> is a space-separated list of
            Juggler debug component names (defined in
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/include/vrj/Util/Debug.h</filename>,
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/include/vpr/Util/Debug.h</filename>,
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/include/tweek/Util/Debug.h</filename>,
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/include/jccl/Util/Debug.h</filename>, and
            <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/include/gadget/Util/Debug.h</filename>).
            The default value is <quote>DBG_ALL</quote>, which performs no
            filtering whatsoever. Examples of setting it are as
            follows:</para>

            <screen>% VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES = DBG_ERROR
% VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES = "DBG_KERNEL DBG_INPUT_MGR DBG_DRAW_MGR"
% VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES = "DBG_CONFIG DBG_RECONFIGURATION"</screen>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>VPR_DEBUG_DISALLOW_CATEGORIES</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This variable is basically the opposite of
            <envar>VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES</envar>. Instead of specifying
            which debugging categories you want to see, you specify which ones
            you <emphasis>do not</emphasis> want to see. Its default value is
            empty which means that no debugging categories are excluded.
            Examples of setting it are as follows:</para>

            <screen>% VPR_DEBUG_DISALLOW_CATEGORIES = DBG_ERROR
% VPR_DEBUG_DISALLOW_CATEGORIES = "DBG_KERNEL DBG_INPUT_MGR DBG_DRAW_MGR"
% VPR_DEBUG_DISALLOW_CATEGORIES = "DBG_CONFIG DBG_RECONFIGURATION"</screen>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>NO_RTRC_PLUGIN</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Setting this environment variable to any value will prevent
            the <ulink url="http://www.vrjuggler.org/jccl/">JCCL</ulink>
            Config Manager from attempting to load the remote run-time
            reconfiguration plug-in. This plug-in is used to allow VRJConfig
            to connect to a running VR Juggler application so that the
            application may be reconfigured on the fly.</para>

            <para>Setting this environment variable is useful in two
            scenarios: when using SPROC threads on IRIX and when using <ulink
            url="http://www.vrjuggler.org/pyjuggler/">PyJuggler</ulink> on Mac
            OS X 10.3 (<quote>Panther</quote>). The current implementation of
            the remote run-time reconfiguration plug-in is based on <ulink
            url="http://omniorb.sourceforge.net/">omniORB</ulink>, which
            cannot be used with SPROC threads. In that case, there will not be
            a plug-in available to load, and setting this enviornment variable
            ultimately prevents the IRIX run-time loader from printing a nasty
            message saying as much. On Mac OS X 10.3, static data
            initialization in omniORB fails when the omniORB libraries are
            loaded into the Python interpreter application space, and this
            leads to a crash. Setting this environment variable allows
            PyJuggler applications to run correctly. This crash does not occur
            with PyJuggler on Mac OS X 10.4 (<quote>Tiger</quote>).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>NO_PERF_PLUGIN</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Setting this environment variable to any value will prevent
            the VR Juggler Performance Mediator from attempting to load the
            remote performance visualization plug-in. This plug-in is used to
            allow a JavaBean loaded by the <ulink
            url="http://www.vrjuggler.org/tweek/">Tweek</ulink> Java GUI to
            connect to a running VR Juggler application and display live
            performance metrics.</para>

            <para>Setting this environment variable is useful in two
            scenarios: when using SPROC threads on IRIX and when using <ulink
            url="http://www.vrjuggler.org/pyjuggler/">PyJuggler</ulink> on Mac
            OS X 10.3 (<quote>Panther</quote>). The current implementation of
            the remote performance visualization plug-in is based on <ulink
            url="http://omniorb.sourceforge.net/">omniORB</ulink>, which
            cannot be used with SPROC threads. In that case, there will not be
            a plug-in available to load, and setting this enviornment variable
            ultimately prevents the IRIX run-time loader from printing a nasty
            message saying as much. On Mac OS X 10.3, static data
            initialization in omniORB fails when the omniORB libraries are
            loaded into the Python interpreter application space, and this
            leads to a crash. Setting this environment variable allows
            PyJuggler applications to run correctly. This crash does not occur
            with PyJuggler on Mac OS X 10.4 (<quote>Tiger</quote>).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>VR Juggler Sample Applications</title>

    <para>VR Juggler comes with several sample applications in its
    <filename>samples</filename> directory tree. Many of them are very simple
    and are designed to demonstrate a specific feature of VR Juggler or a
    technique to use when writing your own applications. This chapter lists
    the current sample applications as of this writing and gives a quick
    description of what you as a potential developer might find interesting in
    the code. Those users who just want to run applications can safely skip
    this chapter.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Tutorial Applications</title>

      <para>Some sample applications designed for getting started with VR
      Juggler are found in
      <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples/OGL/simple</filename>.
      All of these applications were designed to be used as part of courses
      teaching people how to write VR Juggler applications using OpenGL. They
      contain clear comments explaining what the code is doing, and they are
      intended to be as simple as possible. These tutorials are as
      follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>simpleInput: An application that demonstrates how to get input
          from devices. No graphics are rendered with this application. It is
          intended to be a starting point for getting an understanding of how
          user input is queried.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SimpleApp: A very simple OpenGL application that draws a small
          cube in space and draws the coordinate axes for the cube.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>contextApp: An application demonstrating how to use OpenGL
          display lists in VR Juggler applications. This extends SimpleApp by
          using a display list to draw a cube and by moving the cube with the
          wand.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>ConfigApp: A relatively simple application that demonstrates
          how user-level code can take advantage of the VR Juggler
          configuration system, JCCL.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>MPApp: A more complex OpenGL application that demonstrates how
          to do multi-processing in VR Juggler applications. As it exists in
          its distributed form, no multi-processing is done. A more detailed
          lesson is available that explains how to extend the application to
          employ multi-processing techniques.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For a step-by-step lesson how to use these applications to learn
      VR Juggler application programming, please refer to the
      <emphasis>Programmer's Guide</emphasis>. It contains sections explaining
      each of the above applications in great detail. Each lesson ends with an
      exercise where the reader extends the application to include some new
      functionality.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Advanced OpenGL Performer Applications</title>

      <para>Examples of OpenGL Performer applications can be found in
      <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples/Pf/advanced</filename>.
      These are for more advanced developers who are familiar with Performer
      and some of the more complicated aspects of VR Juggler. There are two
      main programs to be found there:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>pfNav: A starting point for basic VR Juggler Performer
          applications that need to load a model and navigate through it.
          Users implement their application by inheriting from a provided
          class, <classname>simplePfNav</classname>. This may be a good place
          for intermediate-level users of OpenGL Performer to start because
          <classname>simplePfNav</classname> hides many of the complicated
          details (which actually makes that class far from simple).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>pfConfigNav: A more advanced example of a VR Juggler Performer
          application that can be given its model through a VR Juggler
          configuration element.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="chapter.app.compile">
    <title>Compiling a VR Juggler Sample Program</title>

    <para>Now that you have VR Juggler installed and you have your environment
    all configured, it is time for the fun to begin. No, seriously. You are
    now ready to compile and run VR Juggler applications, and that is the
    whole point, right? This chapter explains how to compile the applications
    provided in the directory
    <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples/OGL/simple</filename>.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Required Reading</title>

      <para>Before reading any further, make sure you have already read the
      instructions on how to install VR Juggler (in <xref
      linkend="chapter.vrj.install" />) and on how to configure your
      environment (in <xref linkend="chapter.envvar" />). That information
      will not be repeated, and it is assumed that you already know what we
      mean by <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar>. You should also have a basic
      understanding of how <command>make</command>(1) works, but in these
      examples, nothing more will be necessary than typing
      <literal>make</literal> on the command line. Refer to the
      <command>make</command>(1) manual page for more information about
      it.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Compiling an Application</title>

      <para>There are two ways to compile VR Juggler applications: from the
      command line or with Microsoft Visual Studio. Compiling an application
      on the command line requires the use of GNU make (often installed as
      <command>gmake</command>) so that it will work on all supported
      platforms including Win32. Using Microsoft Visual Studio will only work
      on Win32.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Compiling from the Command Line</title>

        <para>All the sample programs in
        <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples</filename> use the same
        basic steps to compile unless otherwise noted. Always refer to the top
        of the sample application's <filename>Makefile</filename> for
        information that may be specific to building that application. In
        general, though, all applications' makefiles require the GNU version
        of the <command>make</command>(1) utility, sometimes installed as
        <command>gmake</command>.</para>

        <para>The example used here will be the MPApp tutorial application
        found in
        <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples/OGL/simple/MPApp</filename>.
        It is an OpenGL-based application that will compile and run on all
        platforms supported by VR Juggler. Begin by changing into the
        directory
        <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/samples/OGL/simple/MPApp</filename>
        in a command shell.</para>

        <para>To compile MPApp, simply enter the following:</para>

        <screen>% gmake</screen>

        <para>The compile process will then begin. As noted above, the use of
        GNU make is required to use the distributed makefiles. With Cygwin,
        GNU make is simply <command>make</command>. If you have your system
        set up properly, it will complete with an executable
        <filename>MPApp</filename> file (or <filename>MPApp.exe</filename> on
        Win32) in the directory. Now that you have a program compiled, it is
        time to learn how to run it. (Readers who are not using Visual Studio
        can skip ahead to <xref linkend="chapter.app.running" />.)</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Compiling Using Microsoft Visual Studio</title>

        <note>
          <para>Remember that the Netscape Portable Runtime (NSPR) is
          <emphasis>required</emphasis> to use VR Juggler on Windows. Its DLL
          directory must be in your path (via the <envar>PATH</envar>
          environment variable) for proper application execution. The NSPR can
          be downloaded from the <ulink
          url="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/nspr">NSPR home page</ulink>.
          If the pre-compiled VR Juggler dependencies are installed, then NSPR
          is already available.</para>
        </note>

        <para>All OpenGL sample applications are shipped with pre-configured
        Microsoft Visual C++ projects. This is done to help new users get
        started with compiling VR Juggler applications and to give experienced
        Visual Studio users a starting place for their application
        development. To use the workspace for the MPApp application, begin by
        opening the folder containing the source code and double-clicking on
        <filename>MPApp.vcproj</filename>.</para>

        <figure>
          <title>Selecting the Visual C++ Project File</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/MPApp.dir.png"
                         format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Visual Studio will open, and the MPApp project will be loaded.
        The unexpanded class view will appear as shown in <xref
        linkend="figure.visual.studio.start" /> when Visual Studio first
        loads.</para>

        <figure id="figure.visual.studio.start">
          <title>MPApp Project</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center" fileref="figures/MPApp.visual.c++.png"
                         format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>In some cases, it may be necessary to change the default project
        properties. The project properties dialog can be opened in several
        ways. For example, right-clicking on the project name in the Solution
        Explorer brings up the menu shown in <xref
        linkend="figure.visual.studio.menu.project" />. We are interested in
        changing the project's properties, so we select the
        <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem> item from the popup menu.</para>

        <figure id="figure.visual.studio.menu.project">
          <title>Project Menu</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
                         fileref="figures/MPApp.visual.c++.properties.png"
                         format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Under the MPApp project settings, the path(s) to the VR Juggler
        C++ dependencies must be filled in. This means setting paths to find
        headers and libraries. All the Visual C++ project files shipped with
        VR Juggler refer to the VR Juggler C++ dependency installation via the
        <envar>VJ_DEPS_DIR</envar> environment variable. If this is not set or
        cannot be used, the paths must be filled in manually.</para>

        <para>Once the program properties are set, compile the application.
        Under the <guimenu>Build</guimenu> menu, choose the <guimenuitem>Build
        MPApp</guimenuitem> item as shown in <xref
        linkend="figure.visual.studio.menu.build" />. Visual C++ will compile
        the application, and if you have everything configured properly on
        your computer, the compiling will complete successfully.</para>

        <figure id="figure.visual.studio.menu.build">
          <title>Build <filename>MPApp.exe</filename></title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
                         fileref="figures/MPApp.visual.c++.build.png"
                         format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>For the remainder of this book, much of the discussion will
        concentrate on running applications from the command line rather than
        from the Visual Studio GUI. Readers can follow whichever method they
        prefer.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="chapter.app.running">
    <title>Running a VR Juggler Sample Program</title>

    <para>It is important to note that the same VR Juggler application can be
    run in simulator mode or in a full-scale VR system with no modifications.
    What does change is the configuration files used when starting the
    program. In
    <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/configFiles</filename>, you
    can find many basic configuration files including those for running in
    simulator using a mouse and keyboard to simulate VR input devices and some
    example files based on those used for the VRAC C4 system. In the
    directory, you will see some files with names containing
    <quote>mixin</quote>. These are special files that provide a specific
    capability not necessarily needed by all applications. They can be mixed
    in (hence the name) with other configuration files as needed. The
    configuration files found in the <filename>configFiles</filename>
    directory will be referenced in the examples provided, so be sure you know
    where they are.</para>

    <section id="section.required.reading">
      <title>Required Reading</title>

      <para>Before reading any further, make sure you have already read the
      instructions on how to install VR Juggler (see <xref
      linkend="chapter.vrj.install" />) and on how to configure your
      environment (see <xref linkend="chapter.envvar" />). That information
      will not be repeated, and it is assumed that you already know what we
      mean by <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> and <envar>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</envar>,
      to name two environment variables. At this point, it is also assumed
      that you already have compiled an application (MPApp in the case of the
      examples provided), so you should be sure to have read about how to
      compile a sample VR Juggler application (in <xref
      linkend="chapter.app.compile" />) before proceeding.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="section.running.simulator">
      <title>Running an Application with a Simulator Configuration</title>

      <para>Running in <quote>simulator mode</quote> means that your input is
      simulated and your display windows may have limited functionality. (By
      <quote>simulated input</quote>, we mean that input is provided through
      windows that take keyboard and mouse input and translate that into
      transformations in the virtual world.) Simulator viewports are limited
      primarily in that they cannot display stereo graphics. It is important
      to note that a simulator viewport is a special kind of VR Juggler
      viewport within a display window. Instead of basing its viewpoint on the
      head position of one of the users, the viewpoint is controlled by a
      separate camera that is just another positional device. Within a
      simulator viewport, VR Juggler draws certain objects to help visualize
      the environment. For example, the heads of users are represented as blue
      ellipsoids with gray eyes, and a wand (if present) is drawn as a green
      pointing device. Besides these common simulator objects, display
      surfaces can be drawn. These represent projection screens or HMD viewing
      projections and are drawn as translucent rectangles.</para>

      <para>As mentioned, several simulator configuration files are provided
      with a VR Juggler distribution. These files provide a complete
      simulation of an immersive environment. Please note that this
      documentation reflects the state of the configuration files at the time
      the documentation was written. For more information about the
      configuration files and how to view or modify the configuration, refer
      to the <emphasis>VRJConfig Guide</emphasis>. (Using VRJConfig is the
      best way to find out how a specific configuration file is set up.) The
      configuration files of interest for simulator mode are as
      follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><filename>sim.base.jconf</filename> - The basic configuration
          file needed by all applications when run in simulator mode. It
          defines commonly used VR Juggler concepts that are beyond the scope
          of this particular book. It also defines simulated head movement
          using the keyboard. For now, it is sufficient to know that it is
          required to run the sample applications in simulator mode.</para>

          <para>This file also contains the basic simulator display
          configuration file needed by all applications when run in simulator
          mode. It defines the display windows where the rendering magic
          occurs. Two simulator display windows are configured by this file: a
          small one that is active by default and a larger one that is
          inactive initially.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>sim.analog.wandmixin.jconf</filename> - A
          <quote>mix-in</quote> configuration file that defines simulated
          analog input using the keyboard. This is only required for
          applications where analog input is used and needs to be simulated
          when in simulator mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>sim.analog.mixin.jconf</filename> - This version of
          the analog simulator opens its own window. See the previous file
          (<filename>sim.analog.wandmixin.jconf</filename>) for other
          details.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>sim.c6displays.mixin.jconf</filename> - A
          <quote>mix-in</quote> configuration file that defines the surface
          displays of VRAC's C6. This is not required for any application but
          can be used to test opening multiple display windows (each
          containing either a surface or a simulator viewport) before running
          in a multi-screen VR system.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>sim.digital.glove.mixin.jconf</filename> - A
          <quote>mix-in</quote> configuration file that defines simulated
          digital glove input using the keyboard. This is only required for
          applications where digital glove input is used and needs to be
          simulated when in simulator mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>sim.glove.mixin.jconf</filename> - A
          <quote>mix-in</quote> configuration file that defines simulated
          gesture-based glove input using the keyboard. This is only required
          for applications where gesture-based glove input is used and needs
          to be simulated when in simulator mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>sim.wand.mixin.jconf</filename> - A
          <quote>mix-in</quote> configuration file that defines simulated wand
          input using the mouse. This is only required for applications where
          wand input is used and needs to be simulated when in simulator
          mode.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>standalone.jconf</filename> - A configuration file
          that stands on its own and combines the functionality of
          <filename>sim.base.jconf</filename> and
          <filename>sim.wand.mixin.jconf</filename>. Note that it uses a
          single display window for all input.</para>

          <note>
            <para>At the time of this writing, this configuration file only
            works with OpenGL, OpenSG, and Open Scene Graph applications on
            UNIX, Win32, and Mac OS X. It will not work with OpenGL
            Performer.</para>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For the MPApp application, we need the base configuration file and
      the wand mix-in configuration file.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Starting the Application</title>

        <para>Now it is time to run the application—finally! Make sure that
        all your environment variables are set properly before trying to start
        the application. Once you are ready, specify the name of the
        application and all the configuration files it needs. An example of
        this is:</para>

        <screen>% MPApp sim.base.jconf sim.wand.mixin.jconf</screen>

        <para>You will notice that no paths are specified for finding the
        configuration files. The full paths to the configuration files is not
        necessary because the default search path will correctly find these
        files in
        <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/configFiles</filename>.
        Beginning users will typically want to reference the example
        configuration files in that directory. As you get more comfortable
        with VR Juggler and its configuration system, you may want to make
        your own modified files and put them in the directory
        <filename>$HOME/.vjconfig</filename>. The environment variable
        <envar>VJ_CFG_PATH</envar> is useful in providing a search path for
        finding your configuration files. (Refer to <xref
        linkend="section.envvars.optional" /> for more information on using
        <envar>VJ_CFG_PATH</envar>). To simplify running applications, you may
        want to make a shell script (or batch file as appropriate) that does
        all the work of passing configuration files and common command-line
        arguments.</para>

        <para>As the application starts, you will see a status output printed
        to the console (more or less depending on how you have
        <envar>VPR_DEBUG_NFY_LEVEL</envar>,
        <envar>VPR_DEBUG_ALLOW_CATEGORIES</envar>, and
        <envar>VPR_DEBUG_DISALLOW_CATEGORIES</envar> set), and then one
        moderately sized simulator display window will open on the left side
        of your screen while three blank keyboard input windows open on the
        right side of your screen. The display window will be titled
        <quote>SimWindow1</quote>, and the keyboard input windows will be
        titled <quote>Head Keyboard</quote>, <quote>Sim View Cameras
        Control</quote> and <quote>Wand Keyboard</quote> (in order from the
        top of the display to the bottom). Do not worry that the keyboard
        windows are black—that is normal. The display window will have an
        animated blue mesh, a cyan ellipsoid, and a green pointer. The mesh is
        what you have come to see; the ellipsoid is the user's head; and the
        pointer is the user's hand. In <xref
        linkend="figure.MPApp.running" />, we show what this looks on a RedHat
        Linux 7.2 desktop for comparison with what you are seeing. Note that
        the head and wand are only rendered in the simulator windows. They are
        present because head and wand input are being simulated, and it is
        typically quite helpful to see the results of that simulated input. To
        exit the application, press <keysym>ESC</keysym> in the window titled
        <quote>Head Window</quote>.</para>

        <figure id="figure.MPApp.running">
          <title>MPApp running on a Linux desktop with multiple input
          windows</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
                         fileref="figures/MPApp.thumbnail.multi.png"
                         format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>With VR Juggler 1.1/2.0, it is possible to use a single window
        for graphics and for input. To use such a configuration, execute MPApp
        as follows:</para>

        <screen>% MPApp standalone.jconf</screen>

        <para>This time, only a single window opens, as shown in <xref
        linkend="figure.MPApp.running.single" />. It shows the same graphics
        as before, but now it is configured to take keyboard and mouse input.
        To exit, press <keysym>ESC</keysym> in the graphics window.</para>

        <figure id="figure.MPApp.running.single">
          <title>MPApp running on a Linux desktop with one window</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata align="center"
                         fileref="figures/MPApp.thumbnail.single.png"
                         format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <section>
          <title>Running an Application on Windows from Within Visual
          Studio</title>

          <para>To run MPApp from within the Visual Studio IDE, the program
          arguments must be set first. This is done by opening the properties
          dialog for the project. In this dialog box, choose the
          <guilabel>Debugging</guilabel> item. There will be an empty text
          entry field under the heading <guilabel>Command
          Arguments</guilabel>. Here, enter the full paths to the VR Juggler
          configuration files that will be used to run the torus application.
          To use the <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> environment variable (or any
          other environment variable), makefile syntax must be used. In other
          words, to load <filename>somefile.jconf</filename>, use
          <filename>$(VJ_BASE_DIR)\share\vrjuggler\data\configFiles\somefile.jconf</filename>.
          As was stated above, the full path need not be specified, so
          referencing <envar>VJ_BASE_DIR</envar> in the path to the example
          configuration files will not be necessary in most cases.. In <xref
          linkend="figure.visual.studio.dialog.project.settings" />, we see
          the use of <filename>standalone.jconf</filename> as the single
          command argument to MPApp.</para>

          <figure id="figure.visual.studio.dialog.project.settings">
            <title>Setting Command Arguments</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center"
                           fileref="figures/MPApp.visual.c++.args.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>With the application already compiled, execute the MPApp
          program by choosing the <guimenuitem>Start</guimenuitem> item from
          the <guimenu>Debug</guimenu> menu, shown below in <xref
          linkend="figure.visual.studio.menu.debug.execute" />.</para>

          <figure id="figure.visual.studio.menu.debug.execute">
            <title>Execute <filename>MPApp.exe</filename></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center"
                           fileref="figures/MPApp.visual.c++.run.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Running an Application on Mac OS X with the X Window
          System</title>

          <para>Running a VR Juggler application on Mac OS X is slightly
          different if VR Juggler was compiled against <ulink
          url="http://www.apple.com/macosx/x11/">X11 for OS X</ulink>. Before
          starting the VR Juggler application, X11 must be running. This can
          be accomplished by double-clicking on the X11 icon in the
          Applications folder. By default, X11 will open a standard xterm when
          it starts. In this xterm, the <envar>$DISPLAY</envar> environment
          variable will be set correctly, and it is recommended that VR
          Juggler applications be launched from this xterm. From this xterm,
          set the necessary environment variables as described earlier in
          <xref linkend="section.envvars.required" />. Once this is done, the
          application can be executed from the command line just as described
          in the previous section.</para>

          <para>MPApp is shown executing on a Mac OS X desktop in <xref
          linkend="figure.MPApp.running.single.OSX" />. Note that in the dock,
          the X11 icon is activated and that the application menu is for an
          X11 application. This truly is an X11 application running on OS
          X.</para>

          <figure id="figure.MPApp.running.single.OSX">
            <title>MPApp running on Mac OS X using X11 with one window</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata align="center"
                           fileref="figures/MPApp-OSX.thumbnail.single.png"
                           format="PNG" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Basic Desktop Configuration Controls</title>

        <para>So now you are probably wondering what you can do with this
        fancy application. Both of the preceding configurations use the same
        keyboard/mouse mappings; they vary only in which windows accept the
        keyboard and mouse input. Using the multi-window configuration, head
        movement is done with the keyboard in <quote>Head Keyboard</quote>;
        camera movement is done with the keyboard in <quote>Sim View Cameras
        Control</quote>; and wand movement is done with the keyboard and mouse
        in <quote>Wand Keyboard</quote>. Using the single-window
        configuration, all input is done with the keyboard and mouse in
        <quote>Sim Window</quote>. Note, however, that for the single-window
        configuration, the camera is attached to the user's head for an
        over-the-shoulder view, and hence, it does not move separately from
        the head. For information on how to verify these settings and to view
        the current configuration, refer to the <emphasis>VRJConfig
        Guide</emphasis>. The following list of tables provides all the
        keyboard and mouse controls for the simulator when using these
        particular configuration files. Note that it is possible to
        reconfigure the simulator to suit your preferences. This is provided
        mainly for those who just want something that works now.</para>

        <table>
          <title>Moving the simulated head</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Transformation</entry>

                <entry>Key Press</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">Move head backward</entry>

                <entry align="left">2 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Move head left</entry>

                <entry align="left">4 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Move head right</entry>

                <entry align="left">6 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Move head forward</entry>

                <entry align="left">8 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Move head down</entry>

                <entry align="left">7 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Move head up</entry>

                <entry align="left">9 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Turn head up</entry>

                <entry align="left">CTRL+2 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Turn head left</entry>

                <entry align="left">CTRL+4 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Turn head right</entry>

                <entry align="left">CTRL+6 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Turn head down</entry>

                <entry align="left">CTRL+8 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Rotate head clockwise</entry>

                <entry align="left">1 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">Rotate head counter-clockwise</entry>

                <entry align="left">3 on keypad</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
          <title>Moving the simulated wand</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Transformation</entry>

                <entry>Mouse Input/Key Press</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Move wand backward</entry>

                <entry>ALT+move mouse backward</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move wand forward</entry>

                <entry>ALT+move mouse forward</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move wand left</entry>

                <entry>CTRL+move mouse left</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move wand right</entry>

                <entry>CTRL+move mouse right</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move wand up</entry>

                <entry>CTRL+move mouse forward</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move wand down</entry>

                <entry>CTRL+move mouse backward</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Rotate wand left</entry>

                <entry>SHIFT+move mouse left</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Rotate wand right</entry>

                <entry>SHIFT+move mouse right</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Rotate wand up</entry>

                <entry>SHIFT+move mouse backward</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Rotate wand down</entry>

                <entry>SHIFT+move mouse forward</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Rotate wand clockwise</entry>

                <entry>Right arrow</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Rotate wand counter-clockwise</entry>

                <entry>Left arrow</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Wand button #1</entry>

                <entry>Left mouse button</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Wand button #2</entry>

                <entry>Middle mouse button</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Wand button #3</entry>

                <entry>Right mouse button</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Wand button #4</entry>

                <entry>4</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Wand button #5</entry>

                <entry>5</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Wand button #6</entry>

                <entry>6</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <table>
          <title>Moving the camera (multi-window configuration only)</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Transformation</entry>

                <entry>Key Press</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Move camera backward</entry>

                <entry>2 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move camera left</entry>

                <entry>4 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move camera right</entry>

                <entry>6 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move camera forward</entry>

                <entry>8 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move camera down</entry>

                <entry>7 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Move camera up</entry>

                <entry>9 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Turn camera up</entry>

                <entry>CTRL+2 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Turn camera left</entry>

                <entry>CTRL+4 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Turn camera right</entry>

                <entry>CTRL+6 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Turn camera down</entry>

                <entry>CTRL+8 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Rotate camera clockwise</entry>

                <entry>1 on keypad</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>Rotate camera counter-clockwise</entry>

                <entry>3 on keypad</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>Before continuing on to running an application in a full-scale
        VR system, we provide two asides: using a simulated glove and using a
        simulated analog device. The examples provided thus far have not
        discussed this because the information was not relevant to the
        particular sample application being used. Knowing how to use these
        simulated devices is important, however, and it is treated separately
        as a reference for your future endeavors in running VR Juggler
        applications.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Using a Simulated Glove</title>

        <para>If you include the <filename>sim.glove.mixin.jconf</filename>
        file, your application will also have access to a simulated glove,
        with position and gesture inputs. The glove is controlled by a window
        titled <quote>Glove Keyboard</quote>. This window lets you control the
        glove position and selected gesture. Movement control of the glove
        uses the mouse and is the same as that of the wand. The mouse buttons
        are used to select gestures. The mapping of the gesture numbers to
        actual hand positions is controlled by the <quote>training
        file</quote> for the sim glove. The default training file is
        <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/gesture/simpleSimGestures.dat</filename>.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Using a Simulated Analog Device</title>

        <para>If you include the
        <filename>sim.analog.wandmixin.jconf</filename> file, your application
        will also have access to a set of four analog devices (devices with a
        value in a range from 0.0 to 1.0). The analog devices are also
        controlled using the <quote>Wand Keyboard</quote> window which means
        that their configuration file requires the wand configuration
        file.</para>

        <note>
          <para>A separate file, <filename>sim.analog.mixin.jconf</filename>,
          is provided for analog input from a separate simulator
          window.</para>
        </note>

        <para>The key presses used for controlling the analog devices are
        listed in <xref linkend="table.sim.analog.keys" />.</para>

        <table id="table.sim.analog.keys">
          <title>Analog Device Simulator Keys</title>

          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="center">Analog Device Action</entry>

                <entry align="center">Key Press</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry align="left">VJAnalog0 increase</entry>

                <entry align="center">Q</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">VJAnalog0 decrease</entry>

                <entry align="center">A</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">VJAnalog1 increase</entry>

                <entry align="center">W</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">VJAnalog1 decrease</entry>

                <entry align="center">S</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">VJAnalog2 increase</entry>

                <entry align="center">E</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">VJAnalog2 decrease</entry>

                <entry align="center">D</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">VJAnalog3 increase</entry>

                <entry align="center">R</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry align="left">VJAnalog3 decrease</entry>

                <entry align="center">F</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Running an Application in a VR System</title>

      <para>Running an application full-scale in a VR system is more
      complicated than running in simulator mode. The reason for this is that
      VR systems tend to differ in configuration and in available hardware. VR
      Juggler is flexible enough to handle most any configuration you throw at
      it, but those configurations need to be put together first. Examples of
      configuration files used in VRAC's C4 system are provided, and they are
      used in this documentation. It should be noted, however, that for any
      particular system, custom configuration files will probably have to be
      written. The idea behind this section is to provide a basic
      understanding of what is needed to get started with running in a VR
      system.</para>

      <para>The example configuration files in the directory
      <filename>$VJ_BASE_DIR/share/vrjuggler/data/configFiles</filename>
      modeled after those used for VRAC's C4 system are as follows:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><filename>C4.closed.jconf</filename> - The single
          configuration file that includes the other configuration files
          necessary for loading a VR Juggler application in the C4 in its
          closed configuration with full tracking and stereoscopic
          graphics.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>C4.closed.mono.jconf</filename> - The single
          configuration file that includes the other configuration files
          necessary for loading a VR Juggler application in the C4 in its
          closed configuration with full tracking and monoscopic
          graphics.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>C4.base.jconf</filename> - The basic configuration
          file needed by all applications when run in the C4. It defines
          commonly used VR Juggler concepts that are beyond the scope of this
          particular book.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>C4.displays.closed.jconf</filename> - The basic
          display configuration file needed to run with all four walls active
          and rendering stereoscopic graphics. This defines only the four
          surface displays to be opened. The corners are configured for the
          closed position of the moveable walls.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>C4.displays.closed.mono.jconf</filename> - The basic
          display configuration file needed to run with all four walls active
          and rendering monoscopic graphics. This defines only the four
          surface displays to be opened. The corners are configured for the
          closed position of the moveable walls.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>C4.mstar.jconf</filename> - The Ascension MotionStar
          configuration file that defines which bird provides input for the
          head and for the wand.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><filename>C4.rfwand.jconf</filename> - The radio frequency
          wireless mouse that acts as a wand.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Running the application is the same as in simulator mode except
      that the configuration files given on the command line are different.
      For example, to run MPApp in the C4 with stereoscopic graphics, the
      following command would be used:</para>

      <screen>% MPApp C4.closed.jconf</screen>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <appendix id="appendix.gfdl">
    <title>GNU Free Documentation License</title>

    <subtitle>Version 1.2, November 2002</subtitle>

    <blockquote id="fsf-copyright">
      <title>FSF Copyright note</title>

      <para>Copyright (C) 2000,2001,2002 Free Software Foundation, Inc. 59
      Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307 USA Everyone is permitted
      to copy and distribute verbatim copies of this license document, but
      changing it is not allowed.</para>
    </blockquote>

    <section id="gfdl-0">
      <title>PREAMBLE</title>

      <para>The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or
      other functional and useful document "free" in the sense of freedom: to
      assure everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it, with
      or without modifying it, either commercially or noncommercially.
      Secondarily, this License preserves for the author and publisher a way
      to get credit for their work, while not being considered responsible for
      modifications made by others.</para>

      <para>This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that derivative
      works of the document must themselves be free in the same sense. It
      complements the GNU General Public License, which is a copyleft license
      designed for free software.</para>

      <para>We have designed this License in order to use it for manuals for
      free software, because free software needs free documentation: a free
      program should come with manuals providing the same freedoms that the
      software does. But this License is not limited to software manuals; it
      can be used for any textual work, regardless of subject matter or
      whether it is published as a printed book. We recommend this License
      principally for works whose purpose is instruction or reference.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="gfdl-1">
      <title>APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS</title>

      <para id="gfdl-doc">This License applies to any manual or other work, in
      any medium, that contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying
      it can be distributed under the terms of this License. Such a notice
      grants a world-wide, royalty-free license, unlimited in duration, to use
      that work under the conditions stated herein. The "Document", below,
      refers to any such manual or work. Any member of the public is a
      licensee, and is addressed as "you". You accept the license if you copy,
      modify or distribute the work in a way requiring permission under
      copyright law.</para>

      <para id="gfdl-mod-ver">A "Modified Version" of the Document means any
      work containing the Document or a portion of it, either copied verbatim,
      or with modifications and/or translated into another language.</para>

      <para id="gfdl-secnd-sect">A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix or
      a front-matter section of the Document that deals exclusively with the
      relationship of the publishers or authors of the Document to the
      Document's overall subject (or to related matters) and contains nothing
      that could fall directly within that overall subject. (Thus, if the
      Document is in part a textbook of mathematics, a Secondary Section may
      not explain any mathematics.) The relationship could be a matter of
      historical connection with the subject or with related matters, or of
      legal, commercial, philosophical, ethical or political position
      regarding them.</para>

      <para id="gfdl-inv-sect">The "Invariant Sections" are certain Secondary
      Sections whose titles are designated, as being those of Invariant
      Sections, in the notice that says that the Document is released under
      this License. If a section does not fit the above definition of
      Secondary then it is not allowed to be designated as Invariant. The
      Document may contain zero Invariant Sections. If the Document does not
      identify any Invariant Sections then there are none.</para>

      <para id="gfdl-cov-text">The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages of
      text that are listed, as Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the
      notice that says that the Document is released under this License. A
      Front-Cover Text may be at most 5 words, and a Back-Cover Text may be at
      most 25 words.</para>

      <para id="gfdl-transparent">A "Transparent" copy of the Document means a
      machine-readable copy, represented in a format whose specification is
      available to the general public, that is suitable for revising the
      document straightforwardly with generic text editors or (for images
      composed of pixels) generic paint programs or (for drawings) some widely
      available drawing editor, and that is suitable for input to text
      formatters or for automatic translation to a variety of formats suitable
      for input to text formatters. A copy made in an otherwise Transparent
      file format whose markup, or absence of markup, has been arranged to
      thwart or discourage subsequent modification by readers is not
      Transparent. An image format is not Transparent if used for any
      substantial amount of text. A copy that is not "Transparent" is called
      "Opaque".</para>

      <para>Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include plain
      ASCII without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input format, SGML or
      XML using a publicly available DTD, and standard-conforming simple HTML,
      PostScript or PDF designed for human modification. Examples of
      transparent image formats include PNG, XCF and JPG. Opaque formats
      include proprietary formats that can be read and edited only by
      proprietary word processors, SGML or XML for which the DTD and/or
      processing tools are not generally available, and the machine-generated
      HTML, PostScript or PDF produced by some word processors for output
      purposes only.</para>

      <para id="gfdl-title-page">The "Title Page" means, for a printed book,
      the title page itself, plus such following pages as are needed to hold,
      legibly, the material this License requires to appear in the title page.
      For works in formats which do not have any title page as such, "Title
      Page" means the text near the most prominent appearance of the work's
      title, preceding the beginning of the body of the text.</para>

      <para id="gfdl-entitled">A section "Entitled XYZ" means a named subunit
      of the Document whose title either is precisely XYZ or contains XYZ in
      parentheses following text that translates XYZ in another language.
      (Here XYZ stands for a specific section name mentioned below, such as
      "Acknowledgements", "Dedications", "Endorsements", or "History".) To
      "Preserve the Title" of such a section when you modify the Document
      means that it remains a section "Entitled XYZ" according to this
      definition.</para>

      <para>The Document may include Warranty Disclaimers next to the notice
      which states that this License applies to the Document. These Warranty
      Disclaimers are considered to be included by reference in this License,
      but only as regards disclaiming warranties: any other implication that
      these Warranty Disclaimers may have is void and has no effect on the
      meaning of this License.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="gfdl-2">
      <title>VERBATIM COPYING</title>

      <para>You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium, either
      commercially or noncommercially, provided that this License, the
      copyright notices, and the license notice saying this License applies to
      the Document are reproduced in all copies, and that you add no other
      conditions whatsoever to those of this License. You may not use
      technical measures to obstruct or control the reading or further copying
      of the copies you make or distribute. However, you may accept
      compensation in exchange for copies. If you distribute a large enough
      number of copies you must also follow the conditions in section
      3.</para>

      <para>You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated above,
      and you may publicly display copies.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="gfdl-3">
      <title>COPYING IN QUANTITY</title>

      <para>If you publish printed copies (or copies in media that commonly
      have printed covers) of the Document, numbering more than 100, and the
      Document's license notice requires Cover Texts, you must enclose the
      copies in covers that carry, clearly and legibly, all these Cover Texts:
      Front-Cover Texts on the front cover, and Back-Cover Texts on the back
      cover. Both covers must also clearly and legibly identify you as the
      publisher of these copies. The front cover must present the full title
      with all words of the title equally prominent and visible. You may add
      other material on the covers in addition. Copying with changes limited
      to the covers, as long as they preserve the title of the Document and
      satisfy these conditions, can be treated as verbatim copying in other
      respects.</para>

      <para>If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to fit
      legibly, you should put the first ones listed (as many as fit
      reasonably) on the actual cover, and continue the rest onto adjacent
      pages.</para>

      <para>If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document
      numbering more than 100, you must either include a machine-readable
      Transparent copy along with each Opaque copy, or state in or with each
      Opaque copy a computer-network location from which the general
      network-using public has access to download using public-standard
      network protocols a complete Transparent copy of the Document, free of
      added material. If you use the latter option, you must take reasonably
      prudent steps, when you begin distribution of Opaque copies in quantity,
      to ensure that this Transparent copy will remain thus accessible at the
      stated location until at least one year after the last time you
      distribute an Opaque copy (directly or through your agents or retailers)
      of that edition to the public.</para>

      <para>It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors of
      the Document well before redistributing any large number of copies, to
      give them a chance to provide you with an updated version of the
      Document.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="gfdl-4">
      <title>MODIFICATIONS</title>

      <para>You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the Document
      under the conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided that you
      release the Modified Version under precisely this License, with the
      Modified Version filling the role of the Document, thus licensing
      distribution and modification of the Modified Version to whoever
      possesses a copy of it. In addition, you must do these things in the
      Modified Version:</para>

      <orderedlist id="gfdl-modif-cond" numeration="upperalpha">
        <title>GNU FDL Modification Conditions</title>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Use in the Title Page (and on the covers, if any) a title
          distinct from that of the Document, and from those of previous
          versions (which should, if there were any, be listed in the History
          section of the Document). You may use the same title as a previous
          version if the original publisher of that version gives
          permission.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>List on the Title Page, as authors, one or more persons or
          entities responsible for authorship of the modifications in the
          Modified Version, together with at least five of the principal
          authors of the Document (all of its principal authors, if it has
          fewer than five), unless they release you from this
          requirement.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>State on the Title page the name of the publisher of the
          Modified Version, as the publisher.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve all the copyright notices of the
          Document.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Add an appropriate copyright notice for your modifications
          adjacent to the other copyright notices.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a license
          notice giving the public permission to use the Modified Version
          under the terms of this License, in the form shown in the <link
          linkend="gfdl-addendum">Addendum</link> below.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve in that license notice the full lists of Invariant
          Sections and required Cover Texts given in the Document's license
          notice.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Include an unaltered copy of this License.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve the section Entitled "History", Preserve its
          Title, and add to it an item stating at least the title, year, new
          authors, and publisher of the Modified Version as given on the Title
          Page. If there is no section Entitled "History" in the Document,
          create one stating the title, year, authors, and publisher of the
          Document as given on its Title Page, then add an item describing the
          Modified Version as stated in the previous sentence.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve the network location, if any, given in the
          Document for public access to a Transparent copy of the Document,
          and likewise the network locations given in the Document for
          previous versions it was based on. These may be placed in the
          "History" section. You may omit a network location for a work that
          was published at least four years before the Document itself, or if
          the original publisher of the version it refers to gives
          permission.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>For any section Entitled "Acknowledgements" or
          "Dedications", Preserve the Title of the section, and preserve in
          the section all the substance and tone of each of the contributor
          acknowledgements and/or dedications given therein.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve all the Invariant Sections of the Document,
          unaltered in their text and in their titles. Section numbers or the
          equivalent are not considered part of the section titles.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Delete any section Entitled "Endorsements". Such a section
          may not be included in the Modified Version.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Do not retitle any existing section to be Entitled
          "Endorsements" or to conflict in title with any Invariant
          Section.</simpara>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <simpara>Preserve any Warranty Disclaimers.</simpara>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para>If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections or
      appendices that qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no material
      copied from the Document, you may at your option designate some or all
      of these sections as invariant. To do this, add their titles to the list
      of Invariant Sections in the Modified Version's license notice. These
      titles must be distinct from any other section titles.</para>

      <para>You may add a section Entitled "Endorsements", provided it
      contains nothing but endorsements of your Modified Version by various
      parties--for example, statements of peer review or that the text has
      been approved by an organization as the authoritative definition of a
      standard.</para>

      <para>You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover Text,
      and a passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the end of the
      list of Cover Texts in the Modified Version. Only one passage of
      Front-Cover Text and one of Back-Cover Text may be added by (or through
      arrangements made by) any one entity. If the Document already includes a
      cover text for the same cover, previously added by you or by arrangement
      made by the same entity you are acting on behalf of, you may not add
      another; but you may replace the old one, on explicit permission from
      the previous publisher that added the old one.</para>

      <para>The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by this
      License give permission to use their names for publicity for or to
      assert or imply endorsement of any Modified Version.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="gfdl-5">
      <title>COMBINING DOCUMENTS</title>

      <para>You may combine the Document with other documents released under
      this License, under the terms defined in <link linkend="gfdl-4">section
      4</link> above for modified versions, provided that you include in the
      combination all of the Invariant Sections of all of the original
      documents, unmodified, and list them all as Invariant Sections of your
      combined work in its license notice, and that you preserve all their
      Warranty Disclaimers.</para>

      <para>The combined work need only contain one copy of this License, and
      multiple identical Invariant Sections may be replaced with a single
      copy. If there are multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but
      different contents, make the title of each such section unique by adding
      at the end of it, in parentheses, the name of the original author or
      publisher of that section if known, or else a unique number. Make the
      same adjustment to the section titles in the list of Invariant Sections
      in the license notice of the combined work.</para>

      <para>In the combination, you must combine any sections Entitled
      "History" in the various original documents, forming one section
      Entitled "History"; likewise combine any sections Entitled
      "Acknowledgements", and any sections Entitled "Dedications". You must
      delete all sections Entitled "Endorsements".</para>
    </section>

    <section id="gfdl-6">
      <title>COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS</title>

      <para>You may make a collection consisting of the Document and other
      documents released under this License, and replace the individual copies
      of this License in the various documents with a single copy that is
      included in the collection, provided that you follow the rules of this
      License for verbatim copying of each of the documents in all other
      respects.</para>

      <para>You may extract a single document from such a collection, and
      distribute it individually under this License, provided you insert a
      copy of this License into the extracted document, and follow this
      License in all other respects regarding verbatim copying of that
      document.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="gfdl-7">
      <title>AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS</title>

      <para>A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other
      separate and independent documents or works, in or on a volume of a
      storage or distribution medium, is called an "aggregate" if the
      copyright resulting from the compilation is not used to limit the legal
      rights of the compilation's users beyond what the individual works
      permit. When the Document is included in an aggregate, this License does
      not apply to the other works in the aggregate which are not themselves
      derivative works of the Document.</para>

      <para>If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to these
      copies of the Document, then if the Document is less than one half of
      the entire aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts may be placed on covers
      that bracket the Document within the aggregate, or the electronic
      equivalent of covers if the Document is in electronic form. Otherwise
      they must appear on printed covers that bracket the whole
      aggregate.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="gfdl-8">
      <title>TRANSLATION</title>

      <para>Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may
      distribute translations of the Document under the terms of section 4.
      Replacing Invariant Sections with translations requires special
      permission from their copyright holders, but you may include
      translations of some or all Invariant Sections in addition to the
      original versions of these Invariant Sections. You may include a
      translation of this License, and all the license notices in the
      Document, and any Warranty Disclaimers, provided that you also include
      the original English version of this License and the original versions
      of those notices and disclaimers. In case of a disagreement between the
      translation and the original version of this License or a notice or
      disclaimer, the original version will prevail.</para>

      <para>If a section in the Document is Entitled "Acknowledgements",
      "Dedications", or "History", the requirement (section 4) to Preserve its
      Title (section 1) will typically require changing the actual
      title.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="gfdl-9">
      <title>TERMINATION</title>

      <para>You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the Document
      except as expressly provided for under this License. Any other attempt
      to copy, modify, sublicense or distribute the Document is void, and will
      automatically terminate your rights under this License. However, parties
      who have received copies, or rights, from you under this License will
      not have their licenses terminated so long as such parties remain in
      full compliance.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="gfdl-10">
      <title>FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE</title>

      <para>The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised versions of
      the GNU Free Documentation License from time to time. Such new versions
      will be similar in spirit to the present version, but may differ in
      detail to address new problems or concerns. See
      http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/.</para>

      <para>Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version
      number. If the Document specifies that a particular numbered version of
      this License "or any later version" applies to it, you have the option
      of following the terms and conditions either of that specified version
      or of any later version that has been published (not as a draft) by the
      Free Software Foundation. If the Document does not specify a version
      number of this License, you may choose any version ever published (not
      as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="gfdl-addendum">
      <title>ADDENDUM: How to use this License for your documents</title>

      <para>To use this License in a document you have written, include a copy
      of the License in the document and put the following copyright and
      license notices just after the title page:</para>

      <blockquote id="copyright-sample">
        <title>Sample Invariant Sections list</title>

        <para>Copyright (c) YEAR YOUR NAME. Permission is granted to copy,
        distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free
        Documentation License, Version 1.2 or any later version published by
        the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no
        Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of the license is
        included in the section entitled "GNU Free Documentation
        License".</para>
      </blockquote>

      <para>If you have Invariant Sections, Front-Cover Texts and Back-Cover
      Texts, replace the "with...Texts." line with this:</para>

      <blockquote id="inv-cover-sample">
        <title>Sample Invariant Sections list</title>

        <para>with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with the
        Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being
        LIST.</para>
      </blockquote>

      <para>If you have Invariant Sections without Cover Texts, or some other
      combination of the three, merge those two alternatives to suit the
      situation.</para>

      <para>If your document contains nontrivial examples of program code, we
      recommend releasing these examples in parallel under your choice of free
      software license, such as the GNU General Public License, to permit
      their use in free software.</para>
    </section>
  </appendix>
</book>