<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>VR Juggler</title>

    <subtitle>VRJConfig Guide</subtitle>

    <releaseinfo>Version 2.0 Alpha 2</releaseinfo>

    <pubdate>$Date$</pubdate>
  </bookinfo>

  <part>
    <title>Getting Started</title>

    <preface>
      <title>Introducing VRJConfig</title>

      <para>Configuring VR software for a particular hardware system can be a
      daunting taks due to the complexity and diversity of the environments
      and hardware in use. In addition to this, many users will need to switch
      between immersive VR hardware and desktop simulators during development,
      or between one hardware system and another.</para>

      <para>VR Juggler&#39;s inherent flexibility increases this complexity.
      VR Juggler components such as displays and device drivers can be
      combined in many ways. For example, a configuration could mix simulated
      and real input devices. Or, hardware permitting, VR Juggler could use
      two separate head-mounted displays (HMDs) simultaneously. Input devices
      can be chained together, manipulated in a variety of ways, and mapped to
      different names. The possibilities are endless - but so are the
      potential pitfalls.</para>

      <para>In order to be successful, the design of VR Juggler mandated the
      need for a simple yet flexible configuration system whereby individual
      configuation elements can be easily mixed together. In such an open
      environment, resulting configuration files can become extremely complex
      making editing configurations by hand can be a tedious task in which
      making mistakes is easy. Enter VRJConfig, a GUI configuration editing
      tool designed to provide a simple, concise view of a configuration while
      helping prevent many kinds of errors.</para>

      <para>This part is provides an introduction to the basic features of the
      VRJConfig configuration editor.</para>
    </preface>

    <chapter>
      <title>The Philosophy Behind VRJConfig</title>

      <para>The design of VRJConfig has been driven by a few simple ideas in
      the hope to come up with a simplified editor for complex configurations.
      The concept of a configuration has been broken down into two parts: the
      configuration data and the definition of how that data is laid out in a
      configuration file.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Configuration Elements</title>

        <para>VRJConfig attempts to break down any complex configuration into
        a set of individual, independent configuration elements. Each element
        contains the information needed to configure a single piece of the
        software. There are many, many different types of configuration
        elements, each specialized to contain different information specific
        to the part of the software they represent.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Configuration Definitions</title>

        <para>Given a file with a list of configuration elements, how do you
        know how to interpret the data? This is where configuration
        definitions come into play. Each configuration definition defines
        exactly what properties are allowed in a given element, how to
        interpret the data contained therein, what values properties should
        default to, and general metadata describing the purpose of the
        element.</para>
      </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
      <title>Getting Started With a New Configuration</title>

      <para>In this chapter, we will carefully walk through the creation of a
      new simple configuration completely from scratch. This should give you a
      good idea of what configuration definitions and elements are in addition
      to learning how to create and edit them in the VRJConfig editor.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Creating a new configuration definition</title>

        <para></para>

        <section>
          <title>Parts of a configuration description</title>

          <para></para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>the name</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>the token</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>categories</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>help text</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>properties</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>the name</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>the token</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>the type</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>variable valued properties</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>items</para>

                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>labels</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>default values</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>enumerations</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>allowed types</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>help text</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para></para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Creating a new configuration element</title>

        <para></para>

        <section>
          <title>Parts of a configuration element</title>

          <para></para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>the name</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>editing numerical values</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>editing element pointers</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>editing embedded elements</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
      </section>
    </chapter>
  </part>
</book>
